[
  {
    "question": "The last opportunity to avoid the partition of India\nwas lost\nwith the rejection of which of the following?\n\n(a) Cripps Mission\n\n(b) Rajagopalachari formula\n\n(c) Cabinet Mission\n\n(d) Wavell Plan\nAnswer: \n(c) Cabinet Mission",
    "choices": "\n(a) Cripps Mission\n\n(b) Rajagopalachari formula\n\n(c) Cabinet Mission\n\n(d) Wavell Plan",
    "answer": "\n(c) Cabinet Mission",
    "topic": "Post-War Struggle",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_c35306__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The last opportunity to avoid the partition of India was lost with the rejection of which of the following?\n\n\na) Cripps Mission\n\nb) Rajagopalachari formula\n\nc) Cabinet Mission\n\nd) Wavell Plan",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is correct?\n\na) The\nConstituent Assembly\nof\nIndia\nwas\nelected\nby\nthe\nProvincial Assemblies in the year 1946.\n\nb)Jawaharlal Nehru, M: A. Jinnah and Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel\nwere members of the Constituent Assembly of India.\n\nc) The first session of the Constituent Assembly of India was\nheld in January 1947 .\n\nd) The Constitution of India was adopted on 26 January 1950.\nAnswer: \n(a) The Constituent Assembly of India was elected by\nthe Provincial Assemblies in the year 1946",
    "choices": "a) The\nConstituent Assembly\nof\nIndia\nwas\nelected\nby\nthe\nProvincial Assemblies in the year 1946.\n\nb)Jawaharlal Nehru, M: A. Jinnah and Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel\nwere members of the Constituent Assembly of India.\n\nc) The first session of the Constituent Assembly of India was\nheld in January 1947 .\n\nd) The Constitution of India was adopted on 26 January 1950.",
    "answer": "\n(a) The Constituent Assembly of India was elected by\nthe Provincial Assemblies in the year 1946",
    "topic": "Post-War Struggle",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_c35306__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following statements is correct?\n\n\na) The Constituent Assembly of India was elected by the Provincial Assemblies in the year 1946.\n\nb) Jawaharlal Nehru, M: A. Jinnah and Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel were members of the Constituent Assembly of India.\n\nc) The first session of the Constituent Assembly of India was held in January 1947.\n\nd) The Constitution of India was adopted on 26 January 1950.",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "The members of the constituent assembly which drafted the\nConstitution of India were\n\na) Nominated\nthe British Parliament.\n\nb)Nominated by the Governor General:\n\nc) Elected by the legislative assemblies of various provinces:\n\nd)Elected by the Indian National Congress. Muslim League:\nAnswer: \n(c) Elected by the legislative assemblies of various\nprovinces",
    "choices": "a) Nominated\nthe British Parliament.\n\nb)Nominated by the Governor General:\n\nc) Elected by the legislative assemblies of various provinces:\n\nd)Elected by the Indian National Congress. Muslim League:",
    "answer": "\n(c) Elected by the legislative assemblies of various\nprovinces",
    "topic": "Post-War Struggle",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_c35306__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The members of the constituent assembly which drafted the Constitution of India were\n\n\na) Nominated the British Parliament.\n\nb) Nominated by the Governor General:\n\nc) Elected by the legislative assemblies of various provinces:\n\nd) Elected by the Indian National Congress. Muslim League:",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which political party formally accepted the Cabinet Mission\nPlan\n6th June, 1946,\nwhich\nhad rejected the\ndemand\nfor\na\nsovereign Pakistan?\n\na) The Hindu Mahasabha\n\nb)The Congress\n\nc) The Muslim League\n\nd) The Unionist Party\nAnswer: \n(c) The Muslim League",
    "choices": "a) The Hindu Mahasabha\n\nb)The Congress\n\nc) The Muslim League\n\nd) The Unionist Party",
    "answer": "\n(c) The Muslim League",
    "topic": "Post-War Struggle",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_c35306__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which political party formally accepted the Cabinet Mission Plan 6th June, 1946, which had rejected the demand for a sovereign Pakistan?\n\n\na) The Hindu Mahasabha\n\nb) The Congress\n\nc) The Muslim League\n\nd) The Unionist Party",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "With\nreference\nto\nCabinet Mission,\nwhich\nof the following\nstatements is/are correct?\n\n1.It recommended a federal government:\n\n2.It enlarged the powers of the Indian courts.\n\n3.It provided for more Indians in the ICS.\nSelect the correct answer\nusing the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 and 3\n\nc) 1 and 3\n\nd)None of the above\nAnswer: \n(a) 1 only",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 and 3\n\nc) 1 and 3\n\nd)None of the above",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 only",
    "topic": "Post-War Struggle",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_c35306__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to Cabinet Mission, which of the following statements is/are correct?\n\n1. It recommended a federal government:\n\n2. It enlarged the powers of the Indian courts.\n\n3. It provided for more Indians in the ICS.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 and 3\n\nc) 1 and 3\n\nd) None of the above",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following suggested the reconstitution of the\nViceroy's Executive Council in which all the portfolios including\nthat of War members were to be held by the Indian leaders?\n\n(a) Simon Commission\n\n(b) Simla Conference\n\n(c) Cripps Proposal\n\n(d) Cabinet Mission\nAnswer: \n(b) Simla Conference",
    "choices": "\n(a) Simon Commission\n\n(b) Simla Conference\n\n(c) Cripps Proposal\n\n(d) Cabinet Mission",
    "answer": "\n(b) Simla Conference",
    "topic": "Post-War Struggle",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_c35306__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following suggested the reconstitution of the Viceroy's Executive Council in which all the portfolios including that of War members were to be held by the Indian leaders? \n\n\na) Simon Commission\n\nb) Simla Conference\n\nc) Cripps Proposal\n\nd) Cabinet Mission",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1. Lord\nMountbatten\nwas\nthe\nViceroy\nwhen\nthe\nSimla\nconference took place.\n\n2. Indian Navy revolt, 1946 took place when the Indian sailors\nin the Royal Indian Navy at Bombay and Karachi rose against\nthe government:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct? Choose\nthe correct answer from the following options:\n\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) Both\n1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(b) 2 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) Both\n1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 only",
    "topic": "Post-War Struggle",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_c35306__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements: \n\n\n1. Lord Mountbatten was the Viceroy when the Simla conference took place. \n\n2. Indian Navy revolt, 1946 took place when the Indian sailors in the Royal Indian Navy at Bombay and Karachi rose against the government:\n\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct? Choose the correct answer from the following options: \n\na) 1 only \n\nb) 2 only \n\nc) Both 1 and 2 \n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\nwas the brainchild of the Balkan plan for fragmentation\nof India?\n\n(a) Winston Churchill\n\n(b) M. A. Jinnah\n\n(c) Lord Mountbatten\n\n(d) V. P Menon\nAnswer: \n(c) Lord Mountbatten",
    "choices": "\n(a) Winston Churchill\n\n(b) M. A. Jinnah\n\n(c) Lord Mountbatten\n\n(d) V. P Menon",
    "answer": "\n(c) Lord Mountbatten",
    "topic": "Post-War Struggle",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_c35306__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who was the brainchild of the Balkan plan for fragmentation of India?\n\na) Winston Churchill\n\nb) M. A. Jinnah\n\nc) Lord Mountbatten\n\nd) V. P Menon",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nIn the context of Colonial India, Shah Nawaz Khan, Prem Kumar\nSehgal and Gurbaksh Singh Dhillon are remembered as\n\n(a) leaders of Swadeshi and Boycott\nMovement\n\n(b) members of the Interim Government in\n1946\n\n(c) members ofthe Drafting Committee in the Constituent\nAssembly\n\n(d) officers of the Indian National\nAnswer: \n(d) officers of the Indian National Army",
    "choices": "\n(a) leaders of Swadeshi and Boycott\nMovement\n\n(b) members of the Interim Government in\n1946\n\n(c) members ofthe Drafting Committee in the Constituent\nAssembly\n\n(d) officers of the Indian National",
    "answer": "\n(d) officers of the Indian National Army",
    "topic": "Post-War Struggle",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_c35306__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In the context of Colonial India, Shah Nawaz Khan, Prem Kumar Sehgal and Gurbaksh Singh Dhillon are remembered as\n\n\na) leaders of Swadeshi and Boycott Movement\n\nb) members of the Interim Government in 1946\n\nc) members ofthe Drafting Committee in the Constituent Assembly\n\nd) officers of the Indian National Army",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "With\nreference\nto\nIndian\nfreedom\nstruggle,\nconsider\nthe\nfollowing events:\n\n1.\nMutiny in Royal Indian Navy\n\n2. Quit India Movement launched\n\n3.Second Round Table Conference\nWhat\nis\nthe\ncorrect   chronological\nsequence\nof\nthe\nabove\nevents?\n\n(a) 1-2-3\n\n(b) 2-1-3\n3-2-1\n\n(d) 3-1-2\nAnswer: \n(c) 3-2-1",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1-2-3\n\n(b) 2-1-3\n3-2-1\n\n(d) 3-1-2",
    "answer": "\n(c) 3-2-1",
    "topic": "Post-War Struggle",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_c35306__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to Indian freedom struggle, consider the following events:\n\n\n1. Mutiny in Royal Indian Navy\n\n2. Quit India Movement launched\n\n3. Second Round Table Conference\n\nWhat is the correct chronological sequence of the above events?\n\n\na) 1-2-3\n\nb) 2-1-3\n\nc) 3-2-1\n\nd) 3-1-2",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the formation of the\nConstituent Assembly is/are correct?\n\n1. The members of the Constituent Assembly were chosen on\nthe basis of the provincial elections of 1946.\n\n2. The Constituent Assembly did\nnot include representatives\nof the Princely States.\n\n3.The discussions within the Constituent Assembly were not\ninfluenced by opinions expressed by the public.\n\n4.In\norder\nto\ncreate\na\nsense\nof\ncollective\nparticipation,\nsubmissions were solicited from the public:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 and 3\n\nc) 3 and 4\n\nd) 1 and 4\nAnswer: \n(d) 1 and 4",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 and 3\n\nc) 3 and 4\n\nd) 1 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1 and 4",
    "topic": "Post-War Struggle",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_c35306__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the formation of the Constituent Assembly is/are correct?\n\n1. The members of the Constituent Assembly were chosen on the basis of the provincial elections of 1946.\n\n2. The Constituent Assembly did not include representatives of the Princely States.\n\n3. The discussions within the Constituent Assembly were not influenced by opinions expressed by the public.\n\n4. In order to create a sense of collective participation, submissions were solicited from the public:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 and 3\n\nc) 3 and 4\n\nd) 1 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "The proposals of the Cabinet Mission did NOT include:\n\n1.a three-tier structure for the Union of India, with both the\nProvinces and the Princely States\n\n2.formation of a Constituent Assembly:\n\n3.creation of\na\nsovereign Pakistan with six Muslim-majority\nprovinces\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below :\n\na) 1 and 3\n\nb)3 only\n\nc) 2 only\n\nd) 1 and 2\nAnswer: \n(b) 3 only",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 3\n\nb)3 only\n\nc) 2 only\n\nd) 1 and 2",
    "answer": "\n(b) 3 only",
    "topic": "Post-War Struggle",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_c35306__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The proposals of the Cabinet Mission did NOT include:\n\n\n1. a three-tier structure for the Union of India, with both the Provinces and the Princely States\n\n2. formation of a Constituent Assembly:\n\n3. creation of a sovereign Pakistan with six Muslim-majority provinces\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below :\n\n\na) 1 and 3\n\nb) 3 only\n\nc) 2 only\n\nd) 1 and 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "The treaty of Yandabo was signed in\n\na)1826\n\nb) 1825\n\nc) 1824\n\nd) 1823\nAnswer: \n(a) 1826",
    "choices": "a)1826\n\nb) 1825\n\nc) 1824\n\nd) 1823",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1826",
    "topic": "British Expansion Beyond Indian Frontiers",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_d6a652__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The treaty of Yandabo was signed in \n\n\na) 1826\n\nb) 1825\n\nc) 1824\n\nd) 1823",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who believed that the Russian designs were 'an imminent peril\nto the security and tranquillity' of the Indian Empire in 1836?\n\na) Lord Auckland\n\nb)Lord Palmerston\n\nc) Lord Canning\n\nd)Alexander Burnes\nAnswer: \n(b) Lord Palmerston",
    "choices": "a) Lord Auckland\n\nb)Lord Palmerston\n\nc) Lord Canning\n\nd)Alexander Burnes",
    "answer": "\n(b) Lord Palmerston",
    "topic": "British Expansion Beyond Indian Frontiers",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_d6a652__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who believed that the Russian designs were 'an imminent peril to the security and tranquillity' of the Indian Empire in 1836? \n\n\na) Lord Auckland\n\nb) Lord Palmerston\n\nc) Lord Canning\n\nd) Alexander Burnes",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Simla was founded as a hill station to\nuse as a\nstrategic place\nfor\nbilleting\ntroops,\nguarding\nthe\nfrontier\nand\nlaunching\ncampaigns during the course of\n\n1.Anglo-Maratha War\n\n2.Anglo-Burmese War\n\n3.Anglo-Gurkha war\n\n4.Anglo-Afghan War\nAnswer: \n(c) Anglo-Gurkha war",
    "choices": "1.Anglo-Maratha War\n\n2.Anglo-Burmese War\n\n3.Anglo-Gurkha war\n\n4.Anglo-Afghan War",
    "answer": "\n(c) Anglo-Gurkha war",
    "topic": "British Expansion Beyond Indian Frontiers",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_d6a652__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Simla was founded as a hill station to use as a strategic place for billeting troops, guarding the frontier and launching campaigns during the course of\n\n\n1. Anglo-Maratha War\n\n2. Anglo-Burmese War\n\n3. Anglo-Gurkha war\n\n4. Anglo-Afghan War",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following\nof years and historical events is\ncorrectly matched?\n\na) 1878: Second Anglo-Afghan War\n\nb)1885: Ilbert Bill Controversy\n\nc) 1785: Fox's India Bill\n\nd)1898: Lord Curzon becomes the Viceroy\nAnswer: \n(a) 1878: Second Anglo-Afghan War",
    "choices": "a) 1878: Second Anglo-Afghan War\n\nb)1885: Ilbert Bill Controversy\n\nc) 1785: Fox's India Bill\n\nd)1898: Lord Curzon becomes the Viceroy",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1878: Second Anglo-Afghan War",
    "topic": "British Expansion Beyond Indian Frontiers",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_d6a652__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following of years and historical events is correctly matched?\n\n\na) 1878: Second Anglo-Afghan War\n\nb) 1885: Ilbert Bill Controversy\n\nc) 1785: Fox's India Bill\n\nd) 1898: Lord Curzon becomes the Viceroy",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Treaty of Yandabo was concluded as part of which one of\nthe following wars?\n\na) First Anglo-Burmese War\n\nb)Second Anglo-Burmese War\nCi\nAnglo-Kuki War\n\nd)Anglo-Maratha War\nAnswer: \n(a) First Anglo-Burmese War",
    "choices": "a) First Anglo-Burmese War\n\nb)Second Anglo-Burmese War\nCi\nAnglo-Kuki War\n\nd)Anglo-Maratha War",
    "answer": "\n(a) First Anglo-Burmese War",
    "topic": "British Expansion Beyond Indian Frontiers",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_d6a652__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Treaty of Yandabo was concluded as part of which one of the following wars? \n\n\na) First Anglo-Burmese War\n\nb) Second Anglo-Burmese War\n\nc) Anglo-Kuki War\n\nd) Anglo-Maratha War",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nThe British policy towards Afghanistan in the first half of the\ncentury aimed at\n\na) Strengthening Afghanistan as a buffer against Russia:\n\nb) Weakening\nRussian\ninfluence\nin\nAfghanistan\nbut\nnot\npromoting a strong Afghanistan either\n\nc) Promoting\nRussian\ninfluence\nin\nAfghanistan\nto\ncontrol\ninsurgent tribal leaders:\n\nd)Annexing\nAfghanistan\nas\na\ndirectly\ncontrolled\nBritish\nTerritory:\nAnswer: \n(b) Weakening Russian influence in Afghanistan but\nnot promoting a strong Afghanistan either",
    "choices": "a) Strengthening Afghanistan as a buffer against Russia:\n\nb) Weakening\nRussian\ninfluence\nin\nAfghanistan\nbut\nnot\npromoting a strong Afghanistan either\n\nc) Promoting\nRussian\ninfluence\nin\nAfghanistan\nto\ncontrol\ninsurgent tribal leaders:\n\nd)Annexing\nAfghanistan\nas\na\ndirectly\ncontrolled\nBritish\nTerritory:",
    "answer": "\n(b) Weakening Russian influence in Afghanistan but\nnot promoting a strong Afghanistan either",
    "topic": "British Expansion Beyond Indian Frontiers",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_d6a652__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The British policy towards Afghanistan in the first half of the century aimed at \n\n\na) Strengthening Afghanistan as a buffer against Russia: \n\nb) Weakening Russian influence in Afghanistan but not promoting a strong Afghanistan either\n\nc) Promoting Russian influence in Afghanistan to control insurgent tribal leaders: \n\nd) Annexing Afghanistan as a directly controlled British Territory:",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the Hastings Plan of 1772 is/are correct?\n\n1. Each district was to have a civil and a criminal Court;\n\n2. The Judges were helped by native assessors who were skilled in Hindu and Islamic laws.\n\n3.The Sadar Diwani Adalat was mainly meant to settle mercantile cases exceeding Rs. 10,000 in value:\n\n4.These Courts did not put into place any procedural improvements.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 2\n\nb)3 and 4\n\nc) 2 and 4\n\nd) 2 only",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 2\n\nb)3 and 4\n\nc) 2 and 4\n\nd) 2 only",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 and 2",
    "topic": "British Administration in India - part one",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0593ef__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the Hastings Plan of 1772 is/are correct?\n\n1. Each district was to have a civil and a criminal Court;\n\n2. The Judges were helped by native assessors who were skilled in Hindu and Islamic laws.\n\n3. The Sadar Diwani Adalat was mainly meant to settle mercantile cases exceeding Rs. 10,000 in value:\n\n4. These Courts did not put into place any procedural improvements.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 2\n\nb) 3 and 4\n\nc) 2 and 4\n\nd) 2 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "[UPSC CSE 2010] By a regulation in 1793, the District Collector was deprived of his judicial powers and made the collecting agent only: What was the reason for such regulation?\n\n(a) Lord Cornwallis felt that the District Collector's efficiency of revenue collection would enormously increase without the burden of other work:\n\n(b) Lord Cornwallis felt that judicial power should compulsorily be in the hands of Europeans while Indians could be given the job of revenue collection in the district\n\n(c) Lord Cornwallis was alarmed at the extent of power concentrated in the District Collector and felt that such absolute power was undesirable in one person:\n\n(d) Judicial work demanded a deep knowledge of India and good training in and Lord Cornwallis felt that the District Collector should be only a revenue collector: ",
    "choices": "\n(a) Lord Cornwallis felt that the District Collector's efficiency of revenue collection would enormously increase without the burden of other work:\n\n(b) Lord Cornwallis felt that judicial power should compulsorily be in the hands of Europeans while Indians could be given the job of revenue collection in the district\n\n(c) Lord Cornwallis was alarmed at the extent of power concentrated in the District Collector and felt that such absolute power was undesirable in one person:\n\n(d) Judicial work demanded a deep knowledge of India and good training in and Lord Cornwallis felt that the District Collector should be only a revenue collector: ",
    "answer": "\n(c) Lord Cornwallis was alarmed at the extent of power concentrated in the District Collector and felt that such absolute power was undesirable in one person",
    "topic": "British Administration in India - part one",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0593ef__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "[UPSC CSE 2010] By a regulation in 1793, the District Collector was deprived of his judicial powers and made the collecting agent only: What was the reason for such regulation? \n\n\na) Lord Cornwallis felt that the District Collector's efficiency of revenue collection would enormously increase without the burden of other work:\n\nb) Lord Cornwallis felt that judicial power should compulsorily be in the hands of Europeans while Indians could be given the job of revenue collection in the district\n\nc) Lord Cornwallis was alarmed at the extent of power concentrated in the District Collector and felt that such absolute power was undesirable in one person:\n\nd) Judicial work demanded a deep knowledge of India and good training in and Lord Cornwallis felt that the District Collector should be only a revenue collector:",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "The College of Fort William\nwas established by which one of\nthe following Governors-General?\n\na) Warren Hastings\n\nb)Lord Cornwallis\n\nc) Richard Wellesley\n\nd) William Bentinck:",
    "choices": "a) Warren Hastings\n\nb)Lord Cornwallis\n\nc) Richard Wellesley\n\nd) William Bentinck:",
    "answer": "\n(c) Richard Wellesley",
    "topic": "British Administration in India - part one",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0593ef__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The College of Fort William was established by which one of the following Governors-General? \n\na) Warren Hastings\n\nb) Lord Cornwallis\n\nc) Richard Wellesley\n\nd) William Bentinck:",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "British Administration in India - part one\n\nWellesley established the Fort William College Calcutta because\n\n(a) He was asked by the Board of Directors at London to do SO\n\n(b) He wanted to revive interest in oriental learning in India\n\n(c) He wanted to provide William Carey and his associates with employment\n\n(d) He wanted to train British civilians for administrative purpose in India\nAnswer: ",
    "choices": "\n(a) He was asked by the Board of Directors at London to do SO\n\n(b) He wanted to revive interest in oriental learning in India\n\n(c) He wanted to provide William Carey and his associates with employment\n\n(d) He wanted to train British civilians for administrative purpose in India",
    "answer": "\n(d) He wanted to train British civilians for administrative purpose in India",
    "topic": "British Administration in India - part one",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0593ef__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "British Administration in India - part one\n\nWellesley established the Fort William College Calcutta because\n\n\na) He was asked by the Board of Directors at London to do SO\n\nb) He wanted to revive interest in oriental learning in India\n\nc) He wanted to provide William Carey and his associates with employment\n\nd) He wanted to train British civilians for administrative purpose in India",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the Viceroy of India at the time of Gandhiji's Dandi march?",
    "choices": "a) Lord Irwin\n\nb)Lord Linlithgow\n\nc) Lord\nReading\n\nd)Lord Willingdon",
    "answer": "\n(a) Lord Irwin",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who was the Viceroy of India at the time of Gandhiji's Dandi march?",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one among the following American newsmagazines was\nhighly sceptical of Gandhiji's Dandi march initially but within a\nweek completely changed its opinion and saluted\nhim\nas\na\nSaint and Statesman?",
    "choices": "a) Saturday Evening Post\n\nb)Readers Digest\n\nc) Time\n\nd) Life",
    "answer": "\n(c) Time",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one among the following American newsmagazines was highly sceptical of Gandhiji's Dandi march initially but within a week completely changed its opinion and saluted him as a Saint and Statesman?",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding the British colonial rule in India, consider\nthe following statements:\n\n1. Mahatma Gandhi was instrumental in the abolition of the system of 'indentured labour'.\n\n2.In Lord Chelmsford's 'War Conference' , Mahatma Gandhi did not support the resolution on recruiting Indians for World War:\n\n3.Consequent upon the breaking of Salt Law by Indian\npeople, the Indian National Congress was declared illegal by\nthe colonial rulers.\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\n\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 1 and 3 only\n\n(c) 2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 1 and 3 only\n\n(c) 2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(b) 1 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Regarding the British colonial rule in India, consider the following statements:\n\n\n1. Mahatma Gandhi was instrumental in the abolition of the system of 'indentured labour'.\n\n2. In Lord Chelmsford's 'War Conference', Mahatma Gandhi did not support the resolution on recruiting Indians for World War:\n\n3. Consequent upon the breaking of Salt Law by Indian people, the Indian National Congress was declared illegal by the colonial rulers.\n\nWhich of the statements given above are correct? \n\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb) 1 and 3 only\n\nc) 2 and 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements about the Gandhi-Irwin\nPact is NOT correct?\n\na) Gandhi wrote a letter seeking an interview with the Viceroy\n\nb) The Civil Disobedience movement was to be discontinued\n\nc) The imprisoned freedom fighters were to be released\n\nd)AII the lands that had been confiscated were to be returned\nto the original owner",
    "choices": "a) Gandhi wrote a letter seeking an interview with the Viceroy\n\nb) The Civil Disobedience movement was to be discontinued\n\nc) The imprisoned freedom fighters were to be released\n\nd)AII the lands that had been confiscated were to be returned\nto the original owner",
    "answer": "\n(d) All the lands that had been confiscated were to be\nreturned to the original owners",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following statements about the Gandhi-Irwin Pact is NOT correct?\n\n\na) Gandhi wrote a letter seeking an interview with the Viceroy\n\nb) The Civil Disobedience movement was to be discontinued\n\nc) The imprisoned freedom fighters were to be released\n\nd) All the lands that had been confiscated were to be returned to the original owner",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)\nWith reference to Indian freedom struggle, which\none of the\nfollowing statements is not correct?\n\n(a)The Rowlatt Act aroused a wave of popular Indian on and\nled to the Jallianwala Bagh massacre:\n\n(b)Subhash Chandra Bose formed the Forward Bloc.\n\n(c)Bhagat Singh was one of the founders of Hindustan Republican Socialist Association.\n\n(d) In 1931, the congress session at Karachi opposed Gandhi\nIrwin pact:",
    "choices": "\n(a)The Rowlatt Act aroused a wave of popular Indian on and\nled to the Jallianwala Bagh massacre:\n\n(b)Subhash Chandra Bose formed the Forward Bloc.\n\n(c)Bhagat Singh was one of the founders of Hindustan Republican Socialist Association.\n\n(d) In 1931, the congress session at Karachi opposed Gandhi\nIrwin pact:",
    "answer": "\n(d) In 1931, the congress session at Karachi opposed\nGandhi Irwin pact",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)\nWith reference to Indian freedom struggle, which one of the following statements is not correct?\n\n\na) The Rowlatt Act aroused a wave of popular Indian on and led to the Jallianwala Bagh massacre:\n\nb) Subhash Chandra Bose formed the Forward Bloc.\n\nc) Bhagat Singh was one of the founders of Hindustan Republican Socialist Association.\n\nd) In 1931, the congress session at Karachi opposed Gandhi Irwin pact:",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\none\nof the following is\nNOT correct about Mahatma\nGandhi's Dandi Yatra or Salt March?\n\na) It was the first national activity in which women participated in large numbers\n\nb)Gandhiji allowed the women's participation at the request\nof Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay\n\nc) The march was fully covered by the Western press\n\nd) The march began after the failure of the First Round Table\nConference",
    "choices": "a) It was the first national activity in which women participated in large numbers\n\nb)Gandhiji allowed the women's participation at the request\nof Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay\n\nc) The march was fully covered by the Western press\n\nd) The march began after the failure of the First Round Table\nConference",
    "answer": "\n(d)",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following is NOT correct about Mahatma Gandhi's Dandi Yatra or Salt March?\n\n\na) It was the first national activity in which women participated in large numbers.\n\nb) Gandhiji allowed the women's participation at the request of Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay.\n\nc) The march was fully covered by the Western press.\n\nd) The march began after the failure of the First Round Table Conference.",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "The march began after the failure of the First Round Table Conference At which Congress Session was the Working Committee authorised to launch a programme of Civil Disobedience?\n\n(a) Bombay\n\n(b) Lahore\n\n(c)Lucknow\n\n(d) Tripuri",
    "choices": "\n(a) Bombay\n\n(b) Lahore\n\n(c)Lucknow\n\n(d) Tripuri",
    "answer": "\n(b) Lahore",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The march began after the failure of the First Round Table Conference. At which Congress Session was the Working Committee authorised to launch a programme of Civil Disobedience? \n\na) Bombay\n\nb) Lahore\n\nc) Lucknow\n\nd) Tripuri",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which Viceroy had observed; \"It's a beautiful world if it wasn't\nfor Gandhi\n? \n\na) Lord Irwin\n\nb)Lord Wavell\n\nc) Lord Mountbatten\n\nd)Lord Willingdon",
    "choices": "a) Lord Irwin\n\nb)Lord Wavell\n\nc) Lord Mountbatten\n\nd)Lord Willingdon",
    "answer": "\n(d) Lord Willingdon",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which Viceroy had observed; \"It's a beautiful world if it wasn't for Gandhi?\n\n\na) Lord Irwin\n\nb) Lord Wavell\n\nc) Lord Mountbatten\n\nd) Lord Willingdon",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one among the following was demanded by the AIl India\nDepressed Classes Leaders\nConference at Bombay in 1931?\n\na) Universal adult suffrage\n\nb)Separate electorates for untouchables\n\nc) Reserved seats for the minorities\n\nd)A unitary State in India",
    "choices": "a) Universal adult suffrage\n\nb)Separate electorates for untouchables\n\nc) Reserved seats for the minorities\n\nd)A unitary State in India",
    "answer": "\n(b) Separate electorates for untouchables",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one among the following was demanded by the AIl India Depressed Classes Leaders Conference at Bombay in 1931?\n\n\na) Universal adult suffrage\n\nb) Separate electorates for untouchables\n\nc) Reserved seats for the minorities\n\nd) A unitary State in India",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following drafted the resolution on Fundamental Rights for the Karachi session of Congress in 1931?\n\n(a) Dr B. R Ambedkar\n\n(b) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n(c) Dr Rajendra Prasad\n\n(d) Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
    "choices": "\n(a) Dr B. R Ambedkar\n\n(b) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n(c) Dr Rajendra Prasad\n\n(d) Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
    "answer": "\n(b) Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following drafted the resolution on Fundamental Rights for the Karachi session of Congress in 1931?\n\n\na) Dr B. R Ambedkar\n\nb) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\nc) Dr Rajendra Prasad\n\nd) Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements about the Gandhi-Irwin\nPact of 1931 is correct?\n\na) The Government would\nnot release those prisoners\nwho\nhad been non-violent:\n\nb) The Government would\nnot release those prisoners\nwho\nhad indulged in the peaceful picketing of liquor and foreign\ncloth shops:\n\nc) The Congress did not agree to the suspension of the Civil\nDisobedience Movement:\n\nd) The Congress agreed to take part in the Second Round Table\nConference.",
    "choices": "a) The Government would\nnot release those prisoners\nwho\nhad been non-violent:\n\nb) The Government would\nnot release those prisoners\nwho\nhad indulged in the peaceful picketing of liquor and foreign\ncloth shops:\n\nc) The Congress did not agree to the suspension of the Civil\nDisobedience Movement:\n\nd) The Congress agreed to take part in the Second Round Table\nConference.",
    "answer": "\n(d) The Congress agreed to take part in the Second\nRound Table Conference",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following statements about the Gandhi-Irwin Pact of 1931 is correct?\n\na) The Government would not release those prisoners who had been non-violent:\n\nb) The Government would not release those prisoners who had indulged in the peaceful picketing of liquor and foreign cloth shops:\n\nc) The Congress did not agree to the suspension of the Civil Disobedience Movement:\n\nd) The Congress agreed to take part in the Second Round Table Conference.",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements about the Salt March:\n\n1. The Salt March\nwas deliberately ignored\nthe European\nmedia.\n\n2. The Salt March\nwas\nwidely covered by the\nAmerican and\nEuropean press.\n\n3.The Salt March\nwas the first nationalist activity in\nwhich\nwomen\nparticipated in large numbers.\n\n4. The Salt March impressed upon the British the urgent need\nto devolve more power to Indians:\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\n\na) 1,2 and 4\n\nb)2,3 and 4\n\nc) 3 and 4 only\n\nd)2 and 3 only",
    "choices": "a) 1,2 and 4\n\nb)2,3 and 4\n\nc) 3 and 4 only\n\nd)2 and 3 only",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2, 3 and 4",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements about the Salt March:\n\n\n1. The Salt March was deliberately ignored the European media.\n\n2. The Salt March was widely covered by the American and European press.\n\n3. The Salt March was the first nationalist activity in which women participated in large numbers.\n\n4. The Salt March impressed upon the British the urgent need to devolve more power to Indians:\n\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\n\n\na) 1,2 and 4\n\nb) 2,3 and 4\n\nc) 3 and 4 only\n\nd) 2 and 3 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which among the following\nwas\nNOT the provision\nof the\nGandhi-Irwin pact?\n\na) Immediate\nrelease\nof\nall political  prisoners\nof the\nCivil\nDisobedience. Movement\n\nb)Clause 2 of the March 1931 pact defined 'reservations and\nsafe- guards to cover financial credit of India\n\nc) The return of confiscated land already sold to third parties\n\nd)Reservation of 18 per cent seats for Depressed classes",
    "choices": "a) Immediate\nrelease\nof\nall political  prisoners\nof the\nCivil\nDisobedience. Movement\n\nb)Clause 2 of the March 1931 pact defined 'reservations and\nsafe- guards to cover financial credit of India\n\nc) The return of confiscated land already sold to third parties\n\nd)Reservation of 18 per cent seats for Depressed classes",
    "answer": "\n(d) Reservation of 18 per cent seats for Depressed\nclasses",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which among the following was NOT the provision of the Gandhi-Irwin pact?\n\n\na) Immediate release of all political prisoners of the Civil Disobedience. Movement\n\nb) Clause 2 of the March 1931 pact defined 'reservations and safe- guards to cover financial credit of India\n\nc) The return of confiscated land already sold to third parties\n\nd) Reservation of 18 per cent seats for Depressed classes",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which one of the following Sessions of the Indian National\nCongress\nwas\nthe\nresolution\non\nFundamental\nRights\nand\nEconomic Policy passed?\n\na) Tripuri Session\n\nb)Lahore Session\n\nc) Lucknow Session\n\nd) Karachi Session",
    "choices": "a) Tripuri Session\n\nb)Lahore Session\n\nc) Lucknow Session\n\nd) Karachi Session",
    "answer": "\n(d) Karachi Session",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "At which one of the following Sessions of the Indian National Congress was the resolution on Fundamental Rights and Economic Policy passed?\n\n\na) Tripuri Session\n\nb) Lahore Session\n\nc) Lucknow Session\n\nd) Karachi Session",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Khudai Khidmatgar (Servants of the God) was organised by\n\na) Mahatma Gandhi\n\nb)Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan\n\nc) M: A. Jinnah\n\nd)M: M. Malaviya",
    "choices": "a) Mahatma Gandhi\n\nb)Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan\n\nc) M: A. Jinnah\n\nd)M: M. Malaviya",
    "answer": "\n(b) Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Khudai Khidmatgar (Servants of the God) was organised by\n\na) Mahatma Gandhi\n\nb) Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan\n\nc) M: A. Jinnah\n\nd) M: M. Malaviya",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who of the\nfollowing organised a march on the Tanjore coast\nto break the Salt Law in April 1930?\n\n(a) V.O Chidambaram Pillai\n\n(b) C. Rajagopalachari\nK. Kamaraj\n\n(d) Annie Besant",
    "choices": "\n(a) V.O Chidambaram Pillai\n\n(b) C. Rajagopalachari\nK. Kamaraj\n\n(d) Annie Besant",
    "answer": "\n(b) C Rajagopalachari",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who of the following organised a march on the Tanjore coast to break the Salt Law in April 1930? \n\n\na) V.O Chidambaram Pillai\n\nb) C. Rajagopalachari \nK. Kamaraj\n\nd) Annie Besant",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why did Mahatma Gandhi undertake the fast unto death in\n1932.\n\n(a) Round table conference failed to satisfy Indian political\naspirations\n\n(b) Congress\nand\nthe\nMuslim\nLeague\nhad\ndifferences\nof\nopinion\n\n(c) Ramsay MacDonald announced the Communal Award\n\n(d) None of the statements \n(a), \n(b) and \n(c) given above is\ncorrect in this context.",
    "choices": "\n(a) Round table conference failed to satisfy Indian political\naspirations\n\n(b) Congress\nand\nthe\nMuslim\nLeague\nhad\ndifferences\nof\nopinion\n\n(c) Ramsay MacDonald announced the Communal Award\n\n(d) None of the statements \n(a), \n(b) and \n(c) given above is\ncorrect in this context.",
    "answer": "\n(c) Ramsay",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Why did Mahatma Gandhi undertake the fast unto death in 1932.\n\n\na) Round table conference failed to satisfy Indian political aspirations\n\nb) Congress and the Muslim League had differences of opinion\n\nc) Ramsay MacDonald announced the Communal Award\n\nd) None of the statements \n(a), \n(b) and \n(c) given above is correct in this context.",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "MacDonald announced\nthe\nCommunal\nAward\nConsider the following statements:\n\n1.In the first Round Table Conference, Dr Ambedkar demanded separate electorates for the depressed classes:\n\n2.In the Poona Pact, special provisions for representation of the depressed class people in the local bodies and civil services were made\n\n3. The Indian National Congress did not take part in the Third Round Table Conference,\nWhich of the statements given above are correct? Choose the\ncorrect answer from the following options:\n\n(a) Iand 2\n\n(b) 2 and 3\n\n(c) 1and 3\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "choices": "\n(a) Iand 2\n\n(b) 2 and 3\n\n(c) 1and 3\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(c) 1 and 3",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "MacDonald announced the Communal Award\n\nConsider the following statements:\n\n\n1. In the first Round Table Conference, Dr Ambedkar demanded separate electorates for the depressed classes:\n\n2. In the Poona Pact, special provisions for representation of the depressed class people in the local bodies and civil services were made\n\n3. The Indian National Congress did not take part in the Third Round Table Conference\n\nWhich of the statements given above are correct? Choose the correct answer from the following options:\n\n\na) Iand 2\n\nb) 2 and 3\n\nc) 1and 3\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "For the Karachi session of the Indian National Congress in 1931,\npresided over by Sardar Patel, who drafted the resolution on\nthe Fundamental Rights and Economics Programme?\n\n(a) Mahatma Gandhi\n\n(b) Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n(c) Dr Rajendra Prasad\n\n(d) Dr B. R. Ambedkar",
    "choices": "\n(a) Mahatma Gandhi\n\n(b) Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n(c) Dr Rajendra Prasad\n\n(d) Dr B. R. Ambedkar",
    "answer": "\n(b) Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "For the Karachi session of the Indian National Congress in 1931, presided over by Sardar Patel, who drafted the resolution on the Fundamental Rights and Economics Programme? \n\na) Mahatma Gandhi \n\nb) Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru \n\nc) Dr Rajendra Prasad \n\nd) Dr B. R. Ambedkar",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following began with the Dandi March?\n\n(a) Home Rule Movement\n\n(b) Non-Cooperation Movement\n\n(c) Civil Disobedience Movement\n\n(d) Quit India Movement",
    "choices": "\n(a) Home Rule Movement\n\n(b) Non-Cooperation Movement\n\n(c) Civil Disobedience Movement\n\n(d) Quit India Movement",
    "answer": "\n(c) Civil Disobedience Movement",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following began with the Dandi March?\n\na) Home Rule Movement\n\nb) Non-Cooperation Movement\n\nc) Civil Disobedience Movement\n\nd) Quit India Movement",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following socialist activists persuaded Gandhiji not to restrict the salt march protest to men alone?\n\na) Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay\n\nb)Sarojini Naidu\n\nc) Matangini Hazra\n\nd)Mithuben Petit",
    "choices": "a) Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay\n\nb)Sarojini Naidu\n\nc) Matangini Hazra\n\nd)Mithuben Petit",
    "answer": "\n(a) Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following socialist activists persuaded Gandhiji not to restrict the salt march protest to men alone?\n\na) Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay\n\nb) Sarojini Naidu\n\nc) Matangini Hazra\n\nd) Mithuben Petit",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about Mahatma Gandhi's\nanti-untouchability campaign is/are correct?\n\n1. The\nAll\nIndia Harijan\nSevak Sangh\nwas founded\nfor this\npurpose:\n\n2. The campaign\nwas to root out\nuntouchability, since it did\nnot enjoy the sanction of the Hindu shastras:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about Mahatma Gandhi's anti-untouchability campaign is/are correct?\n\n\n1. The All India Harijan Sevak Sangh was founded for this purpose:\n\n2. The campaign was to root out untouchability, since it did not enjoy the sanction of the Hindu shastras:\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1. The discussions in the Third Round Table Conference eventually led to the passing ofthe Government of India Act of 1935.\n\n2. The Government of India Act of 1935 provided for the establishment of an all-India Federation to be based on the Union of the provinces of British India and the Princely States.\nWhich of the statement(s) given above is are correct? Choose\nthe correct answer from the following options:\n\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) Both 1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) Both 1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n\n1. The discussions in the Third Round Table Conference eventually led to the passing ofthe Government of India Act of 1935.\n\n\n2. The Government of India Act of 1935 provided for the establishment of an all-India Federation to be based on the Union of the provinces of British India and the Princely States.\n\nWhich of the statement(s) given above is are correct? Choose the correct answer from the following options:\n\n\na) 1 only\n\n\nb) 2 only\n\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following question consists of statements: Statement I and Statement IL: Examine these two statements  carefully and select the correct answer using the code below:\nCode:\n\na) Both statements are individually true, and Statement Il is the\ncorrect explanation of Statement\n\nb)Both statements are individually true, but Statement Il is not\nthe correct explanation of Statement | \nC\nStatement\nis true, but Statement Il is false\n\nd)Statement | is false, but Statement Il is true.\nStatement  : Mahatma Gandhi went on a fast unto death against\nthe Communal Award announced by the British Government:\nStatement I: The Poona Pact resulted in a joint electorate with\nan enhanced number of seats reserved for Depressed Classes:",
    "choices": "a) Both statements are individually true, and Statement Il is the\ncorrect explanation of Statement\n\nb)Both statements are individually true, but Statement Il is not\nthe correct explanation of Statement | \nC\nStatement\nis true, but Statement Il is false\n\nd)Statement | is false, but Statement Il is true.",
    "answer": "\n(a) Both\nstatements\nare\nindividually\ntrue,\nand\nStatement II is the correct explanation of Statement 1",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_01fe74__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The following question consists of statements: Statement I and Statement IL: Examine these two statements carefully and select the correct answer using the code below:\n\nCode:\n\n\na) Both statements are individually true, and Statement Il is the correct explanation of Statement\n\nb) Both statements are individually true, but Statement Il is not the correct explanation of Statement | \n\nc) Statement is true, but Statement Il is false\n\nd) Statement | is false, but Statement Il is true.\nStatement : Mahatma Gandhi went on a fast unto death against the Communal Award announced by the British Government:\nStatement I: The Poona Pact resulted in a joint electorate with an enhanced number of seats reserved for Depressed Classes:",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following was/were connected primarily to the communist ideology?\n\n1. Kirti Kisan Party\n\n2. Labour Swaraj Party\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below :\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "Growth of Left",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5db9ef__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following was/were connected primarily to the communist ideology?\n\n\n1. Kirti Kisan Party\n\n2. Labour Swaraj Party\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below :\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1. The growth of socialist tendency in the national movement led to the foundation of the Congress Socialist Party in 1934 under the leadership of Acharya Narendra Deva and Jayaprakash Narayan:\n\n2.In 1936, Jawaharlal Nehru urged the Congress to accept socialism as its goal and to bring itself closer to the peasantry and the working class.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n6)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n6)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "Growth of Left",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5db9ef__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1. The growth of socialist tendency in the national movement led to the foundation of the Congress Socialist Party in 1934 under the leadership of Acharya Narendra Deva and Jayaprakash Narayan:\n\n2. In 1936, Jawaharlal Nehru urged the Congress to accept socialism as its goal and to bring itself closer to the peasantry and the working class.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the Dutt-Bradley thesis?\n\na) The Working Committee of the Indian National Congress decided that Congress should play a crucial role in realising the independence of India:\n\nb) The Socialist party decided to play foremost part in anti-imperialist struggle\n\nc) Revolutionary socialist Batukeshwar Dutt put forth a ten-point plan to work: for the success of anti-imperialist front\n\nd)It was a Communist party document, according to which the National Congress could play a great part and a foremost part in realising the anti-imperialist people's front\nAnswer: \n(d) It was a Communist party document, according to which the National Congress could play a great part and a foremost in realising the anti-imperialist people's front part",
    "choices": "a) The Working Committee of the Indian National Congress decided that Congress should play a crucial role in realising the independence of India:\n\nb) The Socialist party decided to play foremost part in anti-imperialist struggle\n\nc) Revolutionary socialist Batukeshwar Dutt put forth a ten-point plan to work: for the success of anti-imperialist front\n\nd)It was a Communist party document, according to which the National Congress could play a great part and a foremost part in realising the anti-imperialist people's front",
    "answer": "\n(d) It was a Communist party document, according to which the National Congress could play a great part and a foremost in realising the anti-imperialist people's front part",
    "topic": "Growth of Left",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5db9ef__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "What was the Dutt-Bradley thesis?\n\n\na) The Working Committee of the Indian National Congress decided that Congress should play a crucial role in realising the independence of India:\n\nb) The Socialist party decided to play foremost part in anti-imperialist struggle\n\nc) Revolutionary socialist Batukeshwar Dutt put forth a ten-point plan to work: for the success of anti-imperialist front\n\nd) It was a Communist party document, according to which the National Congress could play a great part and a foremost part in realising the anti-imperialist people's front",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "The concept of a Four Pillar State\" free from district magistracy for India, was suggested by\n\na) Lala Lajpat Rai\n\nb)Ram Manohar Lohia\n\nc) Raja Ram Mohan\n\nd)Subash Chandra Bose\nAnswer: \n(b) Ram Manohar Lohia",
    "choices": "a) Lala Lajpat Rai\n\nb)Ram Manohar Lohia\n\nc) Raja Ram Mohan\n\nd)Subash Chandra Bose",
    "answer": "\n(b) Ram Manohar Lohia",
    "topic": "Growth of Left",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5db9ef__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The concept of a \"Four Pillar State\" free from district magistracy for India, was suggested by\n\n\na) Lala Lajpat Rai\n\nb) Ram Manohar Lohia\n\nc) Raja Ram Mohan\n\nd) Subash Chandra Bose",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "socialist idea of Sapta Kranti (Seven Revolutions) was proposed by\n\na) Ram Manohar Lohia\n\nb)Jawaharlal Nehru\n\nc) M. G. Ranade\n\nd)Jayaprakash Narayan\nAnswer: \n(a) Ram Manohar Lohia",
    "choices": "a) Ram Manohar Lohia\n\nb)Jawaharlal Nehru\n\nc) M. G. Ranade\n\nd)Jayaprakash Narayan",
    "answer": "\n(a) Ram Manohar Lohia",
    "topic": "Growth of Left",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5db9ef__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "socialist idea of Sapta Kranti (Seven Revolutions) was proposed by\n\n\na) Ram Manohar Lohia\n\nb) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\nc) M. G. Ranade\n\nd) Jayaprakash Narayan",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to the Congress Socialist Party, consider the following statements:\n\n1.It advocated the boycott of British goods and evasion of taxes.\n\n2.It wanted to establish the dictatorship of the proletariat.\n\n3.It advocated separate electorate for minorities and oppressed classes.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 3 only\n1, 2 and 3\n\n(d) None of the above\nAnswer: \n(d) None of the above",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 3 only\n1, 2 and 3\n\n(d) None of the above",
    "answer": "\n(d) None of the above",
    "topic": "Growth of Left",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5db9ef__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to the Congress Socialist Party, consider the following statements: \n\n\n1.It advocated the boycott of British goods and evasion of taxes. \n\n\n2.It wanted to establish the dictatorship of the proletariat. \n\n\n3.It advocated separate electorate for minorities and oppressed classes. \n\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct? \n\n\n(a) 1 and 2 only \n\n\n(b) 3 only  \n\n1, 2 and 3 \n\n\n(d) None of the above",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following were jailed in the Kanpur Bolshevik conspiracy case in 1924?\n\na) Muzaffar Ahmad, S.A. Dange, Shaukat Usmani, Nalini Gupta\n\nb)Muhammad Ali and Shaukat Usmani\n\nc) S. A. Dange and S. V. Ghate\n\nd) Muzaffar Ahmad and S. S. Mirajkar\nAnswer: \n(a) Muzaffar Ahmad, S. A. Dange, Shaukat Usmani, Nalini Gupta",
    "choices": "a) Muzaffar Ahmad, S.A. Dange, Shaukat Usmani, Nalini Gupta\n\nb)Muhammad Ali and Shaukat Usmani\n\nc) S. A. Dange and S. V. Ghate\n\nd) Muzaffar Ahmad and S. S. Mirajkar",
    "answer": "\n(a) Muzaffar Ahmad, S. A. Dange, Shaukat Usmani, Nalini Gupta",
    "topic": "Growth of Left",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5db9ef__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following were jailed in the Kanpur Bolshevik conspiracy case in 1924?\n\n\na) Muzaffar Ahmad, S.A. Dange, Shaukat Usmani, Nalini Gupta\n\nb) Muhammad Ali and Shaukat Usmani\n\nc) S. A. Dange and S. V. Ghate\n\nd) Muzaffar Ahmad and S. S. Mirajkar",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following pairs of organization and their founders is NOT correctly matched?\n\na) National Liberation Federation: Tej Bahadur Sapru and M. R; Jayakar\n\nb)Jamiat-ul Ulama-i Hind: Maulana Mahmudal Hasan Shaikh-ul-Hind\n\nc) Congress Democratic Party: B. G. Tilak\n\nd) Congress Socialist Party: M. N. Roy\nAnswer: \n(d) Congress Socialist Party: M. N. Roy",
    "choices": "a) National Liberation Federation: Tej Bahadur Sapru and M. R; Jayakar\n\nb)Jamiat-ul Ulama-i Hind: Maulana Mahmudal Hasan Shaikh-ul-Hind\n\nc) Congress Democratic Party: B. G. Tilak\n\nd) Congress Socialist Party: M. N. Roy",
    "answer": "\n(d) Congress Socialist Party: M. N. Roy",
    "topic": "Growth of Left",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5db9ef__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following pairs of organization and their founders is NOT correctly matched?\n\n\na) National Liberation Federation: Tej Bahadur Sapru and M. R; Jayakar\n\nb) Jamiat-ul Ulama-i Hind: Maulana Mahmudal Hasan Shaikh-ul-Hind\n\nc) Congress Democratic Party: B. G. Tilak\n\nd) Congress Socialist Party: M. N. Roy",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following in Congress represented the socialist view?\n\na) Rajendra Prasad\n\nb)Narendra Dev\n\nc) Maulana Azad\n\nd)Sardar Patel\nAnswer: \n(b) Narendra Dev",
    "choices": "a) Rajendra Prasad\n\nb)Narendra Dev\n\nc) Maulana Azad\n\nd)Sardar Patel",
    "answer": "\n(b) Narendra Dev",
    "topic": "Growth of Left",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5db9ef__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following in Congress represented the socialist view?\n\n\na) Rajendra Prasad\n\n\nb) Narendra Dev\n\n\nc) Maulana Azad\n\n\nd) Sardar Patel\n",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about India's Independence is/are correct?\n\n1. The\nformal\ntransfer\nof\npower\non\n1Sth\nAugust,\n1947\nherald ing\nIndia's Independence\nwas\nannounced\nby\nLord\nMountbatten.\n\n2.Mahatma Gandhi\nwas not\npresent: at the festivities in the\ncapital 15th August, 1947.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "Freedom with Partition",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_f9fbb3__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about India's Independence is/are correct?\n\n\n1. The formal transfer of power on 1Sth August, 1947 heralding India's Independence was announced by Lord Mountbatten.\n\n\n2. Mahatma Gandhi was not present at the festivities in the capital 15th August, 1947.\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\na) 1 only\n\n\nb) 2 only\n\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2\n",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following is not a characteristic feature ofthe\nIndian Independence Act, 1947?\n\na) The Dominion of India got the residuary territory of India,\nexcluding the provinces of Sind, Baluchistan, West Punjab,\nEast Bengal and NWFP .\n\nb)The Act sought to lay down a Constitution by the Legislative\nwill of the British Parliament:\n\nc) The Act proposed to set up two independent Dominions.\n\nd) The Constituent Assembly of each\nDominion\nwas to have\nunlimited: power to frame and adopt any Constitution:\nAnswer: \n(b) The Act sought to lay down a Constitution by the\nLegislative will of the British Parliament",
    "choices": "a) The Dominion of India got the residuary territory of India,\nexcluding the provinces of Sind, Baluchistan, West Punjab,\nEast Bengal and NWFP .\n\nb)The Act sought to lay down a Constitution by the Legislative\nwill of the British Parliament:\n\nc) The Act proposed to set up two independent Dominions.\n\nd) The Constituent Assembly of each\nDominion\nwas to have\nunlimited: power to frame and adopt any Constitution:",
    "answer": "\n(b) The Act sought to lay down a Constitution by the\nLegislative will of the British Parliament",
    "topic": "Freedom with Partition",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_f9fbb3__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following is not a characteristic feature of the Indian Independence Act, 1947?\n\n\na) The Dominion of India got the residuary territory of India, excluding the provinces of Sind, Baluchistan, West Punjab, East Bengal and NWFP.\n\nb) The Act sought to lay down a Constitution by the Legislative will of the British Parliament.\n\nc) The Act proposed to set up two independent Dominions.\n\nd) The Constituent Assembly of each Dominion was to have unlimited power to frame and adopt any Constitution.",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the President of Indian National Congress at the time\nof partition of India?\n\n(a) C. Rajagopalachari\n\n(b) J. B. Kripalani\n\n(c) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n(d) Maulana Abul Kalam Azad\nAnswer: \n(b) J. B. Kripalani",
    "choices": "\n(a) C. Rajagopalachari\n\n(b) J. B. Kripalani\n\n(c) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n(d) Maulana Abul Kalam Azad",
    "answer": "\n(b) J. B. Kripalani",
    "topic": "Freedom with Partition",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_f9fbb3__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who was the President of Indian National Congress at the time of partition of India?\n\n\na) C. Rajagopalachari\n\n\nb) J. B. Kripalani\n\n\nc) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n\nd) Maulana Abul Kalam Azad",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\none of the following is\nnot correct about the Indian\nIndependence Act of 1947?\n\na) The Bill for the Indian Independence Act was introduced in\nParliament on July 4 and received the Royal Assent on July\n18, 1947 .\n\nb)Act of 1947 laid down the basic framework of the Indian\nConstitution.\n\nc) The Act provided for the establishment of two independent\ndominions, India and Pakistan.\n\nd) The\nAct empowered\nthe\nConstituent Assembly\nof each\nDominion to have unlimited power to frame and adopt any\nconstitution.\nAnswer: \n(b) Act of 1947 laid down the basic framework of the\nIndian Constitution",
    "choices": "a) The Bill for the Indian Independence Act was introduced in\nParliament on July 4 and received the Royal Assent on July\n18, 1947 .\n\nb)Act of 1947 laid down the basic framework of the Indian\nConstitution.\n\nc) The Act provided for the establishment of two independent\ndominions, India and Pakistan.\n\nd) The\nAct empowered\nthe\nConstituent Assembly\nof each\nDominion to have unlimited power to frame and adopt any\nconstitution.",
    "answer": "\n(b) Act of 1947 laid down the basic framework of the\nIndian Constitution",
    "topic": "Freedom with Partition",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_f9fbb3__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following is not correct about the Indian Independence Act of 1947?\n\n\na) The Bill for the Indian Independence Act was introduced in Parliament on July 4 and received the Royal Assent on July 18, 1947.\n\n\nb) Act of 1947 laid down the basic framework of the Indian Constitution.\n\n\nc) The Act provided for the establishment of two independent dominions, India and Pakistan.\n\n\nd) The Act empowered the Constituent Assembly of each Dominion to have unlimited power to frame and adopt any constitution.",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following is not a change brought about by\nthe Indian Independence Act of 1947?\n\na) The Government of India Act, 1935 was amended to provide\nan interim Constitution:\n\nb)India ceased to be a dependency:\n\nc) The\nCrown\nwas\nthe\nsource\nof\nauthority\ntill\na\nnew\nConstitution was framed:\n\nd) The Governor-General\nwas the constitutional head of the\nIndian Dominion.\nAnswer: \n(c) The Crown\nwas the source of authority till\na\nnew\nConstitution was framed",
    "choices": "a) The Government of India Act, 1935 was amended to provide\nan interim Constitution:\n\nb)India ceased to be a dependency:\n\nc) The\nCrown\nwas\nthe\nsource\nof\nauthority\ntill\na\nnew\nConstitution was framed:\n\nd) The Governor-General\nwas the constitutional head of the\nIndian Dominion.",
    "answer": "\n(c) The Crown\nwas the source of authority till\na\nnew\nConstitution was framed",
    "topic": "Freedom with Partition",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_f9fbb3__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following is not a change brought about by the Indian Independence Act of 1947?\n\n\na) The Government of India Act, 1935 was amended to provide an interim Constitution:\n\n\nb) India ceased to be a dependency:\n\n\nc) The Crown was the source of authority till a new Constitution was framed:\n\n\nd) The Governor-General was the constitutional head of the Indian Dominion.",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to\nwhich\none\nof the following plans/reports, the\ndecision with regard to the partition of Punjab and Bengal was\nto\nbe taken\non\nthe basis of voting of the\nMembers of the\nrespective Legislative Assemblies\n\na)Nehru report\n\nb)Cripps mission plan\n\nC)\nBeveridge report\n\nd)Mountbatten plan\nAnswer: \n(d) Mountbatten plan",
    "choices": "a)Nehru report\n\nb)Cripps mission plan\n\nC)\nBeveridge report\n\nd)Mountbatten plan",
    "answer": "\n(d) Mountbatten plan",
    "topic": "Freedom with Partition",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_f9fbb3__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "According to which one of the following plans/reports, the decision with regard to the partition of Punjab and Bengal was to be taken on the basis of voting of the Members of the respective Legislative Assemblies?\n\n\na) Nehru report\n\nb) Cripps mission plan\n\nc) Beveridge report\n\nd) Mountbatten plan",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nThe Radcliffe Committee was appointed to\n\n(a) solve the problem of minorities in India\n\n(b) effect to the Independence Bill\ndelimit the boundaries between India\nand Pakistan\n\n(d) enquire into the riots in East Bengal\nAnswer: \n(c) delimit the boundaries between India and Pakistan",
    "choices": "\n(a) solve the problem of minorities in India\n\n(b) effect to the Independence Bill\ndelimit the boundaries between India\nand Pakistan\n\n(d) enquire into the riots in East Bengal",
    "answer": "\n(c) delimit the boundaries between India and Pakistan",
    "topic": "Freedom with Partition",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_f9fbb3__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Radcliffe Committee was appointed to \n\n\na) solve the problem of minorities in India\n\nb) effect to the Independence Bill delimit the boundaries between India and Pakistan\n\nc) delimit the boundaries between India and Pakistan\n\nd) enquire into the riots in East Bengal",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who headed the interim Cabinet formed in the year 1946?\n\n(a) Rajendra Prasad\n\n(b) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n(c) Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel\n\n(d) C. Rajagopalachari\nAnswer: \n(b) Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "choices": "\n(a) Rajendra Prasad\n\n(b) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n(c) Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel\n\n(d) C. Rajagopalachari",
    "answer": "\n(b) Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "topic": "Freedom with Partition",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_f9fbb3__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who headed the interim Cabinet formed in the year 1946?\n\na) Rajendra Prasad\n\nb) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\nc) Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel\n\nd) C. Rajagopalachari",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\none\nof\nthe\nfollowing\nstatements\nconcerning\nthe\nFreedom and Partition f India is NOT correct?\n\na)In February 1947 ,\nBritish Prime Minister Attlee announced\nthat the British were not going to transfer power to Indians,\ncome what may\n\nb)Lord\nWavell advocated the total withdrawal of the British\nfrom India by 31 March 1948\n\nc) It\nwas Lord Mountbatten\nwho speeded up the process of\ntransfer of power\n\nd) The\nPlan\nBalkan\nwas\nabandoned\non\naccount\nof\nNehru's\nopposition to it\nAnswer: \n(a) In February 1947,\nBritish\nPrime\nMinister\nAttlee\nanounced that the British were not going to transfer power to\nIndians, come what may",
    "choices": "a)In February 1947 ,\nBritish Prime Minister Attlee announced\nthat the British were not going to transfer power to Indians,\ncome what may\n\nb)Lord\nWavell advocated the total withdrawal of the British\nfrom India by 31 March 1948\n\nc) It\nwas Lord Mountbatten\nwho speeded up the process of\ntransfer of power\n\nd) The\nPlan\nBalkan\nwas\nabandoned\non\naccount\nof\nNehru's\nopposition to it",
    "answer": "\n(a) In February 1947,\nBritish\nPrime\nMinister\nAttlee\nanounced that the British were not going to transfer power to\nIndians, come what may",
    "topic": "Freedom with Partition",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_f9fbb3__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following statements concerning the Freedom and Partition f India is NOT correct? \n\na) In February 1947, British Prime Minister Attlee announced that the British were not going to transfer power to Indians, come what may \n\nb) Lord Wavell advocated the total withdrawal of the British from India by 31 March 1948 \n\nc) It was Lord Mountbatten who speeded up the process of transfer of power \n\nd) The Plan Balkan was abandoned on account of Nehru's opposition to it",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the Chittagong group is NOT correct?\n\na) Its membership included a large number of youth including\nGanesh Ghosh, Lokenath Baul and Anant Singh\n\nb)Its leader Surya Sen\nhad been\na\nlawyer in\nDhaka before\njoining the group\n\nc) Surya\nSen\nand\nhis\ngroup\nwere\nclosely\nassociated\nwith\nCongress work in Chittagong\n\nd) This group\nhad prepared\nan\naction\nplan\nto\noccupy\nthe\narmouries in Chittagong\nAnswer: \n(b) Its leader Surya Sen had been a lawyer in Dhaka\nbefore joining the group",
    "choices": "a) Its membership included a large number of youth including\nGanesh Ghosh, Lokenath Baul and Anant Singh\n\nb)Its leader Surya Sen\nhad been\na\nlawyer in\nDhaka before\njoining the group\n\nc) Surya\nSen\nand\nhis\ngroup\nwere\nclosely\nassociated\nwith\nCongress work in Chittagong\n\nd) This group\nhad prepared\nan\naction\nplan\nto\noccupy\nthe\narmouries in Chittagong",
    "answer": "\n(b) Its leader Surya Sen had been a lawyer in Dhaka\nbefore joining the group",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1922-29)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0f35be__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the Chittagong group is NOT correct?\n\n\na) Its membership included a large number of youth including Ganesh Ghosh, Lokenath Baul and Anant Singh\n\nb) Its leader Surya Sen had been a lawyer in Dhaka before joining the group\n\nc) Surya Sen and his group were closely associated with Congress work in Chittagong\n\nd) This group had prepared an action plan to occupy the armouries in Chittagong",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following was the first to accept a ministerial\nposition in the Central Provinces in October 1925?\n\na) S. Moonje\n\nb)M. R. Jayakar\n\nc) S. B. Tambe\n\nd)B. N. Sasmal\nAnswer: \n(c) S. B. Tambe",
    "choices": "a) S. Moonje\n\nb)M. R. Jayakar\n\nc) S. B. Tambe\n\nd)B. N. Sasmal",
    "answer": "\n(c) S. B. Tambe",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1922-29)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0f35be__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following was the first to accept a ministerial position in the Central Provinces in October 1925?\n\n\na) S. Moonje\n\nb) M. R. Jayakar\n\nc) S. B. Tambe\n\nd) B. N. Sasmal",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following wrote The Philosophy of the Bomb?\n\na) Sukhdev\n\nb) Chandrashekhar Azad\n\nc) Bhagwati Charan Vohra\n\nd)Bhagat Singh\nAnswer: \n(c) Bhagwati Charan Vohra",
    "choices": "a) Sukhdev\n\nb) Chandrashekhar Azad\n\nc) Bhagwati Charan Vohra\n\nd)Bhagat Singh",
    "answer": "\n(c) Bhagwati Charan Vohra",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1922-29)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0f35be__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following wrote The Philosophy of the Bomb?\n\n\na) Sukhdev\n\nb) Chandrashekhar Azad\n\nc) Bhagwati Charan Vohra\n\nd) Bhagat Singh",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following was the first non-official member to\nbe elected as Speaker of the Central Legislative Assembly on\n24-8-1925?\n\na) Vithalbhai J Patel\n\nb)Muhammad Yakub\n\nc) G. V: Mavalankar\n\nd) Sardar Hukum Singh\nAnswer: \n(a) Vithalbhai J Patel",
    "choices": "a) Vithalbhai J Patel\n\nb)Muhammad Yakub\n\nc) G. V: Mavalankar\n\nd) Sardar Hukum Singh",
    "answer": "\n(a) Vithalbhai J Patel",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1922-29)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0f35be__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following was the first non-official member to be elected as Speaker of the Central Legislative Assembly on 24-8-1925?\n\n\na) Vithalbhai J Patel\n\nb) Muhammad Yakub\n\nc) G. V: Mavalankar\n\nd) Sardar Hukum Singh",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following is the author of the book, Bandi\nJivan?\n\na) Rash Behari Bose\n\nb) Veer Savarkar\n\nc) Aruna Asaf Ali\n\nd) Sachindranath Sanyal\nAnswer: \n(d) Sachindranath Sanyal",
    "choices": "a) Rash Behari Bose\n\nb) Veer Savarkar\n\nc) Aruna Asaf Ali\n\nd) Sachindranath Sanyal",
    "answer": "\n(d) Sachindranath Sanyal",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1922-29)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0f35be__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following is the author of the book, Bandi Jivan?\n\na) Rash Behari Bose\n\nb) Veer Savarkar\n\nc) Aruna Asaf Ali\n\nd) Sachindranath Sanyal",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following was/were the founder member(s) of\nthe\nHindustan\nSocialist\nRepublican\nArmy\nestablished\nin\nSeptember 1928?\n\n1.Bhagat Singh\n\n2.Jatindranath\n\n3.Ajoy Ghosh\n\n4.Phanindranath Ghosh\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1,2 and 3 only\n\nd)1,2,3 and 4\nAnswer: \n(d) 1,2,3 and 4",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1,2 and 3 only\n\nd)1,2,3 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1,2,3 and 4",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1922-29)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0f35be__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following was/were the founder member(s) of the Hindustan Socialist Republican Army established in September 1928?\n\n\n1. Bhagat Singh\n\n2. Jatindranath\n\n3. Ajoy Ghosh\n\n4. Phanindranath Ghosh\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1,2 and 3 only\n\nd) 1,2,3 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following did not belong to the group of 'No-\nChangers'?\n\na)M.A. Ansari\n\nb) Vithalbhai Patel\n\nc) Chakravarti Rajagopalachari\n\nd)Kasturi Ranga lyengar\nAnswer: \n(b) Vithalbhai Patel",
    "choices": "a)M.A. Ansari\n\nb) Vithalbhai Patel\n\nc) Chakravarti Rajagopalachari\n\nd)Kasturi Ranga lyengar",
    "answer": "\n(b) Vithalbhai Patel",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1922-29)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0f35be__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following did not belong to the group of 'No-Changers'?\n\na) M.A. Ansari\n\nb) Vithalbhai Patel\n\nc) Chakravarti Rajagopalachari\n\nd) Kasturi Ranga lyengar",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following is one of the authors of the book\nPhilosophy of the Bomb?\"\n\na) Bhagat Singh\n\nb)Jawaharlal Nehru\n\nc) Surya Sen\n\nd) Yashpal\nAnswer: \n(d) Yashpal",
    "choices": "a) Bhagat Singh\n\nb)Jawaharlal Nehru\n\nc) Surya Sen\n\nd) Yashpal",
    "answer": "\n(d) Yashpal",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1922-29)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0f35be__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following is one of the authors of the book Philosophy of the Bomb?\n\n\na) Bhagat Singh\n\n\nb) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n\nc) Surya Sen\n\n\nd) Yashpal",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nThe Trade Disputes Act of 1929 provided for\n\n(a) The participation\nof\nworkers\nin the management of\nindustries.\n\n(b) Arbitrary powers to the management to quell industrial\ndisputes.\n\n(c) An intervention by the British Court in the event of a\ntrade dispute:\n\n(d) A\nsystem of tribunals and a ban on strikes.\nAnswer: \n(d) A system of tribunals and a ban on strikes",
    "choices": "\n(a) The participation\nof\nworkers\nin the management of\nindustries.\n\n(b) Arbitrary powers to the management to quell industrial\ndisputes.\n\n(c) An intervention by the British Court in the event of a\ntrade dispute:\n\n(d) A\nsystem of tribunals and a ban on strikes.",
    "answer": "\n(d) A system of tribunals and a ban on strikes",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1922-29)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0f35be__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Trade Disputes Act of 1929 provided for \n\n\na) The participation of workers in the management of industries. \n\nb) Arbitrary powers to the management to quell industrial disputes. \n\nc) An intervention by the British Court in the event of a trade dispute: \n\nd) A system of tribunals and a ban on strikes.",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "The object of the Butler Committee of 1927 was to?\n\n(a) Define the jurisdiction\nof the Central\nand\nProvincial\nGovernments.\n\n(b) Define the powers of the Secretary of State for India:\n\n(c) Impose censorship on the national press.\n\n(d) Improve the relationship between the Government of\nIndia and the Indian\nStates.\nAnswer: \n(d) Improve the relationship between the Government\nof India and the Indian States",
    "choices": "\n(a) Define the jurisdiction\nof the Central\nand\nProvincial\nGovernments.\n\n(b) Define the powers of the Secretary of State for India:\n\n(c) Impose censorship on the national press.\n\n(d) Improve the relationship between the Government of\nIndia and the Indian\nStates.",
    "answer": "\n(d) Improve the relationship between the Government\nof India and the Indian States",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1922-29)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0f35be__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The object of the Butler Committee of 1927 was to?\n\n\na) Define the jurisdiction of the Central and Provincial Governments.\n\nb) Define the powers of the Secretary of State for India:\n\nc) Impose censorship on the national press.\n\nd) Improve the relationship between the Government of India and the Indian States.",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following was NOT associated with the Kakori\nConspiracy Case?\n\na) Ramprasad Bismil\n\nb)Rajendra Lahiri\n\nc) Ashfaqulla Khan\n\nd) Surya Sen\nAnswer: \n(d) Surya Sen",
    "choices": "a) Ramprasad Bismil\n\nb)Rajendra Lahiri\n\nc) Ashfaqulla Khan\n\nd) Surya Sen",
    "answer": "\n(d) Surya Sen",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1922-29)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0f35be__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following was NOT associated with the Kakori Conspiracy Case?\n\n1. Ramprasad Bismil\n\n2. Rajendra Lahiri\n\n3. Ashfaqulla Khan\n\n4. Surya Sen",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about Bhagat Singh is/are\nNOT true?\n\n1.Bhagat Singh was influenced by socialist ideas\n\n2.He\nwas\na\nmember of the\nHindustan\nSocialist Republican\nAssociation\n\n3.Bhagat  Singh\nthrew\na\nbomb\nin\nthe\nCentral\nLegislative\nAssembly in 1929 with the objective to kill as many people\nas\npossible\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 3\n6)2 and 3\n\nc) 2 only\n\nd)3 only\nAnswer: \n(d) 3 only",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 3\n6)2 and 3\n\nc) 2 only\n\nd)3 only",
    "answer": "\n(d) 3 only",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1922-29)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0f35be__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about Bhagat Singh is/are NOT true?\n\n\n1. Bhagat Singh was influenced by socialist ideas\n\n2. He was a member of the Hindustan Socialist Republican Association\n\n3. Bhagat Singh threw a bomb in the Central Legislative Assembly in 1929 with the objective to kill as many people as possible\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\na) 1 and 3\n\nb) 2 and 3\n\nc) 2 only\n\nd) 3 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "The\nBritish Committee of the Indian\nNational Congress\nwas\nfounded in\n\na) 1889\n\nb) 1892\n\nc) 1898\n\nd)1901\nAnswer: \n(a) 1889",
    "choices": "a) 1889\n\nb) 1892\n\nc) 1898\n\nd)1901",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1889",
    "topic": "Moderate Nationalism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The British Committee of the Indian National Congress was founded in\n\n\na) 1889\n\nb) 1892\n\nc) 1898\n\nd) 1901",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the purpose with which Sir William Wedderburn and\nW.S.Caine had set up the Indian Parliamentary Committee in\n1893?\n\n(a) To agitate for Indian political reforms in the House of\nCommons\n\n(b) To campaign for the entry of Indians into the Imperial\nJudiciary\n\n(c) To facilitate a discussion on India's Independence in the\nBritish Parliament\n\n(d) To agitate for the entry of eminent Indians into the\nBritish Parliament\nAnswer: \n(a) To agitate for Indian political reforms in the House\nOf Commons",
    "choices": "\n(a) To agitate for Indian political reforms in the House of\nCommons\n\n(b) To campaign for the entry of Indians into the Imperial\nJudiciary\n\n(c) To facilitate a discussion on India's Independence in the\nBritish Parliament\n\n(d) To agitate for the entry of eminent Indians into the\nBritish Parliament",
    "answer": "\n(a) To agitate for Indian political reforms in the House\nOf Commons",
    "topic": "Moderate Nationalism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "What was the purpose with which Sir William Wedderburn and W.S.Caine had set up the Indian Parliamentary Committee in 1893?\n\n\na) To agitate for Indian political reforms in the House of Commons\n\nb) To campaign for the entry of Indians into the Imperial Judiciary\n\nc) To facilitate a discussion on India's Independence in the British Parliament\n\nd) To agitate for the entry of eminent Indians into the British Parliament",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\namong\nthe following\nused\nthe\nphrase\n'Un-British'\nto\ncriticise the English colonial control of India?\n\n(a) Anand Mohan Bose\n\n(b) Badruddin Tyabji\n\n(c) Dadabhai Naoroji\n\n(d) Pherozeshah Mehta\nAnswer: \n(c) Dadabhai Naoroji",
    "choices": "\n(a) Anand Mohan Bose\n\n(b) Badruddin Tyabji\n\n(c) Dadabhai Naoroji\n\n(d) Pherozeshah Mehta",
    "answer": "\n(c) Dadabhai Naoroji",
    "topic": "Moderate Nationalism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following used the phrase 'Un-British' to criticise the English colonial control of India?\n\n\n(a) Anand Mohan Bose\n\n\n(b) Badruddin Tyabji\n\n\n(c) Dadabhai Naoroji\n\n\n(d) Pherozeshah Mehta",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following rejected the title of knighthood and\nrefused to accept a position in the council of the Secretary of\nState for India?\n\n(a) Motilal Nehru\n\n(b) M. 6. Ranade\n\n(c) G.K Gokhale\n\n(d) B. G. Tilak\nAnswer: \n(c) G. K Gokhale",
    "choices": "\n(a) Motilal Nehru\n\n(b) M. 6. Ranade\n\n(c) G.K Gokhale\n\n(d) B. G. Tilak",
    "answer": "\n(c) G. K Gokhale",
    "topic": "Moderate Nationalism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following rejected the title of knighthood and refused to accept a position in the council of the Secretary of State for India?\n\na) Motilal Nehru\n\nb) M. 6. Ranade\n\nc) G.K Gokhale\n\nd) B. G. Tilak",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\none of the following was not\na demand made\nthe\nCongress moderates?\n\na) Universal adult franchise\n\nb)Repeal of the Arms Act\n\nc) Extension of Permanent Settlement\n\nd)Higher\nfor Indians in the army\nAnswer: \n(a) Universal adult franchise",
    "choices": "a) Universal adult franchise\n\nb)Repeal of the Arms Act\n\nc) Extension of Permanent Settlement\n\nd)Higher\nfor Indians in the army",
    "answer": "\n(a) Universal adult franchise",
    "topic": "Moderate Nationalism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following was not a demand made the Congress moderates?\n\n\na) Universal adult franchise \n\nb) Repeal of the Arms Act\n\nc) Extension of Permanent Settlement\n\nd) Higher for Indians in the army",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nConsider\nthe\nfollowing\nstatements:\nThe\nmost\neffective\ncontribution\nmade by\nDadabhai Naoroji to the cause of the\nIndian\nNational Movement was that\n\n1.Exposed the economic exploitation of India by the British.\n\n2. Interpreted the ancient Indian texts and\nrestored the self_\nconfidence of Indians.\n\n3.Stressed\nthe need for eradication\nof all\nthe social\nevils\nbefore anything else:\nWhich of the statement(s) given above is/ are correct?\n\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1,2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(a) 1 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1,2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 only",
    "topic": "Moderate Nationalism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_0__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements: The most effective contribution made by Dadabhai Naoroji to the cause of the Indian National Movement was that\n\n1. Exposed the economic exploitation of India by the British.\n\n2. Interpreted the ancient Indian texts and restored the self-confidence of Indians.\n\n3. Stressed the need for eradication of all the social evils before anything else:\nWhich of the statement(s) given above is/ are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 1,2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is/are characteristic (s) of the debate between Anglicists' and \"Orientalists in the 1830s?\n\n1. The Anglicists wanted to cut the money being spent on printing Sanskrit and Arabic texts\n\n2. The Anglicists wanted to cut the money spent on printing Sanskrit texts but wished to continue to print in Persian\n\n3.The Orientalists wanted stipends for the students of Arabic and Sanskrit\n\n4.The Orientalists started a new Sanskrit College in Delhi\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)1,3 and 4\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd)2,3 and 4",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)1,3 and 4\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd)2,3 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(c) 1 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Social and Cultural Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following is/are characteristic (s) of the debate between Anglicists' and \"Orientalists in the 1830s?\n\n\n1. The Anglicists wanted to cut the money being spent on printing Sanskrit and Arabic texts\n\n2. The Anglicists wanted to cut the money spent on printing Sanskrit texts but wished to continue to print in Persian\n\n3. The Orientalists wanted stipends for the students of Arabic and Sanskrit\n\n4. The Orientalists started a new Sanskrit College in Delhi\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1,3 and 4\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 2,3 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "William James, Henry Colebrooke and Nathaniel Halhed had which of the following common among them?\n\na) They were critics of Indian culture and civilisation\n\nb) They were judges at the courts of the East India Company\n\nc) They were professors teaching the history and society of South Asia\n\nd) They were linguists who tried to interpret the culture of South Asia to the East India Company",
    "choices": "a) They were critics of Indian culture and civilisation\n\nb) They were judges at the courts of the East India Company\n\nc) They were professors teaching the history and society of South Asia\n\nd) They were linguists who tried to interpret the culture of South Asia to the East India Company",
    "answer": "\n(d) They were linguists who tried to interpret the culture of South Asia to the East India Company",
    "topic": "Social and Cultural Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "William James, Henry Colebrooke and Nathaniel Halhed had which of the following common among them?\n\n\na) They were critics of Indian culture and civilisation\n\nb) They were judges at the courts of the East India Company\n\nc) They were professors teaching the history and society of South Asia\n\nd) They were linguists who tried to interpret the culture of South Asia to the East India Company",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the author of the book 'History of British India'?",
    "choices": "a) Charles Grant\n\nb)John Stuart Mill\n\nc) James Mill\n\nd) William Jones",
    "answer": "\n(c) James Mill",
    "topic": "Social and Cultural Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who was the author of the book 'History of British India'?",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements about Act V of 1843 relating to Slavery in India is correct?\n\na) It gave the masters the right to wilfully keep their slaves tied to their estates.\n\nb)It denied the masters the use of Courts to assert their claims on slaves.\n\nc) The Law Courts and masters worked jointly in resolving the cases of desertion.\n\nd) The slaves became the owners of the land:",
    "choices": "a) It gave the masters the right to wilfully keep their slaves tied to their estates.\n\nb)It denied the masters the use of Courts to assert their claims on slaves.\n\nc) The Law Courts and masters worked jointly in resolving the cases of desertion.\n\nd) The slaves became the owners of the land:",
    "answer": "\n(b) It denied the masters the use of Courts to assert their claims on slaves",
    "topic": "Social and Cultural Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following statements about Act V of 1843 relating to Slavery in India is correct?\n\n\na) It gave the masters the right to wilfully keep their slaves tied to their estates.\n\n\nb) It denied the masters the use of Courts to assert their claims on slaves.\n\n\nc) The Law Courts and masters worked jointly in resolving the cases of desertion.\n\n\nd) The slaves became the owners of the land:",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Henry T: Colebrooke was a Professor of Sanskrit in which one of the following institutions?\n\na) Fort William College\n\nb) Serampore Mission\n\nc) Kashi Vidyapith\nd Asiatic Society",
    "choices": "a) Fort William College\n\nb) Serampore Mission\n\nc) Kashi Vidyapith\nd Asiatic Society",
    "answer": "\n(a) Fort William College",
    "topic": "Social and Cultural Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Henry T: Colebrooke was a Professor of Sanskrit in which one of the following institutions? \n\n\na) Fort William College\n\n\nb) Serampore Mission\n\n\nc) Kashi Vidyapith\n\nd Asiatic Society",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following was an important aspect of the Cripps mission of 1942?\n\n(a) All\nIndian\nstate\nshould\njoin\nthe\nIndian\nunion\nas\na\ncondition to consider\ndegree of autonomy for India.\n\n(b) The\ncreation\nof an\nIndian\nunion\nwith\nDominion\nstatus\nvery soon after the second world war:\n\n(c) The participation and co-operation of the Indian people\ncommunities and political par- ties in the British war effort\nas\na\ncondition for granting independence with full\nsover-\n eign status to India after second world war:\n\n(d) The farming of a constitution for the entire Indian union\nwith no separate constitution for any province and a union\nconstitution to be accepted by all province:\nAnswer: \n(b)",
    "choices": "\n(a) All\nIndian\nstate\nshould\njoin\nthe\nIndian\nunion\nas\na\ncondition to consider\ndegree of autonomy for India.\n\n(b) The\ncreation\nof an\nIndian\nunion\nwith\nDominion\nstatus\nvery soon after the second world war:\n\n(c) The participation and co-operation of the Indian people\ncommunities and political par- ties in the British war effort\nas\na\ncondition for granting independence with full\nsover-\n eign status to India after second world war:\n\n(d) The farming of a constitution for the entire Indian union\nwith no separate constitution for any province and a union\nconstitution to be accepted by all province:",
    "answer": "\n(b)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following was an important aspect of the Cripps mission of 1942?\n\n\na) All Indian state should join the Indian union as a condition to consider degree of autonomy for India.\n\nb) The creation of an Indian union with Dominion status very soon after the second world war:\n\nc) The participation and co-operation of the Indian people communities and political par- ties in the British war effort as a condition for granting independence with full sover- eign status to India after second world war:\n\nd) The farming of a constitution for the entire Indian union with no separate constitution for any province and a union constitution to be accepted by all province:",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to\nAugust 1942 in Indian history, which one\nof the following statements is correct?\n\n(a) The Quit India Resolution was adopted by the AICC\n\n(b) The\nViceroy's\nExecutive\nCouncil\nwas\nexpanded\nto\ninclude more Indians:\n\n(c) The Congress ministries resigned in\nseven\nprovinces:\n\n(d) Cripps proposed\nan\nIndian\nUnion\nwith full\nDominion\nStatus once the Second\nWorld War was over:\nAnswer: \n(a)",
    "choices": "\n(a) The Quit India Resolution was adopted by the AICC\n\n(b) The\nViceroy's\nExecutive\nCouncil\nwas\nexpanded\nto\ninclude more Indians:\n\n(c) The Congress ministries resigned in\nseven\nprovinces:\n\n(d) Cripps proposed\nan\nIndian\nUnion\nwith full\nDominion\nStatus once the Second\nWorld War was over:",
    "answer": "\n(a)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to August 1942 in Indian history, which one of the following statements is correct?\n\na) The Quit India Resolution was adopted by the AICC\n\nb) The Viceroy's Executive Council was expanded to include more Indians\n\nc) The Congress ministries resigned in seven provinces\n\nd) Cripps proposed an Indian Union with full Dominion Status once the Second World War was over",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "The plan of Sir Stafford Cripps envisaged that after the Second\nWorld War:\n\n(a) India should be granted complete independence\n\n(b) India should be partitioned into two\nbefore granting\nindependence\n\n(c) India should be\nmade\na\nrepublic with\nthe condition\nthat she will join the Commonwealth\n\n(d) India should be given Dominion status\nAnswer: \n(d)",
    "choices": "\n(a) India should be granted complete independence\n\n(b) India should be partitioned into two\nbefore granting\nindependence\n\n(c) India should be\nmade\na\nrepublic with\nthe condition\nthat she will join the Commonwealth\n\n(d) India should be given Dominion status",
    "answer": "\n(d)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The plan of Sir Stafford Cripps envisaged that after the Second World War:\n\na) India should be granted complete independence\n\nb) India should be partitioned into two before granting independence\n\nc) India should be made a republic with the condition that she will join the Commonwealth\n\nd) India should be given Dominion status",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "8th\nWhich of the following was/were the features of the Quit India\nMovement?\n\n1.From the very beginning, it was a rural revolt\n\n2.It was\nessentially a moderate movement\n\n3.It was marked by the unprecedented use of violence\n\n4.It was marked by acute state repression\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 2\n\nc) 3 and 4 only\n\nd)1,3 and 4\nAnswer: \n(c)",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 2\n\nc) 3 and 4 only\n\nd)1,3 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(c)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following was/were the features of the Quit India Movement?\n\n1. From the very beginning, it was a rural revolt\n\n2. It was essentially a moderate movement\n\n3. It was marked by the unprecedented use of violence\n\n4. It was marked by acute state repression\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 2\n\nc) 3 and 4 only\n\nd) 1, 3 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nWith reference to the proposals of Cripps Mission, consider the\nfollowing statements:\n\n1. The Constituent Assembly would have members nominated\nby the Provincial Assemblies as well as the Princely States:\n\n2.\nProvince,\nwhich\nis\nnot prepared\nto accept the\nnew\nConstitution\nwould\nhave\nthe\nright\nto\nsign\na\nseparate\nagreement with Britain regarding its future status:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 only\nBoth 1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(b)",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 only\nBoth 1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(b)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to the proposals of Cripps Mission, consider the following statements:\n\n\n1. The Constituent Assembly would have members nominated by the Provincial Assemblies as well as the Princely States:\n\n2. Province, which is not prepared to accept the new Constitution would have the right to sign a separate agreement with Britain regarding its future status:\n\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\nBoth 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Any\nWith\nwhom\ndid\nSubhas\nChandra\nBose form\nan\nalliance\nto\ndestroy the Holwel Monument in Calcutta during 1939-40?\n\na) The Communist Party of India\n\nb) The Muslim League\n\nc) The Hindu Mahasabha\n\nd) The Unionist Party\nAnswer: \n(b)",
    "choices": "a) The Communist Party of India\n\nb) The Muslim League\n\nc) The Hindu Mahasabha\n\nd) The Unionist Party",
    "answer": "\n(b)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With whom did Subhas Chandra Bose form an alliance to destroy the Holwel Monument in Calcutta during 1939-40?\n\na) The Communist Party of India\n\nb) The Muslim League\n\nc) The Hindu Mahasabha\n\nd) The Unionist Party",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following moved the motion\nof the Secret\nSitting Session of the Assembly (1942)?\n\na) M. S.\n b) G. V: Mavalankar\n\nc) C. M. Stephen\nA.Ayyangar\nAnswer: \n(a)",
    "choices": "a) M. S.\n b) G. V: Mavalankar\n\nc) C. M. Stephen\nA.Ayyangar",
    "answer": "\n(a)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following moved the motion of the Secret Sitting Session of the Assembly (1942)?\n\n\na) M. S.\n\nb) G. V: Mavalankar\n\nc) C. M. Stephen A.Ayyangar",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aney\nConsider the following statements:\nThe Cripps Proposals included the provisions for\n\n1.Full independence for India\n\n2. Creation of Constitution making body\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct? Choose\nthe correct answer from the following options:\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) Both 1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(b)",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) Both 1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(b)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements:\nThe Cripps Proposals included the provisions for\n\n1. Full independence for India\n\n2. Creation of Constitution making body\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct? Choose the correct answer from the following options:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the\nfreedom struggle,\nAruna\nAsaf\nAli\nwas\na\nmajor\nwoman\norganiser\nof\nunderground activity\nin\nwhich\nof the\nfollowing?\n\n(a) Civil Disobedience Movement\n\n(b) Non-Cooperation Movement\n\n(c) Quit India Movement\n\n(d) Swadeshi Movement\nAnswer: \n(c)",
    "choices": "\n(a) Civil Disobedience Movement\n\n(b) Non-Cooperation Movement\n\n(c) Quit India Movement\n\n(d) Swadeshi Movement",
    "answer": "\n(c)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "During the freedom struggle, Aruna Asaf Ali was a major woman organiser of underground activity in which of the following?\n\na) Civil Disobedience Movement\n\nb) Non-Cooperation Movement\n\nc) Quit India Movement\n\nd) Swadeshi Movement",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements\nAfter forming the Indian National Army, Subhas Chandra Bose\n1,recruited\na\nlarge\nnumber\nof\nsoldiers\nfrom\nthe\nIndian\nPrisoners of War in Japanese camp\n\n2.introduced a women's detachment named after the Rani of\nJhansi\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(c)",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(c)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements\nAfter forming the Indian National Army, Subhas Chandra Bose\n\n1. recruited a large number of soldiers from the Indian Prisoners of War in Japanese camp\n\n2. introduced a women's detachment named after the Rani of Jhansi\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following is the author of the book 'The Indian\nStruggle 1920-1942'?\n\na) Vinayak Damodar Savarkar\n\nb)Subhas Chandra Bose\n\nc) Vallabhbhai Patel\n\nd) Sarat Chandra Bose\nAnswer: \n(b)",
    "choices": "a) Vinayak Damodar Savarkar\n\nb)Subhas Chandra Bose\n\nc) Vallabhbhai Patel\n\nd) Sarat Chandra Bose",
    "answer": "\n(b)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following is the author of the book 'The Indian Struggle 1920-1942'?\n\na) Vinayak Damodar Savarkar\n\nb) Subhas Chandra Bose\n\nc) Vallabhbhai Patel\n\nd) Sarat Chandra Bose",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the\nIndian\nfreedom  struggle,\nwho\nof the following\nraised an army called 'Free Indian Legion'?\n\n(a) Lala Hardayal\n\n(b) Rash Behari Bose\n\n(c) Subhash Chandra Bose\n\n(d) V. D: Savarkar\nAnswer: \n(c)",
    "choices": "\n(a) Lala Hardayal\n\n(b) Rash Behari Bose\n\n(c) Subhash Chandra Bose\n\n(d) V. D: Savarkar",
    "answer": "\n(c)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "During the Indian freedom struggle, who of the following raised an army called 'Free Indian Legion'?\n\n\na) Lala Hardayal\n\n\nb) Rash Behari Bose\n\n\nc) Subhash Chandra Bose\n\n\nd) V. D: Savarkar",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which party was founded by Subhash Chandra Bose in the year\n1939 after he broke away from the Congress?\n\n(a) Indian Freedom Party\n\n(b) Azad Hind Fauj\n\n(c) Revolutionary Front\n\n(d) Forward Bloc\nAnswer: \n(d)",
    "choices": "\n(a) Indian Freedom Party\n\n(b) Azad Hind Fauj\n\n(c) Revolutionary Front\n\n(d) Forward Bloc",
    "answer": "\n(d)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which party was founded by Subhash Chandra Bose in the year 1939 after he broke away from the Congress?\n\n\na) Indian Freedom Party\n\nb) Azad Hind Fauj\n\nc) Revolutionary Front\n\nd) Forward Bloc",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\none\nof\nthe following\nstatements\nabout\nthe Cripps\nMission is not correct?\n\na) It\nwas sent to India by the\nBritish\nGovernment in\nMarch\n1942.\n\nb)lt proposed that the Constitution of India was to be framed\nby an elected Constituent Assembly of the Indian people:\n\nC)\nprovince\nwhich\nwas\nnot\nprepared\nto\naccept\nthe\nConstitution\nwould\nbe\nfree\nto\nretain\nits\nconstitutional\nprovisions existing at that time:\n\nd) The\nBritish\nGovernment\ncould\nenter\ninto\na\nseparate\nconstitutional\narrangement\nwith\nany\nof\nthe\nacceding\nprovinces\nAnswer: \n(d)",
    "choices": "a) It\nwas sent to India by the\nBritish\nGovernment in\nMarch\n1942.\n\nb)lt proposed that the Constitution of India was to be framed\nby an elected Constituent Assembly of the Indian people:\n\nC)\nprovince\nwhich\nwas\nnot\nprepared\nto\naccept\nthe\nConstitution\nwould\nbe\nfree\nto\nretain\nits\nconstitutional\nprovisions existing at that time:\n\nd) The\nBritish\nGovernment\ncould\nenter\ninto\na\nseparate\nconstitutional\narrangement\nwith\nany\nof\nthe\nacceding\nprovinces",
    "answer": "\n(d)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following statements about the Cripps Mission is not correct?\n\na) It was sent to India by the British Government in March 1942.\n\nb)lt proposed that the Constitution of India was to be framed by an elected Constituent Assembly of the Indian people:\n\nc) province which was not prepared to accept the Constitution would be free to retain its constitutional provisions existing at that time:\n\nd) The British Government could enter into a separate constitutional arrangement with any of the acceding provinces",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Any\nWhich one of the following statements about Cripps Mission is\nNOT correct?\n\na)In March 1942, Cripps persuaded War Cabinet to agree to a\ndraft declaration\n\nb)Jawaharlal Nehru and Sardar Patel represented Congress to\nnegotiate with the mission\n\nc) The mission offered Dominion status after the war\n\nd) The mission offered formation of constitution making body\nafter the war\nAnswer: \n(b)",
    "choices": "a)In March 1942, Cripps persuaded War Cabinet to agree to a\ndraft declaration\n\nb)Jawaharlal Nehru and Sardar Patel represented Congress to\nnegotiate with the mission\n\nc) The mission offered Dominion status after the war\n\nd) The mission offered formation of constitution making body\nafter the war",
    "answer": "\n(b)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following statements about Cripps Mission is NOT correct? \n\n\na) In March 1942, Cripps persuaded War Cabinet to agree to a draft declaration\n\nb) Jawaharlal Nehru and Sardar Patel represented Congress to negotiate with the mission\n\nc) The mission offered Dominion status after the war\n\nd) The mission offered formation of constitution making body after the war",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "The principle that the framing\nof the\nnew\nConstitution\nfor\nindependent India should be primarily (though not solely) the\nresponsibility of Indians themselves,\nwas\nfor the first time\nconceded in the\n\na) Government of India Act, 1935\n\nb)August Offer of Viceroy Linlithgow\n\nc) Cripps Proposals\n\nd)Cabinet Mission\nAnswer: \n(b)",
    "choices": "a) Government of India Act, 1935\n\nb)August Offer of Viceroy Linlithgow\n\nc) Cripps Proposals\n\nd)Cabinet Mission",
    "answer": "\n(b)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The principle that the framing of the new Constitution for independent India should be primarily (though not solely) the responsibility of Indians themselves, was for the first time conceded in the\n\na) Government of India Act, 1935\n\nb) August Offer of Viceroy Linlithgow\n\nc) Cripps Proposals\n\nd) Cabinet Mission",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "In 1943, young leaders in which one of the following districts\nof Maharashtra set up\na\nparallel Government (prati sarkar\nwith volunteer corps (seva dals) and village units (tufan dals)?\n\na) Pune\n\nb) Nasik\n\nC)\nNagpur\n\nd) Satara\nAnswer: \n(d)",
    "choices": "a) Pune\n\nb) Nasik\n\nC)\nNagpur\n\nd) Satara",
    "answer": "\n(d)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In 1943, young leaders in which one of the following districts of Maharashtra set up a parallel Government (prati sarkar with volunteer corps (seva dals) and village units (tufan dals)?\n\n\na) Pune\n\nb) Nasik\n\nc) Nagpur\n\nd) Satara",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following historians has described the Quit\nIndia movement as a 'spontaneous revolution'?\n\na) Gordon Johnson\n\nb)David Arnold\n\nc) F G Hutchins\n\nd)Peter Robb\nAnswer: \n(c)",
    "choices": "a) Gordon Johnson\n\nb)David Arnold\n\nc) F G Hutchins\n\nd)Peter Robb",
    "answer": "\n(c)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following historians has described the Quit India movement as a 'spontaneous revolution'?\n\n\na) Gordon Johnson\n\nb) David Arnold\n\nc) F G Hutchins\n\nd) Peter Robb",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "With\nreference\nto\nCabinet Mission,\nwhich\nof the following\nstatements is/are correct?\n\n1.It recommended a federal government:\n\n2.It enlarged the powers of the Indian\ncourts.\n\n3.It provided for more Indians in the ICS.\nSelect the correct answer\nusing the code given below:\n\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 and 3\n\n(c) 1 and 3\n\n(d) None of the above\nAnswer: \n(a)",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 and 3\n\n(c) 1 and 3\n\n(d) None of the above",
    "answer": "\n(a)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to Cabinet Mission, which of the following statements is/are correct?\n\n1. It recommended a federal government:\n\n2. It enlarged the powers of the Indian courts.\n\n3. It provided for more Indians in the ICS.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 and 3\n\nc) 1 and 3\n\nd) None of the above",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Quit India Movement was launched in response to\n\n(a) Cabinet Mission Plan\nCripps Proposals\nT\nSimon Commission Report\nWavell Plan\nAnswer: \n(b)",
    "choices": "\n(a) Cabinet Mission Plan\nCripps Proposals\nT\nSimon Commission Report\nWavell Plan",
    "answer": "\n(b)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Quit India Movement was launched in response to \n\n\na) Cabinet Mission Plan\n\nb) Cripps Proposals\n\nc) Simon Commission Report\n\nd) Wavell Plan",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following Prime Ministers sent Cripps Mission\nto India?\n\n(a) James Ramsay MacDonald\n\n(b) Stanley Baldwin\n\n(c) Nevilli Chamberlain\n\n(d) Winston Churchill\nAnswer: \n(d)",
    "choices": "\n(a) James Ramsay MacDonald\n\n(b) Stanley Baldwin\n\n(c) Nevilli Chamberlain\n\n(d) Winston Churchill",
    "answer": "\n(d)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following Prime Ministers sent Cripps Mission to India?\n\n\na) James Ramsay MacDonald\n\nb) Stanley Baldwin\n\nc) Nevilli Chamberlain\n\nd) Winston Churchill",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "With which one of the following movements is the slogan 'Do\nor Die' associated?\n\n(a) Swadeshi Movement\n\n(b) Non-Cooperation Movement\n\n(c) Civil Disobedience Movement\n\n(d) Quit India Movement\nAnswer: \n(d)",
    "choices": "\n(a) Swadeshi Movement\n\n(b) Non-Cooperation Movement\n\n(c) Civil Disobedience Movement\n\n(d) Quit India Movement",
    "answer": "\n(d)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With which one of the following movements is the slogan 'Do or Die' associated?\n\na) Swadeshi Movement\n\nb) Non-Cooperation Movement\n\nc) Civil Disobedience Movement\n\nd) Quit India Movement",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to Indian freedom struggle, Usha Mehta is well-\nknown for\n\n(a) Running the secret Congress Radio in\nthe wake of Quit\nIndia Movement\n\n(b) Participating in the Second Round Table\nConference\nLeading a contingent of Indian National Army\n\n(d) Assisting\nin\nthe\nformation\nof\nInterim\nGovernment\nunder Pandit Jawaharlal\nNehru\nAnswer: \n(a)",
    "choices": "\n(a) Running the secret Congress Radio in\nthe wake of Quit\nIndia Movement\n\n(b) Participating in the Second Round Table\nConference\nLeading a contingent of Indian National Army\n\n(d) Assisting\nin\nthe\nformation\nof\nInterim\nGovernment\nunder Pandit Jawaharlal\nNehru",
    "answer": "\n(a)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to Indian freedom struggle, Usha Mehta is well-known for\n\n\n(a) Running the secret Congress Radio in the wake of Quit India Movement\n\n\n(b) Participating in the Second Round Table Conference\n\n\n(c) Leading a contingent of Indian National Army\n\n\n(d) Assisting in the formation of Interim Government under Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru\n",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following observations is not true about the\nQuit India Movement of 1942?\n\n(a) It was a nonviolent movement\n\n(b) It was led by Mahatma Gandhi\nIt was a\nspontaneous movement\n\n(d) It did not attract the labour class in general\nAnswer: \n(b)",
    "choices": "\n(a) It was a nonviolent movement\n\n(b) It was led by Mahatma Gandhi\nIt was a\nspontaneous movement\n\n(d) It did not attract the labour class in general",
    "answer": "\n(b)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following observations is not true about the Quit India Movement of 1942?\n\na) It was a nonviolent movement\n\nb) It was led by Mahatma Gandhi It was a spontaneous movement\n\nc) It was a spontaneous movement\n\nd) It did not attract the labour class in general",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\nOn\nthe\neve\nof\nlaunch\nof\nQuit\nIndia\nMovement,Mahatma\nGandhi\n\n1.asked the government servants to resign:\n\n2.asked the soldiers to leave their posts.\n\n3.asked\nthe\nprinces\nof the\nprincely\nstates\nto\naccept the\nsovereignty of their own people:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct? Choose\nthe correct answer from the following options.\n\n(a) 1 and 2\n\n(b) 2 and 3\n\n(c) 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(c)",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2\n\n(b) 2 and 3\n\n(c) 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(c)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements: On the eve of launch of Quit India Movement, Mahatma Gandhi\n\n\n1. asked the government servants to resign:\n\n\n2. asked the soldiers to leave their posts.\n\n\n3. asked the princes of the princely states to accept the sovereignty of their own people:\n\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct? Choose the correct answer from the following options.\n\n\na) 1 and 2\n\n\nb) 2 and 3\n\n\nc) 3 only\n\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following were official Congress negotiators\nwith Cripps Mission?\n\n(a) Mahatma Gandhi and Sardar Patel\n\n(b) Acharya J. B. Kripalani and C. Rajagopalachari\n\n(c) Pandit Nehru and Maulana Azad\n\n(d) Dr Rajendra Prasad and Rafi Ahmed Kidwai\nAnswer: \n(c)",
    "choices": "\n(a) Mahatma Gandhi and Sardar Patel\n\n(b) Acharya J. B. Kripalani and C. Rajagopalachari\n\n(c) Pandit Nehru and Maulana Azad\n\n(d) Dr Rajendra Prasad and Rafi Ahmed Kidwai",
    "answer": "\n(c)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following were official Congress negotiators with Cripps Mission?\n\n\na) Mahatma Gandhi and Sardar Patel\n\nb) Acharya J. B. Kripalani and C. Rajagopalachari\n\nc) Pandit Nehru and Maulana Azad\n\nd) Dr Rajendra Prasad and Rafi Ahmed Kidwai",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the 'Individual Satyagraha'\nVinoba Bhave was chosen as the\nfirst Satyagrahi Who was the second?\n\n(a) Dr Rajendra Prasad\n\n(b) Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n(c) C, Rajagopalachari\n\n(d) Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel\nAnswer: \n(b)",
    "choices": "\n(a) Dr Rajendra Prasad\n\n(b) Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n(c) C, Rajagopalachari\n\n(d) Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
    "answer": "\n(b)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In the 'Individual Satyagraha' Vinoba Bhave was chosen as the first Satyagrahi Who was the second?\n\n\na) Dr Rajendra Prasad\n\n\nb) Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n\nc) C, Rajagopalachari\n\n\nd) Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Subhas Chandra Bose started the 'Azad Hind Radio' in which of\nthe following countries?\n\na) Japan\n\nb)Austria\n\nc) Germany\n\nd)Malaysia\nAnswer: \n(c)",
    "choices": "a) Japan\n\nb)Austria\n\nc) Germany\n\nd)Malaysia",
    "answer": "\n(c)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Subhas Chandra Bose started the 'Azad Hind Radio' in which of the following countries?\n\na) Japan\n\nb) Austria\n\nc) Germany\n\nd) Malaysia",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following was a\nsignificant feature of the Quit\nIndia Movement?\n\na) Women did not play an important role in the movement\n\nb)Nasik in Maharashtra was an important regional base during\nthe movement\n\nc) It was marked by anti-zamindar violence\n\nd)It was marked by the emergence of parallel governments in\ndifferent parts of India\nAnswer: \n(d)",
    "choices": "a) Women did not play an important role in the movement\n\nb)Nasik in Maharashtra was an important regional base during\nthe movement\n\nc) It was marked by anti-zamindar violence\n\nd)It was marked by the emergence of parallel governments in\ndifferent parts of India",
    "answer": "\n(d)",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement during the Second World War",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8b4f6e__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following was a significant feature of the Quit India Movement?\n\n\na) Women did not play an important role in the movement\n\nb) Nasik in Maharashtra was an important regional base during the movement\n\nc) It was marked by anti-zamindar violence\n\nd) It was marked by the emergence of parallel governments in different parts of India",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the formation of the\nIndian National Congress are true?\n\n1. The\nIndian\nNational Congress\nwas\nformed\nat\na\nnational\nconvention\nheld in\nCalcutta\nin\nDecember 1885 under the\nPresidency of Motilal Nehru:\n\n2. The Safety\nValve Theory regarding the formation\nof the\nIndian National Congress emerged from a biography of A; 0.\nHume written by William Wedderburn:\n\n3.An early decision was that the President would be from the\nsame\nregion where the session was to be held.\n\n4. W: C. Banerjee was the first President of the Indian National\nCongress.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1,2 and 4\n\nb)2 and 3\n\nc) 2 and 4 only\n\nd)1 and 3\nAnswer: \n(c) 2 and 4 only",
    "choices": "a) 1,2 and 4\n\nb)2 and 3\n\nc) 2 and 4 only\n\nd)1 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(c) 2 and 4 only",
    "topic": "Indian Nationalism and Indian National Congress",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the formation of the Indian National Congress are true?\n\n\n1. The Indian National Congress was formed at a national convention held in Calcutta in December 1885 under the Presidency of Motilal Nehru:\n\n\n2. The Safety Valve Theory regarding the formation of the Indian National Congress emerged from a biography of A; 0. Hume written by William Wedderburn:\n\n\n3. An early decision was that the President would be from the same region where the session was to be held.\n\n\n4. W: C. Banerjee was the first President of the Indian National Congress.\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\na) 1,2 and 4\n\n\nb) 2 and 3\n\n\nc) 2 and 4 only\n\n\nd) 1 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements about the First Session of\nthe Indian National Congress:\n\n1.It was held in Bombay in 1885.\n\n2.Surendranath Banerji could\nnot attend the session due to\nthe simultaneous session at the Indian National Conference.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "Indian Nationalism and Indian National Congress",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements about the First Session of the Indian National Congress:\n\n\n1. It was held in Bombay in 1885.\n\n2. Surendranath Banerji could not attend the session due to the simultaneous session at the Indian National Conference.\n\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Balgangadhar Tilak was associated with\n\n1.Poona Sarvajanik Sabha\n\n2. The Age of Consent Bill\n\n3. Gaurakshini Sabha\n\n4.Atmiya Sabha\nSelect the correct answer using the given below :\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)1,2 and 4\n\nc) 3 and 4\n\nd)2 and 4 only\nAnswer: \n(a) 1 and 2 only",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)1,2 and 4\n\nc) 3 and 4\n\nd)2 and 4 only",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only",
    "topic": "Indian Nationalism and Indian National Congress",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Balgangadhar Tilak was associated with\n\n1.Poona Sarvajanik Sabha\n\n2. The Age of Consent Bill\n\n3. Gaurakshini Sabha\n\n4.Atmiya Sabha\nSelect the correct answer using the given below :\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)1,2 and 4\n\nc) 3 and 4\n\nd)2 and 4 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name\nthe\nfirst\nmajor\nvoluntary\nassociation\nrepresenting\nprimarily Indian landlord interests that was set up in Calcutta\nin 18517\n\na) British Indian Association\n\nb)Landholder's Society\n\nc) Madras Native Association\n\nd)Bombay Association\nAnswer: \n(a) British Indian Association",
    "choices": "a) British Indian Association\n\nb)Landholder's Society\n\nc) Madras Native Association\n\nd)Bombay Association",
    "answer": "\n(a) British Indian Association",
    "topic": "Indian Nationalism and Indian National Congress",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Name the first major voluntary association representing primarily Indian landlord interests that was set up in Calcutta in 18517\n\n\na) British Indian Association\n\n\nb)Landholder's Society\n\n\nc) Madras Native Association\n\n\nd)Bombay Association",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\nof\nthe following\nwas/were\neconomic   critic/critics\nof\ncolonialism in India?\n\n1.Dadabhai Naoroji\n\n2. G. Subramania Iyer\n\n3.R: C. Dutt\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n\n(c) 2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n\n(c) 2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "topic": "Indian Nationalism and Indian National Congress",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who of the following was/were economic critic/critics of colonialism in India?\n\n\n1.Dadabhai Naoroji\n\n2. G. Subramania Iyer\n\n3.R: C. Dutt\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 2 only\n\nc) 2 and 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Ilbert Bill controversy was related to the\n\n(a) Imposition of certain restrictions to carry arms by the\nIndians.\n\n(b) Imposition\nof\nrestrictions\non\nnewspapers\nand\nmagazines published in Indian languages\n\n(c) Removal\nof disqualifications imposed\non\nthe\nIndian\nMagistrates with regard to the trial of the Europeans\n\n(d) Removal of a duty on imported cotton cloth:\nAnswer: \n(c) Removal of disqualifications imposed on the Indian\nMagistrates with regard to the trial of the Europeans",
    "choices": "\n(a) Imposition of certain restrictions to carry arms by the\nIndians.\n\n(b) Imposition\nof\nrestrictions\non\nnewspapers\nand\nmagazines published in Indian languages\n\n(c) Removal\nof disqualifications imposed\non\nthe\nIndian\nMagistrates with regard to the trial of the Europeans\n\n(d) Removal of a duty on imported cotton cloth:",
    "answer": "\n(c) Removal of disqualifications imposed on the Indian\nMagistrates with regard to the trial of the Europeans",
    "topic": "Indian Nationalism and Indian National Congress",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Ilbert Bill controversy was related to the\n\n\na) Imposition of certain restrictions to carry arms by the Indians.\n\n\nb) Imposition of restrictions on newspapers and magazines published in Indian languages\n\n\nc) Removal of disqualifications imposed on the Indian Magistrates with regard to the trial of the Europeans\n\n\nd) Removal of a duty on imported cotton cloth:",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which one of the following years was the Poona Sarvajanik\nSabha established?\n\na) 1884\n\nb) 1876\n\nc) 1869\n\nd) 1870\nAnswer: \n(d) 1870",
    "choices": "a) 1884\n\nb) 1876\n\nc) 1869\n\nd) 1870",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1870",
    "topic": "Indian Nationalism and Indian National Congress",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In which one of the following years was the Poona Sarvajanik Sabha established?\n\na) 1884\n\nb) 1876\n\nc) 1869\n\nd) 1870",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one among the following explains the meaning of the\n'Safety\nValve\nTheory'\nin\nthe\ncontext\nof\nIndian\nNational\nMovement?\n\na)A theory that argued that the Congress was formedas a safe\noutlet to the discontented educated Indians\nbJA theory that argued that the Congress was formedas a safe\noutlet to the hostile attitude of the British towards\n\nc)A theory which believed that the British and the ex-rebels\nof 1857 should amicably resolve their differences against\neach other\n\nd)An\nidea aimed\nat promoting goodwill among the Indian\npeople\nAnswer: \n(a) A theory that argued that the Congress was formed\nas a safe outlet to the discontented educated Indians",
    "choices": "a)A theory that argued that the Congress was formedas a safe\noutlet to the discontented educated Indians\nbJA theory that argued that the Congress was formedas a safe\noutlet to the hostile attitude of the British towards\n\nc)A theory which believed that the British and the ex-rebels\nof 1857 should amicably resolve their differences against\neach other\n\nd)An\nidea aimed\nat promoting goodwill among the Indian\npeople",
    "answer": "\n(a) A theory that argued that the Congress was formed\nas a safe outlet to the discontented educated Indians",
    "topic": "Indian Nationalism and Indian National Congress",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one among the following explains the meaning of the 'Safety Valve Theory' in the context of Indian National Movement?\n\na) A theory that argued that the Congress was formed as a safe outlet to the discontented educated Indians\n\nb) JA theory that argued that the Congress was formed as a safe outlet to the hostile attitude of the British towards\n\nc) A theory which believed that the British and the ex-rebels of 1857 should amicably resolve their differences against each other\n\nd) An idea aimed at promoting goodwill among the Indian people",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nConsider the following pairs:\n\n1.Radhakanta\nDeb\nFirst President of\nthe\nBritish\nIndian\nAssociation\n\n2. Gazulu\nLakshminarasu Chetty\nFounder of the\nMadras\nMahajana Sabha\n\n3.Surendranath\nBanerjee\nFounder\nof\nthe\nIndian\nAssociation\nWhich of the above pairs is/are correctly matched?\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1and 3 only\n2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(b) 1 and 3 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1and 3 only\n2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(b) 1 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Indian Nationalism and Indian National Congress",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following pairs:\n\n1.Radhakanta Deb First President of the British Indian Association\n\n2. Gazulu Lakshminarasu Chetty Founder of the Madras Mahajana Sabha\n\n3.Surendranath Banerjee Founder of the Indian Association\nWhich of the above pairs is/are correctly matched? \n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1and 3 only\n2 and 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nof\nthe following\nstatements\nabout\nthe\nfirst\nIndian\nFactory Act passed in 1881 is/are correct?\n\n1. The Act dealt primarily with the problem of child labour:\n\n2. The\nAct laid down that children between\n7\nyears and 12\nyears of age would not work for more than 9 hours a\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "Indian Nationalism and Indian National Congress",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the first Indian Factory Act passed in 1881 is/are correct? \n\n\n1. The Act dealt primarily with the problem of child labour: \n\n2. The Act laid down that children between 7 years and 12 years of age would not work for more than 9 hours a \n\n\na) 1 only \n\nb) 2 only \n\nc) Both 1 and 2 \n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Arrange the establishment of the following in a chronological\norder (starting with the earliest):\n\n1. The East India Association.\n\n2. The Poona Sarvajanik Sabha\n\n3.The Madras Mahajan Sabha\n\n4.The Bombay Presidency Association\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na)1,2,3,4\n6)1,3,2,4\n\nc) 2,3,4,1\n\nd)3, 2,1,4\nAnswer: \n(a) 1,2,3,4",
    "choices": "a)1,2,3,4\n6)1,3,2,4\n\nc) 2,3,4,1\n\nd)3, 2,1,4",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1,2,3,4",
    "topic": "Indian Nationalism and Indian National Congress",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Arrange the establishment of the following in a chronological order (starting with the earliest):\n\n\n1. The East India Association.\n\n2. The Poona Sarvajanik Sabha\n\n3. The Madras Mahajan Sabha\n\n4. The Bombay Presidency Association\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\na) 1,2,3,4\n\nb) 1,3,2,4\n\nc) 2,3,4,1\n\nd) 3, 2,1,4",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\namong\nthe  following\nstarted\nthe\nIndian\nAgriculture\nService?",
    "choices": "a) Lord Curzon\n\nb) William Bentinck\n\nc) Lord Minto\n\nd) Lord Rippon",
    "answer": "\n(c) Lord Minto",
    "topic": "Governors-General",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7b4be9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following started the Indian Agriculture Service?",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following Viceroys was the first to officially\nshift his Council to Simla in the summer season?",
    "choices": "a)John Lawrence\n\nb)Lord Dalhousie\n\nc) Lord Mayo\n\nd) William Bentinck",
    "answer": "\n(a) John Lawrence",
    "topic": "Governors-General",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7b4be9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following Viceroys was the first to officially shift his Council to Simla in the summer season?",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "The\nruins\nof Hampi\nwere brought to light by\nwhich\nof the\nfollowing British officers of the East India Company?",
    "choices": "a) Colonel Colin Mackenzie\n\nb)James Prinsep\n\nc) William Jones\n\nd)James Rennell",
    "answer": "\n(a) Colonel Colin Mackenzie",
    "topic": "Governors-General",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7b4be9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The ruins of Hampi were brought to light by which of the following British officers of the East India Company?",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following\nwere the founders\nof the\nHind\nMazdoor Sabha\"\nestablished in 1948?\n\n(a) B.\nKrishna\nPillai,\nE.MS.\nNamboodiripad\nand\nK.C.\nGeorge\n\n(b) Jayaprakash Narayan, Deen Dayal\nUpadhyay and M.N:\n\n(c) C.P Ramaswamy Iyer;\nK: Kamaraj and\nVeeresalingam\nPantulu\n\n(d) Ashok Mehta, T.S. Ramanujam and G.G. Mehta\nAnswer: \n(d) Ashok Mehta, T.S. Ramanujam and G.G. Mehta",
    "choices": "\n(a) B.\nKrishna\nPillai,\nE.MS.\nNamboodiripad\nand\nK.C.\nGeorge\n\n(b) Jayaprakash Narayan, Deen Dayal\nUpadhyay and M.N:\n\n(c) C.P Ramaswamy Iyer;\nK: Kamaraj and\nVeeresalingam\nPantulu\n\n(d) Ashok Mehta, T.S. Ramanujam and G.G. Mehta",
    "answer": "\n(d) Ashok Mehta, T.S. Ramanujam and G.G. Mehta",
    "topic": "Nationalism and Working Class",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_eed970__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following were the founders of the Hind Mazdoor Sabha established in 1948? \n\n\n(a) B. Krishna Pillai, E.MS. Namboodiripad and K.C. George \n\n\n(b) Jayaprakash Narayan, Deen Dayal Upadhyay and M.N: \n\n\n(c) C.P Ramaswamy Iyer; K: Kamaraj and Veeresalingam Pantulu \n\n\n(d) Ashok Mehta, T.S. Ramanujam and G.G. Mehta",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following was not a woman labour leader who\norganised workers in the strikes in the 1920s?\n\na) Sarala Devi Chaudhurani\n\nb)Ushabai Dange\n\nc) Prabhabati Devi\n\nd)Anasuya Behn\nAnswer: \n(a) Sarala Devi Chaudhurani\nRoy",
    "choices": "a) Sarala Devi Chaudhurani\n\nb)Ushabai Dange\n\nc) Prabhabati Devi\n\nd)Anasuya Behn",
    "answer": "\n(a) Sarala Devi Chaudhurani\nRoy",
    "topic": "Nationalism and Working Class",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_eed970__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following was not a woman labour leader who organised workers in the strikes in the 1920s?\n\na) Sarala Devi Chaudhurani\n\nb) Ushabai Dange\n\nc) Prabhabati Devi\n\nd) Anasuya Behn",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following created the first Al India Trade Union\nCongress in 1920?\n\na) B. P Wadia\n\nb)S. A. Dange\n\nc) N: M. Joshi\n\nd)B. T. Ranadive\nAnswer: \n(c) N. M. Joshi",
    "choices": "a) B. P Wadia\n\nb)S. A. Dange\n\nc) N: M. Joshi\n\nd)B. T. Ranadive",
    "answer": "\n(c) N. M. Joshi",
    "topic": "Nationalism and Working Class",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_eed970__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following created the first Al India Trade Union Congress in 1920? \n\n\n(a) B. P Wadia \n\n\n(b)S. A. Dange \n\n\n(c) N: M. Joshi \n\n\n(d)B. T. Ranadive",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one among the following was India's first trade union in\nthe proper sense of the term?\n\na) Bombay Labour Union\n\nb)Ahmedabad Labour Union\n\nc) Madras Labour Union\n\nd)Allahabad Labour Union\nAnswer: \n(c) Madras Labour Union",
    "choices": "a) Bombay Labour Union\n\nb)Ahmedabad Labour Union\n\nc) Madras Labour Union\n\nd)Allahabad Labour Union",
    "answer": "\n(c) Madras Labour Union",
    "topic": "Nationalism and Working Class",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_eed970__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one among the following was India's first trade union in the proper sense of the term?\n\n\na) Bombay Labour Union\n\n\nb) Ahmedabad Labour Union\n\n\nc) Madras Labour Union\n\n\nd) Allahabad Labour Union\n",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nConsider the following statements:\n\n1. The Factories Act, 1881\nwas passed with\na view to fix the\nwages of industrial\nworkers and\nto allow the\nworkers to\nform trade unions.\n\n2.N.M.\nLokhande\nwas\na\npioneer in\norganising the labour\nmovement in\nBritish India.\nWhich of the above statements is/are correct?\n\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 only\nBoth 1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(b) 2 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 only\nBoth 1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 only",
    "topic": "Nationalism and Working Class",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_eed970__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1. The Factories Act, 1881 was passed with a view to fix the wages of industrial workers and to allow the workers to form trade unions.\n\n2. N.M. Lokhande was a pioneer in organising the labour movement in British India.\nWhich of the above statements is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Match List-I with List-Il and select the correct answer using the\ncode given below the Lists:\nList-I (Movement)\nList-II (Mass base/Following)\nA.Bardoli Satyagraha\n\n1. Bargadars\nB. Tebhaga\n\n2. Kaliparaj\nC.Satyasodhak Samaj\n\n3. Mundas\nD.Ulgulan\n\n4. Kunbi peasantry\nCode :\nABCD\n\na)2413\n6)2143\n\nc) 3412\n\nd)3142\nAnswer: \n(b) 2143",
    "choices": "a)2413\n6)2143\n\nc) 3412\n\nd)3142",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2143",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 2",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8fb608__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Match List-I with List-Il and select the correct answer using the code given below the Lists:\n\nList-I (Movement)\nList-II (Mass base/Following)\n\nA. Bardoli Satyagraha  \n\n1. Bargadars \nB. Tebhaga  \n\n2. Kaliparaj \nC. Satyasodhak Samaj  \n\n3. Mundas \nD. Ulgulan  \n\n4. Kunbi peasantry \n\nCode :\nABCD\n\n\na) 2413 \n\nb) 2143 \n\nc) 3412 \n\nd) 3142",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "The elected President of the AIl India Kisan Sabha, which met\nin Vijayawada (1944), was\n\na) Sahajananda Saraswati\n\nb) Vinoba Bhave\n\nc) Achyut Rao Patwardhan\n\nd)Narendra Dev\nAnswer: \n(a) Sahajananda Saraswati",
    "choices": "a) Sahajananda Saraswati\n\nb) Vinoba Bhave\n\nc) Achyut Rao Patwardhan\n\nd)Narendra Dev",
    "answer": "\n(a) Sahajananda Saraswati",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 2",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8fb608__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The elected President of the AIl India Kisan Sabha, which met in Vijayawada (1944), was\n\n\na) Sahajananda Saraswati\n\n\nb) Vinoba Bhave\n\n\nc) Achyut Rao Patwardhan\n\n\nd)Narendra Dev",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Match List-I with List Il and select the correct answer using the\ncode given below the Lists\nList-I (Peasant Movement)\nList II (Leader/Follower)\nA.Bakasht Land Movement\n\n1. Baba Ramchandra\nB. Eka Movement\n\n2. Kunhammed Haji\nC.Mappila Rebellion\n\n3.Madari Pasi\nD.Avadh\nKisan\nSabha\nMovement\n\n4.Karyanand Sharma\nCode:\nABCD\n\na)4321\n\nb)4231\n\nc) 1234\n\nd)1324\nAnswer: \n(a) 4321",
    "choices": "a)4321\n\nb)4231\n\nc) 1234\n\nd)1324",
    "answer": "\n(a) 4321",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 2",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8fb608__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Match List-I with List Il and select the correct answer using the code given below the Lists\nList-I (Peasant Movement)\nList II (Leader/Follower)\nA. Bakasht Land Movement\n\n1. Baba Ramchandra\nB. Eka Movement\n\n2. Kunhammed Haji\nC. Mappila Rebellion\n\n3. Madari Pasi\nD. Avadh Kisan Sabha Movement\n\n4. Karyanand Sharma\nCode:\nABCD\n\na) 4321\n\nb) 4231\n\nc) 1234\n\nd) 1324",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "The demand for the Tebhaga Peasant Movement in Bengal was\nfor\n\n(a) the reduction of the share of the landlords from\none-\nhalf of the crop to\none-third\n\n(b) the grant of ownership of land to peasants asthey were\nthe actual cultivators of the land\n\n(c) the\nuprooting\nof Zamindari system\nand\nthe end\nof\nserfdom\n\n(d) writing off all peasant debts\nAnswer: \n(a) the reduction of the share of the landlords from\none-half of the crop to one-third",
    "choices": "\n(a) the reduction of the share of the landlords from\none-\nhalf of the crop to\none-third\n\n(b) the grant of ownership of land to peasants asthey were\nthe actual cultivators of the land\n\n(c) the\nuprooting\nof Zamindari system\nand\nthe end\nof\nserfdom\n\n(d) writing off all peasant debts",
    "answer": "\n(a) the reduction of the share of the landlords from\none-half of the crop to one-third",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 2",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8fb608__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The demand for the Tebhaga Peasant Movement in Bengal was for\n\n\na) the reduction of the share of the landlords from one-half of the crop to one-third\n\nb) the grant of ownership of land to peasants asthey were the actual cultivators of the land\n\nc) the uprooting of Zamindari system and the end of serfdom\n\nd) writing off all peasant debts",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\namong\nthe\nfollowing\nwas\nnot\nassociated\nwith\nthe\nformation of UP Kisan Sabha in February 1918?\n\n(a) Indra Narayan Dwivedi\n\n(b) Gauri Shankar Misra\n\n(c) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n(d) Madan Mohan Malviva\nAnswer: \n(c) Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "choices": "\n(a) Indra Narayan Dwivedi\n\n(b) Gauri Shankar Misra\n\n(c) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n(d) Madan Mohan Malviva",
    "answer": "\n(c) Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 2",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8fb608__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following was not associated with the formation of UP Kisan Sabha in February 1918?\n\n\na) Indra Narayan Dwivedi\n\nb) Gauri Shankar Misra\n\nc) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\nd) Madan Mohan Malviva",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following was not included in the terms and conditions of the Subsidiary Alliance System of Lord Wellesley?",
    "choices": "a) The British would protect their ally:\n\nb) The\nwas free to enter into agreements with other rulers\nor engage in warfare.\n\nc) In the territory of the\na British armed contingent would\nbe stationed:\n\nd) The\nwould\nhave\nto\nprovide\nresources\nfor\nthe\nmaintenance of the British armed contingent:",
    "answer": "\n(b) The ally was free to enter into agreements with other rulers or engage in warfare",
    "topic": "Role of Governors-General in the Consolidation and Expansion of British Power",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_523b44__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following was not included in the terms and conditions of the Subsidiary Alliance System of Lord Wellesley?",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following Europeans were the last to come to\npre-Independence of India as traders?\n\n(a) Dutch\n\n(b) English\n\n(c) French\n\n(d) Portuguese\nAnswer: \n(c) French",
    "choices": "\n(a) Dutch\n\n(b) English\n\n(c) French\n\n(d) Portuguese",
    "answer": "\n(c) French",
    "topic": "Beginning of European Settlements in India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_068542__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following Europeans were the last to come to pre-Independence of India as traders?\n\n\na) Dutch\n\nb) English\n\nc) French\n\nd) Portuguese",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following was the first fort constructed by the\nBritish in India?\n\n(a) Fort William\n\n(b) Fort St; George\n\n(c) Fort St. David\n\n(d) Fort St. Angelo\nAnswer: \n(b) Fort St. George",
    "choices": "\n(a) Fort William\n\n(b) Fort St; George\n\n(c) Fort St. David\n\n(d) Fort St. Angelo",
    "answer": "\n(b) Fort St. George",
    "topic": "Beginning of European Settlements in India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_068542__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following was the first fort constructed by the British in India?\n\n1. Fort William\n\n2. Fort St; George\n\n3. Fort St. David\n\n4. Fort St. Angelo",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "With\nreference\nto\nIndian\nhistory,\nconsider\nthe  following\nstatements:\n\n1. The Dutch established their factoriesl warehouses\non the\neast coast on lands granted to them by the Gajapati rulers.\n\n2. Alfonso de Albuquerque captured Goa\nfrom\nthe Bijapur\nSultanate:\n\n3.The English\nEast India Company established\na\nfactory\nat\nMadras on a plot of land leased from a representative of the\nVijayanagara empire.\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\n\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(b) 2 and 3 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Beginning of European Settlements in India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_068542__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to Indian history, consider the following statements:\n\n1. The Dutch established their factories/warehouses on the east coast on lands granted to them by the Gajapati rulers.\n\n2. Alfonso de Albuquerque captured Goa from the Bijapur Sultanate:\n\n3. The English East India Company established a factory at Madras on a plot of land leased from a representative of the Vijayanagara empire.\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\n\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n1 and 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the first quarter of the seventeenth century in which of the\nfollowing was/were the factory/factories of the English\nEast\nIndia Company located?\n1,Broach\n\n2. Chicacole\n\n3.\nTrichinopoly\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 2\n\nc) 3 only\n\nd)2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(a) 1 only",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 2\n\nc) 3 only\n\nd)2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 only",
    "topic": "Beginning of European Settlements in India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_068542__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In the first quarter of the seventeenth century in which of the following was/were the factory/factories of the English East India Company located?\n\n\n1. Broach\n\n\n2. Chicacole\n\n\n3. Trichinopoly\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\na) 1 only\n\n\nb) 1 and 2\n\n\nc) 3 only\n\n\nd) 2 and 3\n",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Beginning of European Settlements in India\nWho\namong\nthe\nfollowing\nrulers\nof\nmedieval\nGujarat\nsurrendered Diu to the Portuguese?\n\na)Ahmad Shah\n\nb) Mahmud Begarha\n\nc) Bahadur Shah\n\nd)Muhammad Shah\nAnswer: \n(c) Bahadur Shah",
    "choices": "a)Ahmad Shah\n\nb) Mahmud Begarha\n\nc) Bahadur Shah\n\nd)Muhammad Shah",
    "answer": "\n(c) Bahadur Shah",
    "topic": "Beginning of European Settlements in India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_068542__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Beginning of European Settlements in India\nWho among the following rulers of medieval Gujarat surrendered Diu to the Portuguese?\n\na) Ahmad Shah\n\nb) Mahmud Begarha\n\nc) Bahadur Shah\n\nd) Muhammad Shah",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "In India, among the following locations, the Dutch established\ntheir earliest factory at (2003)\n\n(a) Surat\n\n(b) Pulicat\n\n(c) Cochin\n\n(d) Cossimbazar\nAnswer: \n(b) Pulicat",
    "choices": "\n(a) Surat\n\n(b) Pulicat\n\n(c) Cochin\n\n(d) Cossimbazar",
    "answer": "\n(b) Pulicat",
    "topic": "Beginning of European Settlements in India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_068542__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In India, among the following locations, the Dutch established their earliest factory at (2003)\n\n\na) Surat\n\nb) Pulicat\n\nc) Cochin\n\nd) Cossimbazar",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to the entry of European powers into India\nwhich of the following is not correct?\n\na) The Portuguese captured Goa in 1499.\n\nb) The English opened their first factory in south\nIndian\nat\nMasulipatnam:\n\nc) In\nEastern\nIndia,\nthe\nEnglish\ncompany opened\nits\nfirst\nfactory in Orissa in 1633.\n\nd) Under\nthe leadership\nof\nDupleix,\nthe\nFrench\noccupied\nMadras in 1746.\nAnswer: \n(a) The Portuguese captured Goa in 1499",
    "choices": "a) The Portuguese captured Goa in 1499.\n\nb) The English opened their first factory in south\nIndian\nat\nMasulipatnam:\n\nc) In\nEastern\nIndia,\nthe\nEnglish\ncompany opened\nits\nfirst\nfactory in Orissa in 1633.\n\nd) Under\nthe leadership\nof\nDupleix,\nthe\nFrench\noccupied\nMadras in 1746.",
    "answer": "\n(a) The Portuguese captured Goa in 1499",
    "topic": "Beginning of European Settlements in India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_068542__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to the entry of European powers into India which of the following is not correct?\n\n\na) The Portuguese captured Goa in 1499.\n\n\nb) The English opened their first factory in south Indian at Masulipatnam:\n\n\nc) In Eastern India, the English company opened its first factory in Orissa in 1633.\n\n\nd) Under the leadership of Dupleix, the French occupied Madras in 1746.",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "The\nfollowing item\nconsists\nof statements: Statement\n7\nand\nStatement\nIl:\nExamine\nthese\ntwo\nstatements  carefully\nand\nselect the correct answer using the code below:\nCode:\n\na)Both statements are individually true, and Statement\nIlL is\nthe correct explanation of Statement /\n\nb)Both the statements are individually true, and Statement II\nis NOT the correct explanation of Statement |\n\nc) Statement\nis true, but Statement II is false\n\nd)Statement\nis false, but Statement Il is true\nStatement\nI:\nThe\nBritish\nruled\nIndia\nthrough\na\nmodern\nbureaucracy headed by the Indian Civil Service, whose members\nwere recruited through merit based on open competition\nStatement\nII:\nThe\nIndian\nCivil\nService\nwas\nbased\non\nthe\nwholehearted participation of Indians",
    "choices": "a)Both statements are individually true, and Statement\nIlL is\nthe correct explanation of Statement /\n\nb)Both the statements are individually true, and Statement II\nis NOT the correct explanation of Statement |\n\nc) Statement\nis true, but Statement II is false\n\nd)Statement\nis false, but Statement Il is true",
    "answer": "\n(c) Statement\nis true, but Statement II is false",
    "topic": "British Administration in India - II (1858-1947)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_3__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The following item consists of statements: Statement 7 and Statement Il: Examine these two statements carefully and select the correct answer using the code below: \n\nCode: \n\n\na) Both statements are individually true, and Statement IlL is the correct explanation of Statement / \n\nb) Both the statements are individually true, and Statement II is NOT the correct explanation of Statement | \n\nc) Statement is true, but Statement II is false \n\nd) Statement is false, but Statement Il is true \n\nStatement I: The British ruled India through a modern bureaucracy headed by the Indian Civil Service, whose members were recruited through merit based on open competition \n\nStatement II: The Indian Civil Service was based on the wholehearted participation of Indians",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following was NOT\na\nfeature of railways in\ncolonial India?\n\na) The main purpose of the setting up of railways in India was\nto serve the interest of the empire\n\nb)British\ncapital\ninvestments\nwere\ninvited\nwith\n15%\nguaranteed\ninterest\nto\nbe\nif necessary from\nIndian\nrevenues\n\nc) The construction work disturbed ecology\n\nd) The construction of the railways was planned, in such a way\nthat it connected the internal markets with the ports, but\nprovided\nno\ninter-\nconnection\nbetween\ninternal\nmarket\ncities\nAnswer: \n(b) British capital investments were invited with 15%\nguaranteed\ninterest\nto\nbe\npaid\nif\nnecessary\nfrom\nIndian\nrevenues\npaid",
    "choices": "a) The main purpose of the setting up of railways in India was\nto serve the interest of the empire\n\nb)British\ncapital\ninvestments\nwere\ninvited\nwith\n15%\nguaranteed\ninterest\nto\nbe\nif necessary from\nIndian\nrevenues\n\nc) The construction work disturbed ecology\n\nd) The construction of the railways was planned, in such a way\nthat it connected the internal markets with the ports, but\nprovided\nno\ninter-\nconnection\nbetween\ninternal\nmarket\ncities",
    "answer": "\n(b) British capital investments were invited with 15%\nguaranteed\ninterest\nto\nbe\npaid\nif\nnecessary\nfrom\nIndian\nrevenues\npaid",
    "topic": "British Economic Policies in India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_4__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following was NOT a feature of railways in colonial India? \n\n\na) The main purpose of the setting up of railways in India was to serve the interest of the empire \n\nb) British capital investments were invited with 15% guaranteed interest to be if necessary from Indian revenues \n\nc) The construction work disturbed ecology \n\nd) The construction of the railways was planned, in such a way that it connected the internal markets with the ports, but provided no inter-connection between internal market cities",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to the period of colonial rule in India, \"Home\nCharges\" formed an important part of the drain of wealth from\nIndia.\nWhich\nof\nthe\nfollowing\nfunds\nconstituted\n\"Home\nCharges\"?\n\n1.Funds used to support the India Office in London:\n\n2. Funds used to pay salaries and pensions of British personnel\nengaged in India.\n\n3.Funds used for waging wars outside India\nthe British.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(b) 1 and 2 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(b) 1 and 2 only",
    "topic": "British Economic Policies in India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_4__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to the period of colonial rule in India, \"Home Charges\" formed an important part of the drain of wealth from India.\n\nWhich of the following funds constituted \"Home Charges\"?\n\n\n1. Funds used to support the India Office in London:\n\n2. Funds used to pay salaries and pensions of British personnel engaged in India.\n\n3. Funds used for waging wars outside India the British.\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "In\nwhich\none of the following years was the first telegraphic\nconnection established between Europe and India?\n\na) 1851\n\nb)1854\n\nc) 1865\n\nd)1871\nAnswer: \n(c) 1865",
    "choices": "a) 1851\n\nb)1854\n\nc) 1865\n\nd)1871",
    "answer": "\n(c) 1865",
    "topic": "British Economic Policies in India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_4__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In which one of the following years was the first telegraphic connection established between Europe and India?\n\n\na) 1851\n\n\nb) 1854\n\n\nc) 1865\n\n\nd) 1871\n",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the Industrial Revolution,\nwho among the\nfollowing\ndesigned the 'flying shuttle loom'?\n\na) Samuel Crompton\n\nb)Edmund Cartwright\n\nc) John Kay\n\nd)Richard Arkwright\nAnswer: \n(c) John Kay",
    "choices": "a) Samuel Crompton\n\nb)Edmund Cartwright\n\nc) John Kay\n\nd)Richard Arkwright",
    "answer": "\n(c) John Kay",
    "topic": "British Economic Policies in India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_4__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "During the Industrial Revolution, who among the following designed the 'flying shuttle loom'?\n\n\na) Samuel Crompton\n\nb) Edmund Cartwright\n\nc) John Kay\n\nd) Richard Arkwright",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "In\nwhich\nof\nthe\nfollowing\nyears\nwere\npassenger\ntrains\nintroduced in England?\n\na) 1823\n\nb) 1825\n\nc) 1848\n\nd)1861\nAnswer: \n(b) 1825",
    "choices": "a) 1823\n\nb) 1825\n\nc) 1848\n\nd)1861",
    "answer": "\n(b) 1825",
    "topic": "British Economic Policies in India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_4__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In which of the following years were passenger trains introduced in England?\n\na) 1823\n\nb) 1825\n\nc) 1848\n\nd) 1861",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nWhich\nof\nthe  following\nstatements   correctly  explains\nthe\nimpact of the Industrial Revolution on India during the first half\nof the nineteenth century?\n\n(a) Indian handicrafts were ruined.\n\n(b) Machines were introduced in the Indian textile industry\nin large numbers.\n\n(c) Railway lines were laid in many parts of\nthe country:\n\n(d) Heavy duties were imposed\non the imports of British\nmanufactures.\nAnswer: \n(a) Indian handicrafts were ruined",
    "choices": "\n(a) Indian handicrafts were ruined.\n\n(b) Machines were introduced in the Indian textile industry\nin large numbers.\n\n(c) Railway lines were laid in many parts of\nthe country:\n\n(d) Heavy duties were imposed\non the imports of British\nmanufactures.",
    "answer": "\n(a) Indian handicrafts were ruined",
    "topic": "British Economic Policies in India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_4__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements correctly explains the impact of the Industrial Revolution on India during the first half of the nineteenth century? \n\n\na) Indian handicrafts were ruined.\n\nb) Machines were introduced in the Indian textile industry in large numbers.\n\nc) Railway lines were laid in many parts of the country:\n\nd) Heavy duties were imposed on the imports of British manufactures.",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Economically one ofthe results ofthe British rule in India in the\n19th century was the:\n\n(a) Increase in the export of Indian handicrafts\n\n(b) Growth in the number of Indian owned factories\n\n(c) Commercialisation of Indian agriculture\n\n(d) Rapid increase in the urban population\nAnswer: \n(c) Commercialisation of Indian agriculture",
    "choices": "\n(a) Increase in the export of Indian handicrafts\n\n(b) Growth in the number of Indian owned factories\n\n(c) Commercialisation of Indian agriculture\n\n(d) Rapid increase in the urban population",
    "answer": "\n(c) Commercialisation of Indian agriculture",
    "topic": "British Economic Policies in India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_4__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Economically one of the results of the British rule in India in the 19th century was the:\n\n\na) Increase in the export of Indian handicrafts\n\nb) Growth in the number of Indian owned factories\n\nc) Commercialisation of Indian agriculture\n\nd) Rapid increase in the urban population",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nof the following statements\nabout the\nArya  Samaj;\nwhich emerged in the late\ncentury; are correct?\n\n1.Had a very strong support base amongst the trading castes\n\n2. Introduced 'shuddhi'\nor mass\npurification\n\n3.The moderates in the Arya Samaj were headed by Hans Raj\nand Lajpat Rai and set up a chain of Dayanand Anglo-Vedic\ncolleges\n\n4. The Arya Samaj had fewer members than the Brahmo Samaj\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)1,2 and 3\n\nc) 3 and 4 only\n\nd)1, 3 and 4\nAnswer: \n(b) 1, 2 and 3 ",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)1,2 and 3\n\nc) 3 and 4 only\n\nd)1, 3 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(b) 1, 2 and 3",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the Arya Samaj, which emerged in the late century, are correct? \n\n\n1. Had a very strong support base amongst the trading castes \n\n2. Introduced 'shuddhi' or mass purification \n\n3. The moderates in the Arya Samaj were headed by Hans Raj and Lajpat Rai and set up a chain of Dayanand Anglo-Vedic colleges \n\n4. The Arya Samaj had fewer members than the Brahmo Samaj\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below: \n\n\na) 1 and 2 only \n\nb) 1,2 and 3 \n\nc) 3 and 4 only \n\nd) 1, 3 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "19th\nSwami Dayanand Saraswati\n\n1.was\nopposed\nto\nthe\nworship\nof\nidols\nof\nGods\nand\nGoddesses.\n\n2.Regarded the Vedas as infallible:\n\n3.Had\nmet\nand\nhad\ndiscussions\nwith\nIshwar\nChandra\nVidyasagar\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\n\na) 1,2 and 3\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd)1 and 2only\nAnswer: \n(a) 1,2 and 3 ",
    "choices": "a) 1,2 and 3\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd)1 and 2only",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1,2 and 3",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "19th Swami Dayanand Saraswati\n\n1.was opposed to the worship of idols of Gods and Goddesses.\n\n2.Regarded the Vedas as infallible.\n\n3.Had met and had discussions with Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\n\na) 1,2 and 3\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 1 and 2only",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "The\nfounders\nof\nthe\nParamhansa\nMandali\nfounded\nin\nMaharashtra believed in which one of the following?\n\na) Social distancing along caste lines\n\nb) Glorification of caste system\n\nc) Forbidding widow remarriage\n\nd) One God and in breaking caste rules\nAnswer: \n(d) One God and in breaking caste rules ",
    "choices": "a) Social distancing along caste lines\n\nb) Glorification of caste system\n\nc) Forbidding widow remarriage\n\nd) One God and in breaking caste rules",
    "answer": "\n(d) One God and in breaking caste rules",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The founders of the Paramhansa Mandali founded in Maharashtra believed in which one of the following?\n\n\na) Social distancing along caste lines\n\n\nb) Glorification of caste system\n\n\nc) Forbidding widow remarriage\n\n\nd) One God and in breaking caste rules\n",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the\nfollowing pairs of books and their authors is\nnot correctly matched?\n\na) Bandi Jiwan: Sachindranath Sanyal\n\nb)The Philosophy of the Bomb: Bhagwati Charan Vohra\n\nc) Indian Unrest: Annie Besant\n\nd)Desher Katha: Sakharam Ganesh Deuskar\nAnswer: \n(c) Indian Unrest: Annie Besant ",
    "choices": "a) Bandi Jiwan: Sachindranath Sanyal\n\nb)The Philosophy of the Bomb: Bhagwati Charan Vohra\n\nc) Indian Unrest: Annie Besant\n\nd)Desher Katha: Sakharam Ganesh Deuskar",
    "answer": "\n(c) Indian Unrest: Annie Besant",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following pairs of books and their authors is not correctly matched?\n\n\na) Bandi Jiwan: Sachindranath Sanyal\n\nb) The Philosophy of the Bomb: Bhagwati Charan Vohra\n\nc) Indian Unrest: Annie Besant\n\nd) Desher Katha: Sakharam Ganesh Deuskar",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following founded the Dharma Sabha?\n\na) Krishna Mohan Banerjee\n\nb)Keshab Chandra Sen\n\nc) Radhakanta Deb\n\nd)Akshay Kumar Datta\nAnswer: \n(c) Radhakanta Deb ",
    "choices": "a) Krishna Mohan Banerjee\n\nb)Keshab Chandra Sen\n\nc) Radhakanta Deb\n\nd)Akshay Kumar Datta",
    "answer": "\n(c) Radhakanta Deb",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following founded the Dharma Sabha? \n\n\na) Krishna Mohan Banerjee\n\nb)Keshab Chandra Sen\n\nc) Radhakanta Deb\n\nd)Akshay Kumar Datta",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following events:\n\n1. Foundation of the Ramakrishna Mission\n\n2. Foundation of the Arya Samaj\n\n3. Foundation of the Brahmo Samaj\n\n4.Foundation of the Paramhans Mandali\nWhich one of the following is the correct chronological order\nof the above?\n\na) 1,2,3,4\n6)2,3,4,1\n\nc) 3,4,1,2\n\nd)3,4,2,1\nAnswer: \n(d) 3,4,2,1 ",
    "choices": "a) 1,2,3,4\n6)2,3,4,1\n\nc) 3,4,1,2\n\nd)3,4,2,1",
    "answer": "\n(d) 3,4,2,1",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following events:\n\n1. Foundation of the Ramakrishna Mission\n\n2. Foundation of the Arya Samaj\n\n3. Foundation of the Brahmo Samaj\n\n4. Foundation of the Paramhans Mandali\nWhich one of the following is the correct chronological order of the above?\n\na) 1,2,3,4\n\nb) 2,3,4,1\n\nc) 3,4,1,2\n\nd) 3,4,2,1",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following was/were founded by Raja Ram Mohan\nRoy?\n\n1.Atmiya Sabha\n\n2. Brahmo Samaj\n\n3.Prarthana Samaj\n\n4.Arya Samaj\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1, 2 and 3\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) 1 and 2 only\n\nd)1,3 and 4\nAnswer: \n(c) 1 and 2 only ",
    "choices": "a) 1, 2 and 3\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) 1 and 2 only\n\nd)1,3 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(c) 1 and 2 only",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following was/were founded by Raja Ram Mohan Roy?\n\n\n1. Atmiya Sabha\n\n\n2. Brahmo Samaj\n\n\n3. Prarthana Samaj\n\n\n4. Arya Samaj\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\na) 1, 2 and 3\n\n\nb) 2 only\n\n\nc) 1 and 2 only\n\n\nd) 1, 3 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following:\n\n1. Calcutta Unitarian Committee\n\n2. Tabernacle of New Dispensation\n\n3. Indian Reform Association\nKeshab Chandra Sen is associated with the establishment of\nwhich of the above?\n\n(a) 1 and 3 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(b) 2 and 3 only ",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 3 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following:\n\n\n1. Calcutta Unitarian Committee\n\n\n2. Tabernacle of New Dispensation\n\n\n3. Indian Reform Association\n\nKeshab Chandra Sen is associated with the establishment of which of the above?\n\n\na) 1 and 3 only\n\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n\n\nc) 3 only\n\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\namong\nthe  following\nis\nthe\nauthor\nof\nthe\nbook,\nA\nComparison between Women and Men?\n\na) Pandita Ramabai\n\nb)Sarojini Naidu\n\nc) Tarabai Shinde\n\nd)Rameshwari Nehru\nAnswer: \n(c) Tarabai Shinde ",
    "choices": "a) Pandita Ramabai\n\nb)Sarojini Naidu\n\nc) Tarabai Shinde\n\nd)Rameshwari Nehru",
    "answer": "\n(c) Tarabai Shinde",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following is the author of the book, A Comparison between Women and Men?\n\na) Pandita Ramabai\n\nb) Sarojini Naidu\n\nc) Tarabai Shinde\n\nd) Rameshwari Nehru",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the social base of the\nArya Samaj in British India is/are correct?\n\n1.It was located mainly in Punjab and western Uttar Pradesh:\n\n2.It mainly comprised the trading castes.\n\n3.It was much more limited than that of the Brahmo Samaj:\nSelect the correct answer\nusing the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 only\n\nd)1,2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(a) 1 and 2 only ",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 only\n\nd)1,2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the social base of the Arya Samaj in British India is/are correct?\n\n1. It was located mainly in Punjab and western Uttar Pradesh:\n\n2. It mainly comprised the trading castes.\n\n3. It was much more limited than that of the Brahmo Samaj:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 only\n\nd) 1,2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct?\n\n1. Parmahansa\nMandali\nwas\nfounded\nin\nBengal\nby\nSwami\nVivekananda\n\n2. Prarthana Samaj was started in Maharashtra with the aim\nof reforming Hindu religious thought and practice:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below :\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(b) 2 only ",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 only",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct?\n\n\n1. Parmahansa Mandali was founded in Bengal by Swami Vivekananda\n\n2. Prarthana Samaj was started in Maharashtra with the aim of reforming Hindu religious thought and practice\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nIn the context of Indian history, the Rakhmabai case of 1884\nrevolved around: (2020)\n\n1. Women's right to\neducation\n2 .\nof consent\n\n3.Restitution of conjugal rights\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(b) 2 and 3 only ",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In the context of Indian history, the Rakhmabai case of 1884 revolved around: (2020)\n\n\n1. Women's right to education\n\n\n2. of consent\n\n\n3. Restitution of conjugal rights\n\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which among the following events happened earliest\n\n(a) Swami Dayanand established Arya Samaj:\n\n(b) Dinabandhu Mitra wrote Neel Darpan:\n\n(c) Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyay wrote Anandmath:\n\n(d) Satyendranath\nTagore\nbecame\nthe\nfirst\nIndian\nto\nsucceed in the Indian Civil Services Examination:\nAnswer: \n(b) Dinabandhu Mitra wrote Neel Darpan ",
    "choices": "\n(a) Swami Dayanand established Arya Samaj:\n\n(b) Dinabandhu Mitra wrote Neel Darpan:\n\n(c) Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyay wrote Anandmath:\n\n(d) Satyendranath\nTagore\nbecame\nthe\nfirst\nIndian\nto\nsucceed in the Indian Civil Services Examination:",
    "answer": "\n(b) Dinabandhu Mitra wrote Neel Darpan",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which among the following events happened earliest \n\n\na) Swami Dayanand established Arya Samaj: \n\nb) Dinabandhu Mitra wrote Neel Darpan: \n\nc) Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyay wrote Anandmath: \n\nd) Satyendranath Tagore became the first Indian to succeed in the Indian Civil Services Examination:",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "gain\nAge\nWhich of the following ideas was preached by the Kherwar or\nSapha Har movement of the 1870s\n\na)Acceptance of the Hindu pantheonic order\n\nb)Monotheism and internal social reform\n\nc) Philosophy of Yoga and Mimansa\n\nd)Polytheism\nAnswer: \n(b) Monotheism and internal social reform ",
    "choices": "a)Acceptance of the Hindu pantheonic order\n\nb)Monotheism and internal social reform\n\nc) Philosophy of Yoga and Mimansa\n\nd)Polytheism",
    "answer": "\n(b) Monotheism and internal social reform",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following ideas was preached by the Kherwar or Sapha Har movement of the 1870s \n\n\na) Acceptance of the Hindu pantheonic order \n\nb) Monotheism and internal social reform \n\nc) Philosophy of Yoga and Mimansa \n\nd) Polytheism",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "The \"Tattvabodhini Sabha was established by\n\na) Devendranath Tagore in 1839\n\nb)Keshab Chandra Sen in 1857\n\nC)\nAkshay Kumar Datta in 1850\n\nd)Dwarakanath Tagore in 1840\nAnswer: \n(a) Devendranath Tagore ",
    "choices": "a) Devendranath Tagore in 1839\n\nb)Keshab Chandra Sen in 1857\n\nC)\nAkshay Kumar Datta in 1850\n\nd)Dwarakanath Tagore in 1840",
    "answer": "\n(a) Devendranath Tagore",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The \"Tattvabodhini Sabha was established by\n\na) Devendranath Tagore in 1839\n\nb) Keshab Chandra Sen in 1857\n\nc) Akshay Kumar Datta in 1850\n\nd) Dwarakanath Tagore in 1840",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following wrote the book Babuvivah?\n\n(a) Raja Rammohan\n\n(b) Ishwar Chandra\nVidyasagar\n\n(c) Pandita Ramabai\n\n(d) Rabindranath Tagore\nAnswer: \n(b) Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar ",
    "choices": "\n(a) Raja Rammohan\n\n(b) Ishwar Chandra\nVidyasagar\n\n(c) Pandita Ramabai\n\n(d) Rabindranath Tagore",
    "answer": "\n(b) Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following wrote the book Babuvivah?\n\na) Raja Rammohan\n\nb) Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar\n\nc) Pandita Ramabai\n\nd) Rabindranath Tagore",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Lectures from Colombo to Almora is based on the experiences\nof which of the following?\n\n(a) Veer Savarkar\n\n(b) Annie Besant\n\n(c) Ramakrishna Paramhans\n\n(d) Swami Vivekananda\nAnswer: \n(d) Swami Vivekananda ",
    "choices": "\n(a) Veer Savarkar\n\n(b) Annie Besant\n\n(c) Ramakrishna Paramhans\n\n(d) Swami Vivekananda",
    "answer": "\n(d) Swami Vivekananda",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Lectures from Colombo to Almora is based on the experiences of which of the following?\n\n\na) Veer Savarkar\n\nb) Annie Besant\n\nc) Ramakrishna Paramhans\n\nd) Swami Vivekananda",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following was a proponent of Fabianism as a\nmovement?\n\n(a) Annie Besant\n\n(b) Michael Madhusudan Dutt\n\n(c) A. 0. Hume\n\n(d) R: Palme Dutt\nAnswer: \n(a) Annie Besant ",
    "choices": "\n(a) Annie Besant\n\n(b) Michael Madhusudan Dutt\n\n(c) A. 0. Hume\n\n(d) R: Palme Dutt",
    "answer": "\n(a) Annie Besant",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following was a proponent of Fabianism as a movement? \n\na) Annie Besant\n\nb) Michael Madhusudan Dutt\n\nc) A. 0. Hume\n\nd) R: Palme Dutt",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Roy\nConsider the following statements\n\n1. Muhammadan\nAnglo-Oriental\nCollege\nwas\nfounded\nat\nAligarh by Sayyid Ahmad Khan:\n\n2. Sayyid\nAhmad\nKhan\nwas\na\ngreat\nbeliever\nin\nreligious\ntolerance,\nand\nHindus,\nParsis\nand\nChristians\nhad\ncontributed to the funds of his college:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(c) Both 1 and 2 ",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements\n\n1. Muhammadan Anglo-Oriental College was founded at Aligarh by Sayyid Ahmad Khan:\n\n2. Sayyid Ahmad Khan was a great believer in religious tolerance, and Hindus, Parsis and Christians had contributed to the funds of his college:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the social reformer;\nRaja Rammohun\nis false?\n\na) Rammohun\nbelonged to the gentry class whose power\nhad\nbeen\ndiminished\nbecause\nf\nthe imposition\nof\nthe\nPermanent Settlement.\n\nb)He\nstudied\nboth\nVedantic\nMonism\nand\nChristian\nUnitarianism.\nC\nHe translated the Upanishads into Bengali.\n\nd)His first organization\nwas\nthe Atmiya Sabha, founded\nin\nCalcutta in 1815.\nAnswer: \n(a) ",
    "choices": "a) Rammohun\nbelonged to the gentry class whose power\nhad\nbeen\ndiminished\nbecause\nf\nthe imposition\nof\nthe\nPermanent Settlement.\n\nb)He\nstudied\nboth\nVedantic\nMonism\nand\nChristian\nUnitarianism.\nC\nHe translated the Upanishads into Bengali.\n\nd)His first organization\nwas\nthe Atmiya Sabha, founded\nin\nCalcutta in 1815.",
    "answer": "\n(a)",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the social reformer Raja Rammohun is false?\n\n\n(a) Rammohun belonged to the gentry class whose power had been diminished because f the imposition of the Permanent Settlement.\n\n\n(b) He studied both Vedantic Monism and Christian Unitarianism.\n\n\n(C) He translated the Upanishads into Bengali.\n\n\n(d) His first organization was the Atmiya Sabha, founded in Calcutta in 1815.",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Rammohun\nbelonged\nto\nthe\ngentry\nclass\nwhose power had been diminished because of the imposition\nof the Permanent Settlement\nRoy,\nRoy\nRoy\nWho among the following founded the Hindu Dharma Sabha in\nthe\ncentury?\n\na) Radhakanta Deb\n\nb)Ram Mohan\n\nc) Dwarkanath Tagore\n\nd)Keshab Chandra Sen\nAnswer: \n(a) Radhakanta Deb ",
    "choices": "a) Radhakanta Deb\n\nb)Ram Mohan\n\nc) Dwarkanath Tagore\n\nd)Keshab Chandra Sen",
    "answer": "\n(a) Radhakanta Deb",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Rammohun belonged to the gentry class whose power had been diminished because of the imposition of the Permanent Settlement Roy Roy Roy Who among the following founded the Hindu Dharma Sabha in the century?\n\n\na) Radhakanta Deb\n\nb) Ram Mohan\n\nc) Dwarkanath Tagore\n\nd) Keshab Chandra Sen",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following founded the Atmiya Sabha in 1815?\n\na) Keshab Chandra Sen\n\nb)Debendranath Tagore\n\nc) Ram Mohan\n\nd)Bijoy Krishna Goswami\nAnswer: \n(c) Ram Mohan ",
    "choices": "a) Keshab Chandra Sen\n\nb)Debendranath Tagore\n\nc) Ram Mohan\n\nd)Bijoy Krishna Goswami",
    "answer": "\n(c) Ram Mohan",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following founded the Atmiya Sabha in 1815?\n\n\na) Keshab Chandra Sen\n\nb) Debendranath Tagore\n\nc) Ram Mohan\n\nd) Bijoy Krishna Goswami",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "19th\nRoy\nRoy\nRoy\nWho\namong\nthe\nfollowing\nwas\npopularly\nknown\nas\n'Lokahitwadi'?\n\na) Gopal Hari Deshmukh\n\nb)Mahadev Govind Ranade\n\nc) Gopal Krishna Gokhale\n\nd)Jyotiba Phule\nAnswer: \n(a) Gopal Hari Deshmukh ",
    "choices": "a) Gopal Hari Deshmukh\n\nb)Mahadev Govind Ranade\n\nc) Gopal Krishna Gokhale\n\nd)Jyotiba Phule",
    "answer": "\n(a) Gopal Hari Deshmukh",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following was popularly known as 'Lokahitwadi'?\n\n\na) Gopal Hari Deshmukh \n\nb) Mahadev Govind Ranade \n\nc) Gopal Krishna Gokhale \n\nd) Jyotiba Phule",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Swami Dayanand Saraswati took inspiration from\n\na) Puranas\n\nb) Vedas\n\nc) Medieval saints\n\nd)Sufism\nAnswer: \n(b) Vedas ",
    "choices": "a) Puranas\n\nb) Vedas\n\nc) Medieval saints\n\nd)Sufism",
    "answer": "\n(b) Vedas",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Swami Dayanand Saraswati took inspiration from\n\n\na) Puranas\n\nb) Vedas\n\nc) Medieval saints\n\nd) Sufism",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "During\nthe\ncentury,\nwho\namong\nthe\nfollowing\nwrote\nSatapatra Series?\n\na)M: G. Ranade\n\nb) G. Tilak\n\nc) Bankim Chandra Chatterjee\n\nd)G. H: Deshmukh\nAnswer: \n(d) G. H. Deshmukh ",
    "choices": "a)M: G. Ranade\n\nb) G. Tilak\n\nc) Bankim Chandra Chatterjee\n\nd)G. H: Deshmukh",
    "answer": "\n(d) G. H. Deshmukh",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "During the century, who among the following wrote Satapatra Series? \n\n\na) M: G. Ranade \n\nb) G. Tilak \n\nc) Bankim Chandra Chatterjee \n\nd) G. H: Deshmukh",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following founded the Mohammedan Anglo-\nOriental Defence Association (1893)?\n\na)Auckland Colvin\n\nb) Badruddin Tyabji\n\nc) Theodore Beck\n\nd)Sir Syed Ahmad Khan\nAnswer: \n(d) Sir Syed Ahmad Khan ",
    "choices": "a)Auckland Colvin\n\nb) Badruddin Tyabji\n\nc) Theodore Beck\n\nd)Sir Syed Ahmad Khan",
    "answer": "\n(d) Sir Syed Ahmad Khan",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following founded the Mohammedan Anglo-Oriental Defence Association (1893)?\n\na) Auckland Colvin\n\nb) Badruddin Tyabji\n\nc) Theodore Beck\n\nd) Sir Syed Ahmad Khan",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "19th\nWhich of the following statements about\nBarnaparichay' ,\na\nmid 192 century Bengali text is/are correct?\n\n1.It was written by Raja Rammohan\n\n2.It was the most widely used Bengali primer of the time\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(b) 2 only ",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 only",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "19th \n\nWhich of the following statements about 'Barnaparichay', a mid 192 century Bengali text is/are correct? \n\n\n1.It was written by Raja Rammohan \n\n\n2.It was the most widely used Bengali primer of the time \n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below: \n\n\n(a) 1 only \n\n\n(b)2 only \n\n\n(c) Both 1and 2 \n\n\n(d)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who founded the Central Hindu School at Benaras which was\nlater developed into Benaras Hindu University?\n\na) Madan Mohan Malaviya\n\nb)Annie Besant\n\nc) Ishwar Chandra\nVidyasagar\n\nd)Madame H.P Blavatsky\nAnswer: \n(b) Annie Besant ",
    "choices": "a) Madan Mohan Malaviya\n\nb)Annie Besant\n\nc) Ishwar Chandra\nVidyasagar\n\nd)Madame H.P Blavatsky",
    "answer": "\n(b) Annie Besant",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who founded the Central Hindu School at Benaras which was later developed into Benaras Hindu University?\n\na) Madan Mohan Malaviya\n\nb) Annie Besant\n\nc) Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar\n\nd) Madame H.P Blavatsky",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Roy\nWhich\nof\nthe   following\nstatements\nabout\nIshwarchandra\nVidyasagar is/are NOT correct?\n\n1. Vidyasagar's writings significantly helped\nto develop the\nBengali language\n\n2. He received the title 'Vidyasagar' from Presidency College,\nKolkata\n\n3.He was enthusiastic about the spread of women's education\n\n4.\nVidyasagar\ndefended\nwidow\nmarriage\nwithout\nbeing\nconvinced about scriptural support\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 2 and 4\n\nb) 1 and 2\n\nc) 4 only\n\nd)3\nAnswer: \n(a) 2 and 4 ",
    "choices": "a) 2 and 4\n\nb) 1 and 2\n\nc) 4 only\n\nd)3",
    "answer": "\n(a) 2 and 4",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Roy Which of the following statements about Ishwarchandra Vidyasagar is/are NOT correct?\n\n1. Vidyasagar's writings significantly helped to develop the Bengali language.\n\n2. He received the title 'Vidyasagar' from Presidency College, Kolkata.\n\n3. He was enthusiastic about the spread of women's education.\n\n4. Vidyasagar defended widow marriage without being convinced about scriptural support.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 2 and 4\n\nb) 1 and 2\n\nc) 4 only\n\nd) 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Annie Besant was:\n\n1.Responsible for starting the Home Rule\nMovement:\n\n2. The founder of the Theosophical Society:\n\n3.Once the President of the Indian National Congress.\nSelect the correct statement/statements using the code given\nbelow:\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(c) 1 and 3 only ",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(c) 1 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Annie Besant was:\n\n1. Responsible for starting the Home Rule Movement:\n\n2. The founder of the Theosophical Society:\n\n3. Once the President of the Indian National Congress.\nSelect the correct statement/statements using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1.Arya Samaj was founded in 1835.\n\n2.Lala\nLajpat\nRai\nopposed\nArya\nSamaj's\nappeal\nto\nthe\nauthority\nof\nthe\nVedas\nin\nsupport\nof\nits\nsocial\nreform\nprogrammes.\n\n3.Under Keshab Chandra Sen, the Brahmo Samaj campaigned\nfor women's education.\n4,Vinobha\nBhave\nfounded\nthe\nSarvodaya\nSamaj\nto\nwork\namong refugees.\nWhich of the following statements given above is/are correct?\n\n(a) 1 and 2\n\n(b) 2 and 3\n\n(c) 2 and 4\n\n(d) 3 and 4\nAnswer: \n(d) 3 and 4 ",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2\n\n(b) 2 and 3\n\n(c) 2 and 4\n\n(d) 3 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(d) 3 and 4",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n\n1. Arya Samaj was founded in 1835.\n\n\n2. Lala Lajpat Rai opposed Arya Samaj's appeal to the authority of the Vedas in support of its social reform programmes.\n\n\n3. Under Keshab Chandra Sen, the Brahmo Samaj campaigned for women's education. \n\n\n4. Vinobha Bhave founded the Sarvodaya Samaj to work among refugees. \n\nWhich of the following statements given above is/are correct?\n\n\na) 1 and 2\n\n\nb) 2 and 3\n\n\nc) 2 and 4\n\n\nd) 3 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements about Syed Ahmed Khan,\nthe founder of Muhammadan Anglo-Oriental College, Aligarh:\n\n1.He was a staunch supporter ofthe Indian National Congress:\n\n2. Muhammadan Anglo-Oriental College was set up with the\nobjective of promoting learning of Islamic education among\nMuslims.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(d) Neither 1 nor 2 ",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements about Syed Ahmed Khan, the founder of Muhammadan Anglo-Oriental College, Aligarh:\nHe was a staunch supporter of the Indian National Congress.\nMuhammadan Anglo-Oriental College was set up with the objective of promoting learning of Islamic education among Muslims.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\namong\nthe\nfollowing\nwas\nnot\nassociated\nwith\nthe\nactivities of the Theosophical Society?\n\na) Madame H. P Blavatsky\n\nb)Mr: A. 0. Hume\n\nc) Col: H: S. Olcott\n\nd)Mrs. Annie Besant\nAnswer: \n(b) A: 0_ ",
    "choices": "a) Madame H. P Blavatsky\n\nb)Mr: A. 0. Hume\n\nc) Col: H: S. Olcott\n\nd)Mrs. Annie Besant",
    "answer": "\n(b) A: 0_",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following was not associated with the activities of the Theosophical Society?\n\na) Madame H. P Blavatsky\n\nb) Mr: A. 0. Hume\n\nc) Col: H: S. Olcott\n\nd) Mrs. Annie Besant",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hume\nWhich\none of the following statements about Tattvabodhini\nPatrika is correct?\n\na) It promoted a systematic study of India's past in the Bengali\nlanguage.\n\nb)lt promoted\na\nsystematic study\nof\nIndia's\npast through\nSanskrit sources.\n\nc) It promoted\na\nsystematic  study\nof\nIndia's\npast through\nPersian sources.\n\nd)lt promoted\na\nsystematic study\nof\nIndia's\npast through\nWestern sources.\nAnswer: \n(a) It promoted a systematic study of India's past in ",
    "choices": "a) It promoted a systematic study of India's past in the Bengali\nlanguage.\n\nb)lt promoted\na\nsystematic study\nof\nIndia's\npast through\nSanskrit sources.\n\nc) It promoted\na\nsystematic  study\nof\nIndia's\npast through\nPersian sources.\n\nd)lt promoted\na\nsystematic study\nof\nIndia's\npast through\nWestern sources.",
    "answer": "\n(a) It promoted a systematic study of India's past in ",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Hume\n\nWhich one of the following statements about Tattvabodhini Patrika is correct?\n\n\na) It promoted a systematic study of India's past in the Bengali language.\n\nb) It promoted a systematic study of India's past through Sanskrit sources.\n\nc) It promoted a systematic  study of India's past through Persian sources.\n\nd) It promoted a systematic study of India's past through Western sources.",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "the Bengali language:\nWho among the following was known as Lokhitwadi'?\n\na) Keshub Chandra Sen\n\nb) Gopal Hari Deshmukh\n\nc) M.G. Ranade\n\nd) Gopal Ganesh Agarkar\nAnswer: \n(b) Gopal Hari Deshmukh ",
    "choices": "a) Keshub Chandra Sen\n\nb) Gopal Hari Deshmukh\n\nc) M.G. Ranade\n\nd) Gopal Ganesh Agarkar",
    "answer": "\n(b) Gopal Hari Deshmukh",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "the Bengali language:\nWho among the following was known as Lokhitwadi'? \n\n\na) Keshub Chandra Sen\n\nb) Gopal Hari Deshmukh\n\nc) M.G. Ranade\n\nd) Gopal Ganesh Agarkar",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nof the following statements is/are\ncorrect regarding\nBrahmo Samaj?\n\n1. It opposed idolatry:\n\n2.It denied the need for\na\npriestly class for interpreting the\nreligious texts.\n\n3.It\npopularized the doctrine that the\nVedas are infallible:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n\n(c) 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(b) 1 and 2 only ",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n\n(c) 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(b) 1 and 2 only",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct regarding Brahmo Samaj?\n\n\n1. It opposed idolatry:\n\n\n2.It denied the need for a priestly class for interpreting the religious texts.\n\n\n3.It popularized the doctrine that the Vedas are infallible:\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n\n\n(c) 3 only\n\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\none among the following is\nnot true of the\nBrahmo\nSamaj?\n\na) It considered Vedic scriptures as infallible\n\nb)lt opposed idolatry\n\nc) It emphasised the worship of one God\n\nd)it emphasised the worship of God without the mediation of\npriests\nAnswer: \n(a) It considered Vedic scriptures as infallible ",
    "choices": "a) It considered Vedic scriptures as infallible\n\nb)lt opposed idolatry\n\nc) It emphasised the worship of one God\n\nd)it emphasised the worship of God without the mediation of\npriests",
    "answer": "\n(a) It considered Vedic scriptures as infallible",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one among the following is not true of the Brahmo Samaj?\n\na) It considered Vedic scriptures as infallible\n\nb) lt opposed idolatry\n\nc) It emphasised the worship of one God\n\nd) it emphasised the worship of God without the mediation of priests",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one among the following is not true of the Theosophical\nSociety of Madam HP Blavatsky?\n\na)It was founded outside India.\n\nb)It advocated the revival of ancient religions\n\nc) It recognised the doctrine of transmigration of the soul\n\nd)lt was silent on the idea of Universal Brotherhood\nAnswer: \n(d) It was silent on the idea of Universal Brotherhood ",
    "choices": "a)It was founded outside India.\n\nb)It advocated the revival of ancient religions\n\nc) It recognised the doctrine of transmigration of the soul\n\nd)lt was silent on the idea of Universal Brotherhood",
    "answer": "\n(d) It was silent on the idea of Universal Brotherhood",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one among the following is not true of the Theosophical Society of Madam HP Blavatsky?\n\na) It was founded outside India.\n\nb) It advocated the revival of ancient religions\n\nc) It recognised the doctrine of transmigration of the soul\n\nd) It was silent on the idea of Universal Brotherhood",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "During\nthe\nIndian\nfreedom\nstruggle,\nthe\nNational\nSocial\nConference\nwas\nformed.\nWhat\nwas\nthe\nreason\nfor\nits\nformation?\n\n(a) Different social reform groups\nor\norganisations of the\nBengal region united to form\na\nsingle body to discuss the\nissues\nof\nlarger\ninterest\nand\nto\nprepare   appropriate\npetitions/ representations to the government:\n\n(b) Indian National Congress did not\nwant to include social\nreforms in its deliberations and decided to form\na\nseparate\nbody for such a purpose.\n\n(c) Behramji Malabari and M. G. Ranade decided to bring\ntogether all the social reform groups of the country under\none\norganisation.\n\n(d) None of the statements \n(a), \n(b) a n d \n(c) given above is\ncorrect in this context.\nAnswer: \n(b) Indian National Congress did not ",
    "choices": "\n(a) Different social reform groups\nor\norganisations of the\nBengal region united to form\na\nsingle body to discuss the\nissues\nof\nlarger\ninterest\nand\nto\nprepare   appropriate\npetitions/ representations to the government:\n\n(b) Indian National Congress did not\nwant to include social\nreforms in its deliberations and decided to form\na\nseparate\nbody for such a purpose.\n\n(c) Behramji Malabari and M. G. Ranade decided to bring\ntogether all the social reform groups of the country under\none\norganisation.\n\n(d) None of the statements \n(a), \n(b) a n d \n(c) given above is\ncorrect in this context.",
    "answer": "\n(b) Indian National Congress did not",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "During the Indian freedom struggle, the National Social Conference was formed.\nWhat was the reason for its formation?\n\na) Different social reform groups or organisations of the Bengal region united to form a single body to discuss the issues of larger interest and to prepare appropriate petitions/ representations to the government:\n\nb) Indian National Congress did not want to include social reforms in its deliberations and decided to form a separate body for such a purpose.\n\nc) Behramji Malabari and M. G. Ranade decided to bring together all the social reform groups of the country under one organisation.\n\nd) None of the statements \n(a), \n(b) and \n(c) given above is correct in this context.",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "want to include\nsocial\nreforms\nin\nits\ndeliberations\nand\ndecided\nto form\na\nseparate body for such a purpose\nWho among the following social reformers started a society for\nthe\nencouragement\nof\nwidow\nremarriage\nin\n1866\nin\nMaharashtra?\n\na) Bal Gangadhar Tilak\n\nb)Jyotirao Phule\n\nc) Vishnushastri Pandit\n\nd)Pandita Ramabai\nAnswer: \n(c) Vishnushastri Pandit ",
    "choices": "a) Bal Gangadhar Tilak\n\nb)Jyotirao Phule\n\nc) Vishnushastri Pandit\n\nd)Pandita Ramabai",
    "answer": "\n(c) Vishnushastri Pandit",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "want to include social reforms in its deliberations and decided to form a separate body for such a purpose Who among the following social reformers started a society for the encouragement of widow remarriage in 1866 in Maharashtra? \n\n\na) Bal Gangadhar Tilak\n\nb)Jyotirao Phule\n\nc) Vishnushastri Pandit\n\nd)Pandita Ramabai",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among\nthe following gave evidence\nbefore\nthe\nJoint\nSelect Committee on the Government of India Bill, 1919 in\nfavour of female franchise?\n\n1.Mrs. Annie Besant\n\n2. Mrs. Sarojini Naidu\n\n3.Mrs. Hirabai Tata\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)1 and 2 only\n\nc) 2 and 3 only\n\nd)1,2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(d) 1,2 and 3 ",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)1 and 2 only\n\nc) 2 and 3 only\n\nd)1,2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1,2 and 3",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following gave evidence before the Joint Select Committee on the Government of India Bill, 1919 in favour of female franchise?\n\n\n1.Mrs. Annie Besant\n\n\n2. Mrs. Sarojini Naidu\n\n\n3.Mrs. Hirabai Tata\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\na) 1 only\n\n\nb)1 and 2 only\n\n\nc) 2 and 3 only\n\n\nd)1,2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the context of eighteenth-century India, what was\nDastak?",
    "choices": "a) Signature\n\nb)Land document\n\nc) Trade Permit\n\nd) Tax on textiles",
    "answer": "\n(c) Trade Permit",
    "topic": "British Conquest of India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_55f4f1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In the context of eighteenth-century India, what was Dastak?",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nMaratha\nstatesman signed the Treaty\nof Bassein\non\nDecember 31, 1802?",
    "choices": "a) Baji Rao II\n\nb) Vithuji Holkar\n\nc) Daulat Rao Sindhia\n\nd) Madhava Rao Narayan",
    "answer": "\n(a) Baji Rao II",
    "topic": "British Conquest of India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_55f4f1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which Maratha statesman signed the Treaty of Bassein on December 31, 1802?",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Chronologically\narrange\nthe\nfollowing\ntreaties/conventions\nsigned between the Marathas and the British (starting with the\nearliest):\n\n1. Treaty of Salbai\n\n2. Treaty of Purandar\n\n3.Convention of Wadgaon\n\n4.Treaty of Surat\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below :\n\na)4-2-3-1\n\nb)4-3-2-1\n\nc) 1-3-2-4\n\nd)1-2-3-4",
    "choices": "a)4-2-3-1\n\nb)4-3-2-1\n\nc) 1-3-2-4\n\nd)1-2-3-4",
    "answer": "\n(a) 4-2-3-1",
    "topic": "British Conquest of India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_55f4f1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Chronologically arrange the following treaties/conventions signed between the Marathas and the British (starting with the earliest):\n\n1. Treaty of Salbai\n\n2. Treaty of Purandar\n\n3. Convention of Wadgaon\n\n4. Treaty of Surat\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below :\n\na) 4-2-3-1\n\nb) 4-3-2-1\n\nc) 1-3-2-4\n\nd) 1-2-3-4",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who took over the Eka Movement' started by the Congress in\nAwadh during 1921-19227\n\na) Bhagwan Ahir\n\nb) Madari Pasi\n\nc) Baba Ramchandra\n\nd)Shah Naeem Ata\nAnswer: \n(b) Madari Pasi",
    "choices": "a) Bhagwan Ahir\n\nb) Madari Pasi\n\nc) Baba Ramchandra\n\nd)Shah Naeem Ata",
    "answer": "\n(b) Madari Pasi",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 2",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8fb608__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who took over the Eka Movement' started by the Congress in Awadh during 1921-19227\n\na) Bhagwan Ahir\n\nb) Madari Pasi\n\nc) Baba Ramchandra\n\nd) Shah Naeem Ata",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one ofthe following was NOT a feature of the Subsidiary Alliance of Lord Wellesley?",
    "choices": "a) The British were responsible for protecting the ally from any\nexternal threats\n\nb)AII internal threats\nwere to be handled by the ally alone,\nwith no help from the British\n\nc) The\nwas to provide resources for maintaining a\nBritish\narmed contingent stationed in its territory\n\nd) The ally could\nnot\nenter into\nany agreement with\nother\nrulers without the permission of the British",
    "answer": "\n(b) All internal threats were to be handled by the ally alone, with no help from the British ally",
    "topic": "Role of Governors-General in the Consolidation and Expansion of British Power",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_523b44__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one ofthe following was NOT a feature of the Subsidiary Alliance of Lord Wellesley?",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements does not apply to the\nsystem of Subsidiary Alliance introduced by Lord Wellesley?",
    "choices": "\n(a) To maintain a large standing army at others expense\n\n(b) To keep India safe from Napoleonic danger\nTo secure a fixed income for the Company\n\n(d) To establish British paramountcy over the Indian States",
    "answer": "\n(c) To secure @ fixed income for the Company",
    "topic": "Role of Governors-General in the Consolidation and Expansion of British Power",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_523b44__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following statements does not apply to the system of Subsidiary Alliance introduced by Lord Wellesley?",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to Pondicherry (now Puducherry), consider the\nfollowing statements:\n\n1.The first European power to occupy Pondicherry were the\nPortuguese:\n\n2. The second European power to occupy Pondcherry\nwere\nthe French.\n\n3.The English never occupied Pondicherry:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(a) 1 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 only",
    "topic": "Beginning of European Settlements in India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_068542__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to Pondicherry (now Puducherry), consider the following statements:\n\n1. The first European power to occupy Pondicherry were the Portuguese.\n\n2. The second European power to occupy Pondicherry were the French.\n\n3. The English never occupied Pondicherry.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n\nc) 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "In\nwhich\none\nof the following places\nwas\nthe Ahmadiyya\nMovement started by Mirza Ghulam Ahmad?\n\na) Patna\n\nb)Aligarh\n\nc) Bhopal\n\nd)Gurdaspur\nAnswer: \n(d) Gurdaspur ",
    "choices": "a) Patna\n\nb)Aligarh\n\nc) Bhopal\n\nd)Gurdaspur",
    "answer": "\n(d) Gurdaspur",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements = 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_5__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In which one of the following places was the Ahmadiyya Movement started by Mirza Ghulam Ahmad?\n\n\na) Patna \n\nb) Aligarh \n\nc) Bhopal \n\nd) Gurdaspur",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\none of the following statements about the Treaty of\nAllahabad is NOT correct?\n\na)lt was signed in the year 1765\n\nb) The Mughal Emperor by\na\nfarman, formally granted the\nDiwani\nof\nBengal,\nBihar\nand\nOrissa\nto\nthe\nEast\nIndia\nCompany\nC\nAwadh\nwas restored to its\nNawab\non payment of Rs.\n50\nLakhs\n\nd)Banaras and the Surrounding tracts\nwere detached from\nAwadh and handed over to Shah Alam",
    "choices": "a)lt was signed in the year 1765\n\nb) The Mughal Emperor by\na\nfarman, formally granted the\nDiwani\nof\nBengal,\nBihar\nand\nOrissa\nto\nthe\nEast\nIndia\nCompany\nC\nAwadh\nwas restored to its\nNawab\non payment of Rs.\n50\nLakhs\n\nd)Banaras and the Surrounding tracts\nwere detached from\nAwadh and handed over to Shah Alam",
    "answer": "\n(d) Banaras and the Surrounding tracts were detached\nfrom Awadh and handed over to Shah Alam II",
    "topic": "British Conquest of India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_55f4f1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following statements about the Treaty of Allahabad is NOT correct?\n\n\na) lt was signed in the year 1765\n\nb) The Mughal Emperor by a farman, formally granted the Diwani of Bengal, Bihar and Orissa to the East India Company\n\nc) Awadh was restored to its Nawab on payment of Rs. 50 Lakhs\n\nd) Banaras and the Surrounding tracts were detached from Awadh and handed over to Shah Alam",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1.In the Third Battle of Panipat, Ahmad Shah Abdali defeated\nIbrahim Lodi.\n\n2. Tipu Sultan was killed in the Third Anglo- Mysore War:\n\n3. Mir Jafar entered in\na\nconspiracy with the English for the\ndefeat of Nawab Siraj ud- Daulah in the Battle of Plassey:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n(a) 1, 2 and 3\n\n(b) 3 only\n\n(c) 2 and 3\n\n(d) None",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1, 2 and 3\n\n(b) 3 only\n\n(c) 2 and 3\n\n(d) None",
    "answer": "\n(b) 3 only",
    "topic": "British Conquest of India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_55f4f1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1. In the Third Battle of Panipat, Ahmad Shah Abdali defeated Ibrahim Lodi.\n\n2. Tipu Sultan was killed in the Third Anglo- Mysore War:\n\n3. Mir Jafar entered in a conspiracy with the English for the defeat of Nawab Siraj ud- Daulah in the Battle of Plassey:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1, 2 and 3\n\nb) 3 only\n\nc) 2 and 3\n\nd) None",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following Princely states ofthe British rule in India\n\n1.Jhansi\n\n2.Sambalpur\n\n3.Satara\nThe correct chronological order in which they were annexed\nthe British is:\n\n(a) 1-2-3\n\n(b) 1-3-2.\n\n(c) 3-2-1\n\n(d) 3-1-2",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1-2-3\n\n(b) 1-3-2.\n\n(c) 3-2-1\n\n(d) 3-1-2",
    "answer": "\n(c) 3-2-1",
    "topic": "British Conquest of India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_55f4f1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following Princely states ofthe British rule in India 1.Jhansi 2.Sambalpur 3.Satara The correct chronological order in which they were annexed the British is:\n\n\na) 1-2-3\n\nb) 1-3-2\n\nc) 3-2-1\n\nd) 3-1-2",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "The First Anglo-Maratha War was concluded\nwhich one of\nthe following?\n\na) The Treaty of Surat\n\nb) The Treaty of Purandar\n\nc) The Convention of Wadgaon\n\nd) The Treaty of Salbai",
    "choices": "a) The Treaty of Surat\n\nb) The Treaty of Purandar\n\nc) The Convention of Wadgaon\n\nd) The Treaty of Salbai",
    "answer": "\n(d) The Treaty of Salbai",
    "topic": "British Conquest of India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_55f4f1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The First Anglo-Maratha War was concluded which one of the following?\n\na) The Treaty of Surat\n\nb) The Treaty of Purandar\n\nc) The Convention of Wadgaon\n\nd) The Treaty of Salbai",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nThe ruler of which one of the following states\nwas removed\nfrom power by the British on the pretext of misgovernance?\n\n(a) Awadh\n\n(b) Jhansi\n\n(c) French\n\n(d) Satara",
    "choices": "\n(a) Awadh\n\n(b) Jhansi\n\n(c) French\n\n(d) Satara",
    "answer": "\n(a) Awadh",
    "topic": "British Conquest of India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_55f4f1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The ruler of which one of the following states was removed from power by the British on the pretext of misgovernance?\n\n(a) Awadh\n\n(b) Jhansi\n\n(c) French\n\n(d) Satara",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is the correct chronological order of the\nbattles fought in India in the 18th Century?\n\n(a) Battle of Wandiwash,\nBattle of Buxar; Battle of Ambur;\nBattle of Plassey\n\n(b) Battle of Ambur; Battle of Plassey, Battle of Wandiwash,\nBattle of Buxar\n\n(c) Battle of Wandiwash, Battle of Plassey Battle of Ambur;\nBattle of Buxar\n\n(d) Battle of Ambur;\nBattle of Buxar Battle of Wandiwash,\nBattle of Plassey",
    "choices": "\n(a) Battle of Wandiwash,\nBattle of Buxar; Battle of Ambur;\nBattle of Plassey\n\n(b) Battle of Ambur; Battle of Plassey, Battle of Wandiwash,\nBattle of Buxar\n\n(c) Battle of Wandiwash, Battle of Plassey Battle of Ambur;\nBattle of Buxar\n\n(d) Battle of Ambur;\nBattle of Buxar Battle of Wandiwash,\nBattle of Plassey",
    "answer": "\n(b) Battle\nof Ambur;\nBattle\nof Plassey,\nBattle\nOf\nWandiwash, Battle f Buxar",
    "topic": "British Conquest of India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_55f4f1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following is the correct chronological order of the battles fought in India in the 18th Century?\n\n\na) Battle of Wandiwash, Battle of Buxar; Battle of Ambur; Battle of Plassey\n\nb) Battle of Ambur; Battle of Plassey, Battle of Wandiwash, Battle of Buxar\n\nc) Battle of Wandiwash, Battle of Plassey Battle of Ambur; Battle of Buxar\n\nd) Battle of Ambur; Battle of Buxar Battle of Wandiwash, Battle of Plassey",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1. The\nbattle\nof\nBuxar provided\nthe\nfor the English\nto\nestablish their rule in India.\n\n2. The Treaty of Allahabad, concluded in 1765, enabled the\nBritish to establish their rule in Bengal:\nWhich of the statements given above is /are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n6)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n6)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "British Conquest of India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_55f4f1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements: \n\n1. The battle of Buxar provided the for the English to establish their rule in India. \n\n2. The Treaty of Allahabad, concluded in 1765, enabled the British to establish their rule in Bengal: \nWhich of the statements given above is /are correct? \n\na) 1 only \n6)2 only \n\nc) Both 1 and 2 \n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider\nthe\nfollowing\nstatements\nabout\nthe\nTreaty\nof\nAmritsar (1809):\n\n1. The Treaty fixed the Sutlej as the boundary between the\nPunjab and British India\n\n2. It was after this treaty that Maharaja Ranjit Singh was able\nto annex Jammu, Multan and Kashmir to his domains.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "British Conquest of India",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_55f4f1__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements about the Treaty of Amritsar (1809):\n\n\n1. The Treaty fixed the Sutlej as the boundary between the Punjab and British India.\n\n2. It was after this treaty that Maharaja Ranjit Singh was able to annex Jammu, Multan and Kashmir to his domains.\n\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\nwas\nthe Viceroy\nof\nIndia\nwhen\nthe\nRowlatt\nAct\nwas\npassed?\n\n(a) Lord Irwin\n\n(b) Lord Reading\n\n(c) Lord Chelmsford\n\n(d) Lord Wavell\nAnswer: \n(c) Lord Chelmsford",
    "choices": "\n(a) Lord Irwin\n\n(b) Lord Reading\n\n(c) Lord Chelmsford\n\n(d) Lord Wavell",
    "answer": "\n(c) Lord Chelmsford",
    "topic": "Non-Cooperation and Khilafat Movements",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_bd8e30__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who was the Viceroy of India when the Rowlatt Act was passed?\n\n\na) Lord Irwin\n\nb) Lord Reading\n\nc) Lord Chelmsford\n\nd) Lord Wavell",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\none\nof\nthe\nfollowing\naroused\na\nwave\nof\npopular\nindignition\nthat\nled\nto\nthe\nmassacre\nby\nthe\nBritish\nat\nJallianwala Bagh?\n\n(a) The Arms Act\n\n(b) The Public Safety Act\n\n(c) The Rowlatt Act\n\n(d) The Vernacular Press Act\nAnswer: \n(c) The Rowlatt Act",
    "choices": "\n(a) The Arms Act\n\n(b) The Public Safety Act\n\n(c) The Rowlatt Act\n\n(d) The Vernacular Press Act",
    "answer": "\n(c) The Rowlatt Act",
    "topic": "Non-Cooperation and Khilafat Movements",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_bd8e30__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following aroused a wave of popular indignation that led to the massacre by the British at Jallianwala Bagh?\n\na) The Arms Act\n\nb) The Public Safety Act\n\nc) The Rowlatt Act\n\nd) The Vernacular Press Act",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "What\nwas\nthe\nname\nof\nthe famous\nperson\nof\nIndia\nwho\nreturned\nthe\nKnighthood\nconferred\non\nhim\nby\nthe\nBritish\ngovernment as\na token of protest against atrocities in Punjab\nin 1919? (2004)\n\n(a) Tej Bahadur Sapru\n\n(b) Ashutosh Mukherjee\n\n(c) Rabindranath Tagore\n\n(d) Syed Ahmed Khan\nAnswer: \n(c) Rabindranath Tagore",
    "choices": "\n(a) Tej Bahadur Sapru\n\n(b) Ashutosh Mukherjee\n\n(c) Rabindranath Tagore\n\n(d) Syed Ahmed Khan",
    "answer": "\n(c) Rabindranath Tagore",
    "topic": "Non-Cooperation and Khilafat Movements",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_bd8e30__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "What was the name of the famous person of India who returned the Knighthood conferred on him by the British government as a token of protest against atrocities in Punjab in 1919? (2004)\n\n\na) Tej Bahadur Sapru \n\nb) Ashutosh Mukherjee \n\nc) Rabindranath Tagore \n\nd) Syed Ahmed Khan",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "When Congress leaders condemned the Montagu-Chelmsford\nReport, many moderates left the party to form which of the\nfollowing\n\n(a) Swaraj Party\n\n(b) Indian Freedom Party\n\n(c) Independence Federation of India\n\n(d) Indian Liberal Federation\nAnswer: \n(d) Indian Liberal Federation",
    "choices": "\n(a) Swaraj Party\n\n(b) Indian Freedom Party\n\n(c) Independence Federation of India\n\n(d) Indian Liberal Federation",
    "answer": "\n(d) Indian Liberal Federation",
    "topic": "Non-Cooperation and Khilafat Movements",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_bd8e30__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "When Congress leaders condemned the Montagu-Chelmsford Report, many moderates left the party to form which of the following\n\n\na) Swaraj Party\n\nb) Indian Freedom Party\n\nc) Independence Federation of India\n\nd) Indian Liberal Federation",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following characteristics does NOT describe\nthe Khilafat movement?\n\na) Mahatma Gandhi sought to link it to the Non-Cooperation\nmovement\n\nb)It was not supported\nthe Congress\n\nc) It demanded that the\nTurkish\nSultan\nmust retain control\nover Muslim sacred spaces in the erstwhile Ottoman empire\n\nd)lt was led\nMuhammad Ali and Shaukat Ali\nAnswer: \n(b) It was not supported by the Congress",
    "choices": "a) Mahatma Gandhi sought to link it to the Non-Cooperation\nmovement\n\nb)It was not supported\nthe Congress\n\nc) It demanded that the\nTurkish\nSultan\nmust retain control\nover Muslim sacred spaces in the erstwhile Ottoman empire\n\nd)lt was led\nMuhammad Ali and Shaukat Ali",
    "answer": "\n(b) It was not supported by the Congress",
    "topic": "Non-Cooperation and Khilafat Movements",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_bd8e30__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following characteristics does NOT describe the Khilafat movement? \n\na) Mahatma Gandhi sought to link it to the Non-Cooperation movement\n\nb)It was not supported the Congress\n\nc) It demanded that the Turkish Sultan must retain control over Muslim sacred spaces in the erstwhile Ottoman empire\n\nd)lt was led Muhammad Ali and Shaukat Ali",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following founded the Bhil Seva Mandal in\n1922?\n\na) Dayaram Gidumal\n\nb) Gurusaday Dutt\n\nc) Dhondo Keshav Karve\n\nd)Amrital Vithaldas Thakkar\nAnswer: \n(d) Amrital Vithaldas Thakkar",
    "choices": "a) Dayaram Gidumal\n\nb) Gurusaday Dutt\n\nc) Dhondo Keshav Karve\n\nd)Amrital Vithaldas Thakkar",
    "answer": "\n(d) Amrital Vithaldas Thakkar",
    "topic": "Non-Cooperation and Khilafat Movements",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_bd8e30__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following founded the Bhil Seva Mandal in 1922?\n\na) Dayaram Gidumal\n\nb) Gurusaday Dutt\n\nc) Dhondo Keshav Karve\n\nd)Amrital Vithaldas Thakkar",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to Rowlatt Satyagraha, which of the following\nstatements is/are correct?\n\n1. The Rowlatt Act was based on the recommendations of the\n'Sedition\nCommittee'.\n\n2. In Rowlatt Satyagraha Gandhiji tried to use the Home Rule\nLeague:\n\n3.Demonstrations against the Simon\nCommission coincided\nwith the Rowlatt Satyagraha.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n\n(c) 2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(b) 1 and 2 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n\n(c) 2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(b) 1 and 2 only",
    "topic": "Non-Cooperation and Khilafat Movements",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_bd8e30__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to Rowlatt Satyagraha, which of the following statements is/are correct?\n\n1. The Rowlatt Act was based on the recommendations of the 'Sedition Committee'.\n\n2. In Rowlatt Satyagraha Gandhiji tried to use the Home Rule League:\n\n3. Demonstrations against the Simon Commission coincided with the Rowlatt Satyagraha.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 2 only\n\nc) 2 and 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Rowlatt Act aimed at\n\n(a) Compulsory economic support to war efforts.\n\n(b) Imprisonment without trial and summary procedures\nfor trial:\n\n(c) Suppression of the Khilafat Movement;\n\n(d) Imposition of restrictions on freedom of the press.\nAnswer:\n\n(b) Imprisonment\nwithout\ntrial\nand\nsummary\nprocedures for trial",
    "choices": "\n(a) Compulsory economic support to war efforts.\n\n(b) Imprisonment without trial and summary procedures\nfor trial:\n\n(c) Suppression of the Khilafat Movement;\n\n(d) Imposition of restrictions on freedom of the press.",
    "answer": "\n(b) Imprisonment\nwithout\ntrial\nand\nsummary\nprocedures for trial",
    "topic": "Non-Cooperation and Khilafat Movements",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_bd8e30__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Rowlatt Act aimed at: \n\n(a) Compulsory economic support to war efforts. \n\n(b) Imprisonment without trial and summary procedures for trial. \n\n(c) Suppression of the Khilafat Movement. \n\n(d) Imposition of restrictions on freedom of the press.",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the Indian freedom struggle, why did the Rowlatt Act\narouse popular indignation?\n\n(a) It curtailed the freedom of religion\n\n(b) It suppressed the Indian traditional education\n\n(c) It authorised the government to imprison people without\ntrial\n\n(d) It curbed the trade union activities\nAnswer: \n(c) It authorised the government to imprison people\nwithout trial",
    "choices": "\n(a) It curtailed the freedom of religion\n\n(b) It suppressed the Indian traditional education\n\n(c) It authorised the government to imprison people without\ntrial\n\n(d) It curbed the trade union activities",
    "answer": "\n(c) It authorised the government to imprison people\nwithout trial",
    "topic": "Non-Cooperation and Khilafat Movements",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_bd8e30__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "During the Indian freedom struggle, why did the Rowlatt Act arouse popular indignation?\n\n(a) It curtailed the freedom of religion\n\n(b) It suppressed the Indian traditional education\n\n(c) It authorised the government to imprison people without trial\n\n(d) It curbed the trade union activities",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "In 1921, during\nwhich\none\nof the following tours, Gandhiji\nshaved\nhis\nhead\nand\nbegan wearing loincloth\nin\norder\nto\nidentify with the poor?\n\na)Ahmadabad\n\nb)Champaran\n\nc) Chauri Chaura\n\nd)South India\nAnswer: \n(d) South India",
    "choices": "a)Ahmadabad\n\nb)Champaran\n\nc) Chauri Chaura\n\nd)South India",
    "answer": "\n(d) South India",
    "topic": "Non-Cooperation and Khilafat Movements",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_bd8e30__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In 1921, during which one of the following tours, Gandhiji shaved his head and began wearing loincloth in order to identify with the poor?\n\n\na) Ahmadabad\n\nb) Champaran\n\nc) Chauri Chaura\n\nd) South India",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nWith reference to Madanapalle of Andhra Pradesh, which one\nof the following statements is correct?\n\n(a) Pingali Venkayya designed the tricolour Indian National\nFlag here:\n\n(b) Pattabhi Sitaramaiah led the Quit India\nMovement of\nthe Andhra region from here.\n\n(c) Rabindranath Tagore translated the National Anthem\nfrom Bengali to English here:\n\n(d) Madame\nBlavatsky\nand\nColonel\nOlcott\nset\nup\nheadquarters of Theosophical Society first here.\nAnswer:\n\n(c) Rabindranath\nTagore\ntranslated\nthe\nNational\nAnthem from Bengali to English here",
    "choices": "\n(a) Pingali Venkayya designed the tricolour Indian National\nFlag here:\n\n(b) Pattabhi Sitaramaiah led the Quit India\nMovement of\nthe Andhra region from here.\n\n(c) Rabindranath Tagore translated the National Anthem\nfrom Bengali to English here:\n\n(d) Madame\nBlavatsky\nand\nColonel\nOlcott\nset\nup\nheadquarters of Theosophical Society first here.",
    "answer": "\n(c) Rabindranath\nTagore\ntranslated\nthe\nNational\nAnthem from Bengali to English here",
    "topic": "Non-Cooperation and Khilafat Movements",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_bd8e30__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to Madanapalle of Andhra Pradesh, which one of the following statements is correct?\n\na) Pingali Venkayya designed the tricolour Indian National Flag here:\n\nb) Pattabhi Sitaramaiah led the Quit India Movement of the Andhra region from here.\n\nc) Rabindranath Tagore translated the National Anthem from Bengali to English here:\n\nd) Madame Blavatsky and Colonel Olcott set up headquarters of Theosophical Society first here.",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Hunter Commission was\nappointed after the_\n\n(a) Black hole incident\n\n(b) Jallianwala Bagh massacre\n\n(c) Uprising of 1857\n\n(d) Partition of Bengal\nAnswer: \n(b) Jallianwala Bagh Massacre",
    "choices": "\n(a) Black hole incident\n\n(b) Jallianwala Bagh massacre\n\n(c) Uprising of 1857\n\n(d) Partition of Bengal",
    "answer": "\n(b) Jallianwala Bagh Massacre",
    "topic": "Non-Cooperation and Khilafat Movements",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_bd8e30__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Hunter Commission was appointed after the\n\n\na) Black hole incident\n\nb) Jallianwala Bagh massacre\n\nc) Uprising of 1857\n\nd) Partition of Bengal",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\namong\nthe following formed\nthe\nNational\nLiberation\nFederation (Liberal Party)?\n\na) Motilal Nehru and C. R: Das\n\nb)Muhammad Ali and C. R. Das\n\nc) T B. Sapru and M. R: Jayakar\n\nd)M: R Jayakar and C R. Das\nAnswer: \n(c) T B. Sapru and M. R: Jayakar",
    "choices": "a) Motilal Nehru and C. R: Das\n\nb)Muhammad Ali and C. R. Das\n\nc) T B. Sapru and M. R: Jayakar\n\nd)M: R Jayakar and C R. Das",
    "answer": "\n(c) T B. Sapru and M. R: Jayakar",
    "topic": "Non-Cooperation and Khilafat Movements",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_bd8e30__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following formed the National Liberation Federation (Liberal Party)?\n\n\na) Motilal Nehru and C. R: Das\n\nb)Muhammad Ali and C. R. Das\n\nc) T B. Sapru and M. R: Jayakar\n\nd)M: R Jayakar and C R. Das",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the Non-Cooperation\nMovement is/are correct?\n\n1.It was marked by significant participation of peasants from\nKarnataka.\n\n2. It was marked by non-Brahmin lower caste participation in\nMadras and Maharashtra.\n\n3.It\nwas\nmarked by the lack of labour unrest in places like\nAssam, Bengal and Madras.\n\n4.lt was\nbadly shaken\nthe Chauri Chaura incident in 1922\nafter\nwhich\nGandhiji\ndecided\nto\ncontinue\nwith\nwith the\nmovement on a much smaller scale.\nSelect the correct answer\nusing the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)1,2 and 4\n\nc) 2 and 3\n\nd) 2 only\nAnswer: \n(d) 2 only",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)1,2 and 4\n\nc) 2 and 3\n\nd) 2 only",
    "answer": "\n(d) 2 only",
    "topic": "Non-Cooperation and Khilafat Movements",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_bd8e30__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the Non-Cooperation Movement is/are correct? \n\n1.It was marked by significant participation of peasants from Karnataka. \n\n2. It was marked by non-Brahmin lower caste participation in Madras and Maharashtra. \n\n3.It was marked by the lack of labour unrest in places like Assam, Bengal and Madras. \n\n4.lt was badly shaken the Chauri Chaura incident in 1922 after which Gandhiji decided to continue with the movement on a much smaller scale. \nSelect the correct answer using the code given below: \n\na) 1 only \n\nb)1,2 and 4 \n\nc) 2 and 3 \n\nd) 2 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Azamgarh Proclamation of August 25, 1857, stressed which\none of the\nfollowing issues?\n\na) Hindu-Muslim divide\n\nb)Support to the English Government\n\nc) The return of the Badshahi\n\nd) The imposition of heavy Jumas (revenue demand)\nAnswer: \n(c) The return of the Badshahi",
    "choices": "a) Hindu-Muslim divide\n\nb)Support to the English Government\n\nc) The return of the Badshahi\n\nd) The imposition of heavy Jumas (revenue demand)",
    "answer": "\n(c) The return of the Badshahi",
    "topic": "Revolt of 1857",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_119e32__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Azamgarh Proclamation of August 25, 1857, stressed which one of the following issues?\n\na) Hindu-Muslim divide\n\nb) Support to the English Government\n\nc) The return of the Badshahi\n\nd) The imposition of heavy Jumas (revenue demand)",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following was known during the days of the\nRevolt of 1857 as Danka Shah?\n\na) Shah Mal\n\nb) Maulavi Ahmadullah Shah\n\nc) Nana Sahib\n\nd) Tantia Tope\nAnswer: \n(b) Maulavi Ahmadullah Shah",
    "choices": "a) Shah Mal\n\nb) Maulavi Ahmadullah Shah\n\nc) Nana Sahib\n\nd) Tantia Tope",
    "answer": "\n(b) Maulavi Ahmadullah Shah",
    "topic": "Revolt of 1857",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_119e32__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following was known during the days of the Revolt of 1857 as Danka Shah? \n\n\n(a) Shah Mal \n\n\n(b) Maulavi Ahmadullah Shah \n\n\n(c) Nana Sahib \n\n\n(d) Tantia Tope",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\none of the\nfollowing statements about the Revolt of\n1857 is correct?\n\na)It was a Revolt carefully organised and planned by the Rajas,\nNawabs and Taluqdars\n\nb)Rumours\nand\nprophecies\ndid\nnot\nplay\nany\nrole\nin\nits\noutbreak and spread\n\nc) The rebel proclamations in 1857 repeatedly appealed to all\nsections of the population irrespective of their caste and\ncreed:\n\nd) The British succeeded in quickly and easily controlling the\nrebels\nAnswer:\n\n(c) The\nrebel\nproclamations\nin\n1857\nrepeatedly\nappealed to all sections of the population irrespective of their\ncaste and creed",
    "choices": "a)It was a Revolt carefully organised and planned by the Rajas,\nNawabs and Taluqdars\n\nb)Rumours\nand\nprophecies\ndid\nnot\nplay\nany\nrole\nin\nits\noutbreak and spread\n\nc) The rebel proclamations in 1857 repeatedly appealed to all\nsections of the population irrespective of their caste and\ncreed:\n\nd) The British succeeded in quickly and easily controlling the\nrebels",
    "answer": "\n(c) The\nrebel\nproclamations\nin\n1857\nrepeatedly\nappealed to all sections of the population irrespective of their\ncaste and creed",
    "topic": "Revolt of 1857",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_119e32__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following statements about the Revolt of 1857 is correct?\n\n(a) It was a Revolt carefully organised and planned by the Rajas, Nawabs and Taluqdars\n\n(b) Rumours and prophecies did not play any role in its outbreak and spread\n\n(c) The rebel proclamations in 1857 repeatedly appealed to all sections of the population irrespective of their caste and creed\n\n(d) The British succeeded in quickly and easily controlling the rebels",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "The\nfollowing question consists of statements: Statement I and\nStatement\nIL:\nExamine\nthese\ntwo\nstatements  carefully\nand\nselect the correct answer using the code below:\nCode:\n\na) Both statements are individually true, and Statement Il is the\ncorrect explanation of Statement\n\nb)Both statements are individually true, but Statement Il is not\nthe correct explanation of Statement |\nC\nStatement\nis true, but Statement Il is false\n\nd)Statement | is false, but Statement Il is true.\nStatement I: In 1856, Nawab Wajid Ali Shah was dethroned and\nexiled\nto\nCalcutta\non\nthe\nplea\nthat\nthe\nregion\nwas\nbeing\nmisgoverned:\nStatement I: The Nawab was accused of being unable to control\nthe rebellious chiefs and Taluqdars.\nAnswer:\n\n(a) Both\nstatements\nare\nindividually\ntrue,\nand\nStatement II is the correct explanation of Statement |",
    "choices": "a) Both statements are individually true, and Statement Il is the\ncorrect explanation of Statement\n\nb)Both statements are individually true, but Statement Il is not\nthe correct explanation of Statement |\nC\nStatement\nis true, but Statement Il is false\n\nd)Statement | is false, but Statement Il is true.",
    "answer": "\n(a) Both\nstatements\nare\nindividually\ntrue,\nand\nStatement II is the correct explanation of Statement |",
    "topic": "Revolt of 1857",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_119e32__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The following question consists of statements: Statement I and Statement IL: Examine these two statements carefully and select the correct answer using the code below: \nCode: \n\na) Both statements are individually true, and Statement Il is the correct explanation of Statement \n\nb)Both statements are individually true, but Statement Il is not the correct explanation of Statement | \nC Statement is true, but Statement Il is false \n\nd)Statement | is false, but Statement Il is true. \nStatement I: In 1856, Nawab Wajid Ali Shah was dethroned and exiled to Calcutta on the plea that the region was being misgoverned: \nStatement I: The Nawab was accused of being unable to control the rebellious chiefs and Taluqdars.",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following territories was not affected by the\nRevolt of 1857?\n\n(a) Jhansi\n\n(b) Chittor\n\n(c) Jagdishpur\n\n(d) Lucknow\nAnswer: \n(b) Chittor",
    "choices": "\n(a) Jhansi\n\n(b) Chittor\n\n(c) Jagdishpur\n\n(d) Lucknow",
    "answer": "\n(b) Chittor",
    "topic": "Revolt of 1857",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_119e32__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following territories was not affected by the Revolt of 1857?\n\n\na) Jhansi\n\nb) Chittor\n\nc) Jagdishpur\n\nd) Lucknow",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\none\nof\nthe following  places\ndid\nKunwar   Singh,\na\nprominent leader of the Revolt of 1857, belong to?\n\n(a) Bihar\n\n(b) Madhya Pradesh\n\n(c) Rajasthan\n\n(d) Uttar Pradesh\nAnswer: \n(a) Bihar",
    "choices": "\n(a) Bihar\n\n(b) Madhya Pradesh\n\n(c) Rajasthan\n\n(d) Uttar Pradesh",
    "answer": "\n(a) Bihar",
    "topic": "Revolt of 1857",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_119e32__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following places did Kunwar Singh, a prominent leader of the Revolt of 1857, belong to?\n\na) Bihar\n\nb) Madhya Pradesh\n\nc) Rajasthan\n\nd) Uttar Pradesh",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\none of the following towns\nwas\nnot\na\ncentre\nof the\nRevolt of 1857?\n\na) Ayodhya\n\nb)Agra\n\nc) Delhi\n\nd)Kanpur\nAnswer: \n(a) Ayodhya",
    "choices": "a) Ayodhya\n\nb)Agra\n\nc) Delhi\n\nd)Kanpur",
    "answer": "\n(a) Ayodhya",
    "topic": "Revolt of 1857",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_119e32__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following towns was not a centre of the Revolt of 1857?\n\na) Ayodhya\n\nb) Agra\n\nc) Delhi\n\nd) Kanpur",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\none of the following statements about the ishtahars\nissued during the Revolt of 1857 is correct?\n\na) They glorified the Muslim rule in India:\n\nb) They glorified the\nCO-existence\nof different\ncommunities\nunder the Mughal Empire:\n\nc) They glorified the message of Islam:\n\nd) They glorified the role of Queen Victoria.\nAnswer:\n\n(b) They   glorified\nthe\nCO-existence\nof\ndifferent\ncommunities under the Mughal Empire.",
    "choices": "a) They glorified the Muslim rule in India:\n\nb) They glorified the\nCO-existence\nof different\ncommunities\nunder the Mughal Empire:\n\nc) They glorified the message of Islam:\n\nd) They glorified the role of Queen Victoria.",
    "answer": "\n(b) They   glorified\nthe\nCO-existence\nof\ndifferent\ncommunities under the Mughal Empire.",
    "topic": "Revolt of 1857",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_119e32__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following statements about the ishtahars issued during the Revolt of 1857 is correct? \n\na) They glorified the Muslim rule in India: \n\nb) They glorified the CO-existence of different communities under the Mughal Empire: \n\nc) They glorified the message of Islam: \n\nd) They glorified the role of Queen Victoria.",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the\nfollowing was NOT a cause of the Revolt of\n1857?\n\na) The\nrumour that the\nBritish had\nmixed the bone dust of\ncows and pigs into the flour being sold in the market\n\nb) The prophecy that British rule would come to an end on the\ncentenary of the Battle of Plassey on 23rd June, 1857\n\nc) Popular discontent with British rule\n\nd) The prophecy that the end of British rule would lead to the\nend of the Kali Yuga and the return of Ram Rajya\nAnswer: \n(d) The prophecy that the end of British rule would\nlead to the end of the Kali Yuga and the return of Ram Rajya",
    "choices": "a) The\nrumour that the\nBritish had\nmixed the bone dust of\ncows and pigs into the flour being sold in the market\n\nb) The prophecy that British rule would come to an end on the\ncentenary of the Battle of Plassey on 23rd June, 1857\n\nc) Popular discontent with British rule\n\nd) The prophecy that the end of British rule would lead to the\nend of the Kali Yuga and the return of Ram Rajya",
    "answer": "\n(d) The prophecy that the end of British rule would\nlead to the end of the Kali Yuga and the return of Ram Rajya",
    "topic": "Revolt of 1857",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_119e32__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following was NOT a cause of the Revolt of 1857?\n\n1. The rumour that the British had mixed the bone dust of cows and pigs into the flour being sold in the market\n\n2. The prophecy that British rule would come to an end on the centenary of the Battle of Plassey on 23rd June, 1857\n\n3. Popular discontent with British rule\n\n4. The prophecy that the end of British rule would lead to the end of the Kali Yuga and the return of Ram Rajya",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nWith reference to the Revolt of the\n1857,\nwho among the\nfollowing was betrayed by a friend, captured and put to death\nby the British?\n\n(a) Nana Sahib\n\n(b) Kunwar Singh\n\n(c) Khan Bahadur Khan\n\n(d) Tantia Tope\nAnswer: \n(d) Tantia Tope",
    "choices": "\n(a) Nana Sahib\n\n(b) Kunwar Singh\n\n(c) Khan Bahadur Khan\n\n(d) Tantia Tope",
    "answer": "\n(d) Tantia Tope",
    "topic": "Revolt of 1857",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_119e32__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to the Revolt of the 1857, who among the following was betrayed by a friend, captured and put to death by the British?\n\na) Nana Sahib\n\nb) Kunwar Singh\n\nc) Khan Bahadur Khan\n\nd) Tantia Tope",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\nwas\nthe\nGovernor\nGeneral\nof India during the sepoy\nmutiny?\n\n(a) Lord Canning\n\n(b) Lord Dalhousie\n\n(c) Lord Hardinge\n\n(d) Lord Lytton\nAnswer: \n(a) Lord Canning",
    "choices": "\n(a) Lord Canning\n\n(b) Lord Dalhousie\n\n(c) Lord Hardinge\n\n(d) Lord Lytton",
    "answer": "\n(a) Lord Canning",
    "topic": "Revolt of 1857",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_119e32__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who was the Governor General of India during the sepoy mutiny?\n\na) Lord Canning\n\nb) Lord Dalhousie\n\nc) Lord Hardinge\n\nd) Lord Lytton",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "year\nThe Summary Settlement of 1856 was based on which one of\nthe following assumptions?\n\na) The Talukdars were the rightful owners of the land:\n\nb)The Talukdars were interlopers with no permanent stakes in\nthe land:\n\nc) The Talukdars could evict the peasants from the lands.\n\nd) The Talukdars would take\na\nportion of the revenue which\nflowed to the State:\nAnswer: \n(b) The Talukdars were interlopers with no permanent\nstakes in the land",
    "choices": "a) The Talukdars were the rightful owners of the land:\n\nb)The Talukdars were interlopers with no permanent stakes in\nthe land:\n\nc) The Talukdars could evict the peasants from the lands.\n\nd) The Talukdars would take\na\nportion of the revenue which\nflowed to the State:",
    "answer": "\n(b) The Talukdars were interlopers with no permanent\nstakes in the land",
    "topic": "Revolt of 1857",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_119e32__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "year\nThe Summary Settlement of 1856 was based on which one of the following assumptions?\n\n\na) The Talukdars were the rightful owners of the land:\n\nb) The Talukdars were interlopers with no permanent stakes in the land:\n\nc) The Talukdars could evict the peasants from the lands.\n\nd) The Talukdars would take a portion of the revenue which flowed to the State:",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the rebel who fought against the British in the battle of\nChinhat during the 1857 Revolt?\n\na)Ahmadullah Shah\n\nb)Shah Mal\n\nC)\nMangal Pandey\n\nd) Kunwar Singh\nAnswer: \n(a) Ahmadullah Shah",
    "choices": "a)Ahmadullah Shah\n\nb)Shah Mal\n\nC)\nMangal Pandey\n\nd) Kunwar Singh",
    "answer": "\n(a) Ahmadullah Shah",
    "topic": "Revolt of 1857",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_119e32__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Name the rebel who fought against the British in the battle of Chinhat during the 1857 Revolt?\n\na) Ahmadullah Shah\n\nb) Shah Mal\n\nC) Mangal Pandey\n\nd) Kunwar Singh",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about Maulvi Ahmadullah\nShah, who played an important part in the 1857 Revolt, is/are\ncorrect?\n\n1.He was\npopularly known as Danka Shah or the Maulvi with\na drum.\n\n2.He fought in the famous Battle of Chinhat.\n\n3.He was killed by British troops under the command of Henry\nLawrence.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 3\nand 3\n\nd) 1 and 2\nAnswer: \n(d) 1 and 2",
    "choices": "1.He was\npopularly known as Danka Shah or the Maulvi with\na drum.\n\n2.He fought in the famous Battle of Chinhat.\n\n3.He was killed by British troops under the command of Henry\nLawrence.\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 3\n\nc) 2 and 3\n\nd) 1 and 2",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1 and 2",
    "topic": "Revolt of 1857",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_119e32__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about Maulvi Ahmadullah Shah, who played an important part in the 1857 Revolt, is/are correct?\nHe was popularly known as Danka Shah or the Maulvi with a drum.\nHe fought in the famous Battle of Chinhat.\nHe was killed by British troops under the command of Henry Lawrence.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 3 and 3\n\nc) 1, 2 and 3\n\nd) 1 and 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the consequence of the Permanent Settlement on\nrural society in Bengal?",
    "choices": "a) The zamindars invested capital and enterprise to improve\nagriculture along the lines of British yeoman farmers\n\nb) A group of rich peasants known\nas\njotedars succeeded in\nconsolidating their position in the villages\n\nc) The ryots prospered as\na\nresult of the fixed revenue\nimposed on them\n\nd) The system of Collectorate introduced\nthe Company for\nexercising supervisory control\non zamindars failed to take\noff",
    "answer": "\n(b) A\ngroup\nof\nrich\npeasants\nknown\nas\nJotedars\nsucceeded in consolidating their position in the villages",
    "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "What was the consequence of the Permanent Settlement on rural society in Bengal?",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\namong\nthe following\nwas/were\nassociated\nwith\nthe\nintroduction of the Ryotwari Settlement in India during British\nrule?\n\n1. Lord Cornwallis\n\n2.Alexander Read\n\n3.Thomas Munro\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1 and 3 only\n\n(c) 2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1 and 3 only\n\n(c) 2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(c) 2 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following was/were associated with the introduction of the Ryotwari Settlement in India during British rule?\n\n1. Lord Cornwallis\n\n2. Alexander Read\n\n3. Thomas Munro\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1 and 3 only\n\n(c) 2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nWith reference to the history of India, consider the following\npairs:\n\n1.Aurang: In-charge of treasury of the State\n\n2. Banian: Indian agent of the East India Company\n\n3.Mirasidar\nDesignated revenue payer to the State\nWhich of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched?\n\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 3\nonly\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 3\nonly\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to the history of India, consider the following pairs:\n\n1. Aurang: In-charge of treasury of the State\n\n2. Banian: Indian agent of the East India Company\n\n3. Mirasidar Designated revenue payer to the State\nWhich of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched?\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n\nc) 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT a characteristic of the Permanent\nSettlement?\n\na) The Permanent Settlement vested landownership rights in\nthe Zamindar\n\nb) The Permanent Settlement continued to pay attention to\nthe customary occupancy rights of peasants\n\nc) The burden of the high revenue assessment was shifted to\nthe peasants under the Permanent Settlement\n\nd) The condition of the actual cultivators of the land declined\nunder Permanent Settlement",
    "choices": "a) The Permanent Settlement vested landownership rights in\nthe Zamindar\n\nb) The Permanent Settlement continued to pay attention to\nthe customary occupancy rights of peasants\n\nc) The burden of the high revenue assessment was shifted to\nthe peasants under the Permanent Settlement\n\nd) The condition of the actual cultivators of the land declined\nunder Permanent Settlement",
    "answer": "\n(b) The\nPermanent\nSettlement\ncontinued\nto\npay\nattention to the customary occupancy rights of peasants",
    "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following is NOT a characteristic of the Permanent Settlement?\n\n\na) The Permanent Settlement vested landownership rights in the Zamindar\n\n\nb) The Permanent Settlement continued to pay attention to the customary occupancy rights of peasants\n\n\nc) The burden of the high revenue assessment was shifted to the peasants under the Permanent Settlement\n\n\nd) The condition of the actual cultivators of the land declined under Permanent Settlement",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following pairs is/are correctly matched?\n\n1. Permanent Settlement: Lord Cornwallis\n\n2. Ryotwari Settlement: Thomas Munro\n\n3.Mahalwari Settlement: Holt Mackenzie\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 2\n\nc) 2 and 3 only\n\nd) 1,2 and 3",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 2\n\nc) 2 and 3 only\n\nd) 1,2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1,2 and 3\nonly",
    "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following pairs is/are correctly matched?\n\n1. Permanent Settlement: Lord Cornwallis\n\n2. Ryotwari Settlement: Thomas Munro\n\n3. Mahalwari Settlement: Holt Mackenzie\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 2\n\nc) 2 and 3 only\n\nd) 1,2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to Ryotwari Settlement, consider the following\nstatements\n\n1. The\nrent\nwas\ndirectly\nby\nthe\npeasants\nto\nthe\ngovernment:\n\n2. The government gave the Pattas to the Ryots.\n\n3.The lands were surveyed and assessed\nbefore being taxed:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n1, 2 and 3\n\n(d) None of the above",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n1, 2 and 3\n\n(d) None of the above",
    "answer": "\n(c) 1, 2 and 3",
    "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to Ryotwari Settlement, consider the following statements\n\n\n1. The rent was directly by the peasants to the government\n\n2. The government gave the Pattas to the Ryots.\n\n3. The lands were surveyed and assessed before being taxed\n\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n1, 2 and 3\n\n(d) None of the above",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "The tendency for\nincreased  litigation\nwas\nvisible\nafter\nthe\nintroduction of the land settlement system of Lord Cornwallis\nin 1793. The reason for this is normally traced to which of the\nfollowing provisions?\n\n(a) Making Zamindar's position stronger vis-a-vis the Ryot\n\n(b) Making East India Company an overlord of Zamindars\n\n(c) Making the judicial system more efficient\n\n(d) None of the above",
    "choices": "\n(a) Making Zamindar's position stronger vis-a-vis the Ryot\n\n(b) Making East India Company an overlord of Zamindars\n\n(c) Making the judicial system more efficient\n\n(d) None of the above",
    "answer": "\n(d) None of the above",
    "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The tendency for increased litigation was visible after the introduction of the land settlement system of Lord Cornwallis in 1793. \nThe reason for this is normally traced to which of the following provisions?\n\na) Making Zamindar's position stronger vis-a-vis the Ryot \n\nb) Making East India Company an overlord of Zamindars \n\nc) Making the judicial system more efficient \n\nd) None of the above",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "paid\nWhich of the following is/are characteristic(s) of the Ryotwari\nsystem?\n\n1.It was the brainchild of Thomas Munro\n\n2.It was meant to reduce intermediaries\n\n3.Cultivating peasants\nwere gradually impoverished by the\nsystem\n\n4.It was introduced in parts of Madras and Bengal Presidency\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)1, 2 and 3\n\nc) 2 and 4 only\n\nd)2,3 and 4",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)1, 2 and 3\n\nc) 2 and 4 only\n\nd)2,3 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(b) 1,2 and 3",
    "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following is/are characteristic(s) of the Ryotwari system?\nIt was the brainchild of Thomas Munro\nIt was meant to reduce intermediaries Cultivating peasants were gradually impoverished by the system\nIt was introduced in parts of Madras and Bengal Presidency\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)1, 2 and 3\n\nc) 2 and 4 only\n\nd)2,3 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements with regard to ryotwari\nsettlement is not correct?\n\na)In southern and western India, the ryotwari settlement was\nadopted:\n\nb)Ryotwari was in principle a direct contract between the ryot\nand the state:\n\nc) It means a tax contract valid for usually 30 years\n\nd)In principle, it strengthened the former elite, the zamindars\nand weakened the peasantry:",
    "choices": "a)In southern and western India, the ryotwari settlement was\nadopted:\n\nb)Ryotwari was in principle a direct contract between the ryot\nand the state:\n\nc) It means a tax contract valid for usually 30 years\n\nd)In principle, it strengthened the former elite, the zamindars\nand weakened the peasantry:",
    "answer": "\n(d) In principle, it strengthened the former elite, the\nzamindars and weakened the peasantry",
    "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following statements with regard to ryotwari settlement is not correct?\n\n\na) In southern and western India, the ryotwari settlement was adopted:\n\nb) Ryotwari was in principle a direct contract between the ryot and the state:\n\nc) It means a tax contract valid for usually 30 years\n\nd) In principle, it strengthened the former elite, the zamindars and weakened the peasantry:",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Ryotwari experiment in land revenue was started by\n\na) Henry Dundas\n\nb)Alexander Reed\n\nc) David Ricardo\n\nd)Mountstuart Elphinstone",
    "choices": "a) Henry Dundas\n\nb)Alexander Reed\n\nc) David Ricardo\n\nd)Mountstuart Elphinstone",
    "answer": "\n(b) Alexander Reed",
    "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Ryotwari experiment in land revenue was started by\n\n\na) Henry Dundas\n\n\nb)Alexander Reed\n\n\nc) David Ricardo\n\n\nd)Mountstuart Elphinstone",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "The\nfollowing question consists of statements: Statement I and\nStatement\nIL:\nExamine\nthese\ntwo\nstatements  carefully\nand\nselect the correct answer using the code below:\nCode:\n\na) Both statements are individually true, and Statement Il is the\ncorrect explanation of Statement\n\nb)Both statements are individually true, but Statement Il is not\nthe correct explanation of Statement |\nC\nStatement\nis true, but Statement Il is false\n\nd)Statement | is false, but Statement Il is true.\nStatement I: The Permanent Settlement was rarely extended to\nany region beyond Bengal:\nStatement\nII:\nAfter\n1810,\nthe\nagricultural\nprices\ndeclined\naffecting adversely the income of the Bengal Zamindars.",
    "choices": "a) Both statements are individually true, and Statement Il is the\ncorrect explanation of Statement\n\nb)Both statements are individually true, but Statement Il is not\nthe correct explanation of Statement |\nC\nStatement\nis true, but Statement Il is false\n\nd)Statement | is false, but Statement Il is true.",
    "answer": "\n(c) Statement | is true, but Statement Il is false",
    "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The following question consists of statements: Statement I and Statement IL: Examine these two statements carefully and select the correct answer using the code below:\nCode:\n\na) Both statements are individually true, and Statement Il is the correct explanation of Statement\n\nb)Both statements are individually true, but Statement Il is not the correct explanation of Statement I\n\nc) Statement I is true, but Statement Il is false\n\nd)Statement I is false, but Statement Il is true.\nStatement I: The Permanent Settlement was rarely extended to any region beyond Bengal:\nStatement II: After 1810, the agricultural prices declined affecting adversely the income of the Bengal Zamindars.",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "The\nPermanent\nSettlement\nwas\nrarely\nextended\nto\nother\nregions because\n\na)An increase in agricultural prices after 1810 increased the\nvalue\nof\nthe\nharvest,\nwhile\nthe\nPermanent\nSettlement\ndisallowed an increase in the State's share\n\nb)the\neconomic theories\nof\nRicardo\ninfluenced\nthe policy\nmakers\n\nc) The state found it expedient to settle directly with the ryot\n\nd)all of the above",
    "choices": "a)An increase in agricultural prices after 1810 increased the\nvalue\nof\nthe\nharvest,\nwhile\nthe\nPermanent\nSettlement\ndisallowed an increase in the State's share\n\nb)the\neconomic theories\nof\nRicardo\ninfluenced\nthe policy\nmakers\n\nc) The state found it expedient to settle directly with the ryot\n\nd)all of the above",
    "answer": "\n(d) all of the above",
    "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Permanent Settlement was rarely extended to other regions because\n\na) An increase in agricultural prices after 1810 increased the value of the harvest, while the Permanent Settlement disallowed an increase in the State's share\n\nb) the economic theories of Ricardo influenced the policy makers\n\nc) The state found it expedient to settle directly with the ryot\n\nd) all of the above",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\namong\nthe\nfollowing\nintroduced\nthe\nPermanent\nSettlement of Bengal in 1793?\n\na) Lord Cornwallis\n\nb) Lord Ripon\n\nc) Robert Clive\n\nd)John Adam",
    "choices": "a) Lord Cornwallis\n\nb) Lord Ripon\n\nc) Robert Clive\n\nd)John Adam",
    "answer": "\n(a) Lord Cornwallis",
    "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_7__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following introduced the Permanent Settlement of Bengal in 1793?\n\na) Lord Cornwallis\n\nb) Lord Ripon\n\nc) Robert Clive\n\nd)John Adam",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following belonged to Serampore Mission?\n\n1. William Carey\n\n2.Joshua Marshman\n\n3. William Ward\n\n4.David Hare\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below :\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)1 and 3 only\n\nc) 1,2 and 3\n\nd)2,3 and 4 only\nAnswer: \n(c) 1, 2 and 3 only",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)1 and 3 only\n\nc) 1,2 and 3\n\nd)2,3 and 4 only",
    "answer": "\n(c) 1, 2 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Spread of Education",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following belonged to Serampore Mission?\n\n1. William Carey\n\n2. Joshua Marshman\n\n3. William Ward\n\n4. David Hare\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below :\n\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb) 1 and 3 only\n\nc) 1,2 and 3\n\nd) 2,3 and 4 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "The real beginning of Western education in India can be dated\nfrom\n\na)the Charter Act of 1813\n\nb)the Charter Act of 1793\n\nc)the Sarda Act of 1929\n\nd)the Macaulay's Minute on Indian Education, 1835\nAnswer: \n(a) the Charter Act of 1813\nonly",
    "choices": "a)the Charter Act of 1813\n\nb)the Charter Act of 1793\n\nc)the Sarda Act of 1929\n\nd)the Macaulay's Minute on Indian Education, 1835",
    "answer": "\n(a) the Charter Act of 1813\nonly",
    "topic": "Spread of Education",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The real beginning of Western education in India can be dated from\n\na) the Charter Act of 1813\n\nb) the Charter Act of 1793\n\nc) the Sarda Act of 1929\n\nd) the Macaulay's Minute on Indian Education, 1835",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "In 1911,\nwho among the following introduced\na\nbill\nin the\nImperial Legislative Council for introduction of compulsory and\nfree primary education in India?\n\na) Dadabhai Naoroji\n\nb)Bal Gangadhar Tilak\n\nc) Sir Harcourt Butler\n\nd) Gopal Krishna Gokhale\nAnswer: \n(d) Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
    "choices": "a) Dadabhai Naoroji\n\nb)Bal Gangadhar Tilak\n\nc) Sir Harcourt Butler\n\nd) Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
    "answer": "\n(d) Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
    "topic": "Spread of Education",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In 1911, who among the following introduced a bill in the Imperial Legislative Council for introduction of compulsory and free primary education in India?\n\na) Dadabhai Naoroji\n\nb) Bal Gangadhar Tilak\n\nc) Sir Harcourt Butler\n\nd) Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Hunter Commission (1882) appointed to survey the state\nof education in India.\n\na)deprecated University education\n\nb)overruled the Despatch of 1854\n\nc) endorsed the Despatch of 1854 with greater emphasis on\nprimary: education\n\nd)criticised the grants-in-aid system of schooling\nAnswer:\n\n(c) endored\nthe\nDespatch\nof\n1854\nwith\ngreater\nemphasis on primary education",
    "choices": "a)deprecated University education\n\nb)overruled the Despatch of 1854\n\nc) endorsed the Despatch of 1854 with greater emphasis on\nprimary: education\n\nd)criticised the grants-in-aid system of schooling",
    "answer": "\n(c) endored\nthe\nDespatch\nof\n1854\nwith\ngreater\nemphasis on primary education",
    "topic": "Spread of Education",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Hunter Commission (1882) appointed to survey the state of education in India.\n\n\na) deprecated University education\n\nb) overruled the Despatch of 1854\n\nc) endorsed the Despatch of 1854 with greater emphasis on primary education\n\nd) criticised the grants-in-aid system of schooling",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nof the following\nled\nto\nthe\nintroduction\nof English\nEducation in India?\n\n1.Charter Act of 1813\n\n2. General Committee of Public Instruction,\n1823\n\n3.Orientalist and Anglicist Controversy\nSelect the correct answer\nusing the code given below:\n\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) 1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) 1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "topic": "Spread of Education",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following led to the introduction of English Education in India?\n\n1. Charter Act of 1813\n\n2. General Committee of Public Instruction, 1823\n\n3. Orientalist and Anglicist Controversy\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to educational institutions during colonial rule\nin India, consider the_following pairs:\nInstitution\nFounder\n\n1.Sanskrit College at Benaras\nWilliam Jones\n\n2. Calcutta Madrasa\nWarren Hastings\n\n3.Fort William College\nArthur\nWellesley\nWhich of the pairs given above is/are correct?\n\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 only\n1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 3 only\nAnswer: \n(b) 2 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 only\n1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 3 only",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 only",
    "topic": "Spread of Education",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to educational institutions during colonial rule in India, consider the_following pairs: Institution Founder.\n\n1.Sanskrit College at Benaras William Jones.\n\n2. Calcutta Madrasa Warren Hastings.\n\n3.Fort William College Arthur Wellesley.\nWhich of the pairs given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb) 2 only\n1 and 3 only\n\nd) 3 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "In collaboration with David Hare and Alexander Duff; who out\nof the following established Hindu College at Calcutta?\n\n(a) Henry Louis Vivian Derozio\n\n(b) Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar\n\n(c) Keshab Chandra Sen\n\n(d) Raja Rammohan\nAnswer: \n(d) Raja Rammohan\nRoy",
    "choices": "\n(a) Henry Louis Vivian Derozio\n\n(b) Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar\n\n(c) Keshab Chandra Sen\n\n(d) Raja Rammohan",
    "answer": "\n(d) Raja Rammohan\nRoy",
    "topic": "Spread of Education",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In collaboration with David Hare and Alexander Duff; who out of the following established Hindu College at Calcutta?\n\na) Henry Louis Vivian Derozio\n\nb) Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar\n\nc) Keshab Chandra Sen\n\nd) Raja Rammohan Roy",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Spread of Education\nWho among the following\nwas associated\nas Secretary with\nHindu Female School which later came to be known as Bethune\nFemale School?\n\n(a) Annie Besant\n\n(b) Debendranath Tagore\nIshwar Chandra Vidyasagar\n\n(d) Sarojini Naidu\nAnswer: \n(c) Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar",
    "choices": "\n(a) Annie Besant\n\n(b) Debendranath Tagore\nIshwar Chandra Vidyasagar\n\n(d) Sarojini Naidu",
    "answer": "\n(c) Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar",
    "topic": "Spread of Education",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Spread of Education\nWho among the following was associated as Secretary with Hindu Female School which later came to be known as Bethune Female School?\n\n\na) Annie Besant\n\nb) Debendranath Tagore\nIshwar Chandra Vidyasagar\n\nd) Sarojini Naidu",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding Wood's Dispatch, which of the following statements\nare true?\n\n1. Grants-in-Aid system was introduced:\n\n2.Establishment of universities was\nrecommended:\n\n3.English as a medium of instruction at all\nlevels of education\nwas recommended:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1 and 2\nonly\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(a) 1 and 2 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2\nonly\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only",
    "topic": "Spread of Education",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Regarding Wood's Dispatch, which of the following statements are true?\n\n1. Grants-in-Aid system was introduced:\n\n2. Establishment of universities was recommended:\n\n3. English as a medium of instruction at all levels of education was recommended:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following were well known as champions of\nwomen's education in colonial India?\n\n1.Sister Subbalaksmi\n\n2.Begum Rokeya Sakhawat Hossain\n\n3.Keshub Chandra Sen\n\n4.Ananda Coomaraswamy\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below :\n\na) 1,2,3 and 4\n\nb)1,2 and 3\n\nc) 3 and 4 only\n\nd) 1 and 2 only\nAnswer: \n(b) 1, 2 and 3 only\nonly",
    "choices": "a) 1,2,3 and 4\n\nb)1,2 and 3\n\nc) 3 and 4 only\n\nd) 1 and 2 only",
    "answer": "\n(b) 1, 2 and 3 only\nonly",
    "topic": "Spread of Education",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following were well known as champions of women's education in colonial India?\n\n\n1. Sister Subbalaksmi\n\n2. Begum Rokeya Sakhawat Hossain\n\n3. Keshub Chandra Sen\n\n4. Ananda Coomaraswamy\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below :\n\n\na) 1,2,3 and 4\n\nb) 1,2 and 3\n\nc) 3 and 4 only\n\nd) 1 and 2 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where were the Ghadar revolutionaries, who became active\nduring the outbreak of World war\nbased\n\n(a) Central America\n\n(b) North America\n\n(c) West America\n\n(d) South America",
    "choices": "\n(a) Central America\n\n(b) North America\n\n(c) West America\n\n(d) South America",
    "answer": "\n(b) North America",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Where were the Ghadar revolutionaries, who became active during the outbreak of World war based\n\n\na) Central America\n\nb) North America\n\nc) West America\n\nd) South America",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "With\nreference\nto\nthe\nperiod\nof\nextremist\nnationalist\nmovement in India with its spirit f Swadeshi, which one of the\nfollowing statements is not correct?\n\n(a) Liaqat Hossian led the Muslim peasants of Barisal in their\nagitations\n\n(b) In\n1898,\nthe\nscheme\nof\nnational\neducation\nwas\nformulated by Satish Chandra Mukherjee\n\n(c) The Bengal National College\nwas founded in\n1906 with\nAurobindo as the principal\n\n(d) Tagore preached the cult of Atmashakti, the main plan of\nwhich\nwas the\nsocial and\neconomic regeneration\nof the\nvillages.",
    "choices": "\n(a) Liaqat Hossian led the Muslim peasants of Barisal in their\nagitations\n\n(b) In\n1898,\nthe\nscheme\nof\nnational\neducation\nwas\nformulated by Satish Chandra Mukherjee\n\n(c) The Bengal National College\nwas founded in\n1906 with\nAurobindo as the principal\n\n(d) Tagore preached the cult of Atmashakti, the main plan of\nwhich\nwas the\nsocial and\neconomic regeneration\nof the\nvillages.",
    "answer": "\n(a) Liaqat Hossian led the Muslim peasants of Barisal\nin their agitations",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to the period of extremist nationalist movement in India with its spirit f Swadeshi, which one of the following statements is not correct?\n\n\na) Liaqat Hossian led the Muslim peasants of Barisal in their agitations\n\nb) In 1898, the scheme of national education was formulated by Satish Chandra Mukherjee\n\nc) The Bengal National College was founded in 1906 with Aurobindo as the principal\n\nd) Tagore preached the cult of Atmashakti, the main plan of which was the social and economic regeneration of the villages.",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following were the main influences on Vasudeo\nBalvant Phadke?\n\n1. Experience of the Deccan famine of 1876-77\n\n2. Hindu revivalism\n\n3.Theory of Drain of Wealth\n\n4.The reformist idea of Phule\nSelect the correct answer\nusing the code given below :\n\na) 1,2 and 3\n\nb)2,3 and 4\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 2 and 4 only",
    "choices": "a) 1,2 and 3\n\nb)2,3 and 4\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 2 and 4 only",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1, 2 and 3",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following were the main influences on Vasudeo Balvant Phadke?\n\n1. Experience of the Deccan famine of 1876-77\n\n2. Hindu revivalism\n\n3. Theory of Drain of Wealth\n\n4. The reformist idea of Phule\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below :\n\na) 1,2 and 3\n\nb) 2,3 and 4\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 2 and 4 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about Sir Syed Ahmad Khan\nis/are correct?\n\n1.He\nargued\nthat\nIndia\nwas\na\nfederation\nof\nethnic\ncommunities based on common descent.\n\n2. His   philosophy\nwas\nvery\nsimilar\nto\nthat\nof\nthe\nIndian\nNational Congress.\n\n3.He imagined India\nas\na\nNation State based\non individual\ncitizen's rights.\n\n4.The curriculum at the Mohammedan Anglo-Oriental College\nblended Muslim theology and European empiricism:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2and3\n\nc) 3 only\n\nd) 1 and 4",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb) 2and3\n\nc) 3 only\n\nd) 1 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1 and 4",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about Sir Syed Ahmad Khan is/are correct?\nHe argued that India was a federation of ethnic communities based on common descent.\nHis philosophy was very similar to that of the Indian National Congress.\nHe imagined India as a Nation State based on individual citizen's rights.\nThe curriculum at the Mohammedan Anglo-Oriental College blended Muslim theology and European empiricism:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2and3\n\nc) 3 only\n\nd) 1 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "With\nreference\nto\nthe\nbook\n'Desher\nKatha'\nwritten\nby\nSakharam\nGanesh\nDeuskar   during\nthe\nfreedom\nstruggle,\nconsider the following statements:\n\n1.It warned against the Colonial State's hypnotic conquest of\nthe mind.\n\n2.It inspired the performance of swadeshi\nstreet plays and\nfolk songs.\n\n3.The use of 'desh' by Deuskar was in the specific context of\nthe region of Bengal:\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\n\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1,2 and 3",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1,2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to the book 'Desher Katha' written by Sakharam Ganesh Deuskar during the freedom struggle, consider the following statements:\n\n\n1. It warned against the Colonial State's hypnotic conquest of the mind.\n\n2. It inspired the performance of swadeshi street plays and folk songs.\n\n3. The use of 'desh' by Deuskar was in the specific context of the region of Bengal:\n\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\n\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 1,2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "After the First World War; the Triveni Sangh was formed by\n\na)the Jats and Gujjars\nbJthe Rajputs and Yadavs\n\nc)the Jats and Yadavs\n\nd)the Ahirs and Kurmis",
    "choices": "a)the Jats and Gujjars\nbJthe Rajputs and Yadavs\n\nc)the Jats and Yadavs\n\nd)the Ahirs and Kurmis",
    "answer": "\n(d) the Ahirs and Kurmis",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "After the First World War, the Triveni Sangh was formed by\n\na) the Jats and Gujjars\n\nb) the Rajputs and Yadavs\n\nc) the Jats and Yadavs\n\nd) the Ahirs and Kurmis",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nConsider the following freedom fighters:\n\na) Barindra Kumar Ghosh\n\nb)Jogesh Chandra Chatterjee\n\nc) Rash Behari Bose\nWho\nof the\nabove was/were actively\nassociated with\nthe\nGhadar Party?\n\n(a) 1 and 2\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) 1 and 3\n\n(d) 3 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) 1 and 3\n\n(d) 3 only",
    "answer": "\n(d) 3 only",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following freedom fighters: \n\na) Barindra Kumar Ghosh \n\nb)Jogesh Chandra Chatterjee \n\nc) Rash Behari Bose \nWho of the above was/were actively associated with the Ghadar Party? \n\n(a) 1 and 2 \n\n(b) 2 only \n\n(c) 1 and 3 \n\n(d) 3 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who founded the 'Seva Samiti at Allahabad in 1914?\n\na) Hridayanath Kunzru\n\nb)G. K: Gokhale\n\nc) Shri Ram Bajpai\n\nd)T: B. Sapru",
    "choices": "a) Hridayanath Kunzru\n\nb)G. K: Gokhale\n\nc) Shri Ram Bajpai\n\nd)T: B. Sapru",
    "answer": "\n(a) Hridayanath Kunzru",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who founded the 'Seva Samiti at Allahabad in 1914?\n\na) Hridayanath Kunzru\n\nb) G. K: Gokhale\n\nc) Shri Ram Bajpai\n\nd) T: B. Sapru",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Partition of Bengal made by Lord Curzon in 1905 lasted\nuntil\n\n(a) the First World War when Indian troops were needed\nby the British and the partition was ended:\n\n(b) King George\nV\nabrogated\nCurzon's\nAct\nat\nthe Royal\nDurbar in Delhi in 1911.\n\n(c) Gandhiji launched his Civil Disobedience\nMovement:\n\n(d) the Partition of India in 1947 when East Bengal became\nEast Pakistan.",
    "choices": "\n(a) the First World War when Indian troops were needed\nby the British and the partition was ended:\n\n(b) King George\nV\nabrogated\nCurzon's\nAct\nat\nthe Royal\nDurbar in Delhi in 1911.\n\n(c) Gandhiji launched his Civil Disobedience\nMovement:\n\n(d) the Partition of India in 1947 when East Bengal became\nEast Pakistan.",
    "answer": "\n(b) King George V abrogated Curzon's Act at the Royal\nDurbar in Delhi in 1911",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Partition of Bengal made by Lord Curzon in 1905 lasted until\n\na) the First World War when Indian troops were needed by the British and the partition was ended\n\nb) King George V abrogated Curzon's Act at the Royal Durbar in Delhi in 1911\n\nc) Gandhiji launched his Civil Disobedience Movement\n\nd) the Partition of India in 1947 when East Bengal became East Pakistan",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "A\nLondon\nbranch\nof\nthe\nAII\nIndia\nMuslim\nLeague\nwas\nestablished in 1908 under the presidency of\n\n(a) Aga Khan\n\n(b) Ameer Ali\n\n(c) Liyaqat Ali Khan\n\n(d) Ms\nA. Jinnah",
    "choices": "\n(a) Aga Khan\n\n(b) Ameer Ali\n\n(c) Liyaqat Ali Khan\n\n(d) Ms\nA. Jinnah",
    "answer": "\n(b) Ameer Ali",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "A London branch of the AII India Muslim League was established in 1908 under the presidency of\n\na) Aga Khan\n\nb) Ameer Ali\n\nc) Liyaqat Ali Khan\n\nd) Ms A. Jinnah",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which member of the Servants of India Society founded the\nSeva Samiti at Allahabad in 1914?\n\na) Shri Ram Bajpai\n\nb)Hriday Nath Kunzru\n\nc) S. G. Vaze\n\nd)Srinivas Shastri",
    "choices": "a) Shri Ram Bajpai\n\nb)Hriday Nath Kunzru\n\nc) S. G. Vaze\n\nd)Srinivas Shastri",
    "answer": "\n(b) Hriday Nath Kunzru",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which member of the Servants of India Society founded the Seva Samiti at Allahabad in 1914?\n\na) Shri Ram Bajpai\n\nb)Hriday Nath Kunzru\n\nc) S. G. Vaze\n\nd)Srinivas Shastri",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following is the author of the autobiography\nAamar Katha (1913)?\n\na) Satyajit\n\nb)Rassundari Devi\n\nc) Ganesh Chandra Ghosh\n\nd)Binodini Dasi",
    "choices": "a) Satyajit\n\nb)Rassundari Devi\n\nc) Ganesh Chandra Ghosh\n\nd)Binodini Dasi",
    "answer": "\n(d) Binodini Dasi",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following is the author of the autobiography Aamar Katha (1913)?\n\n\na) Satyajit\n\nb) Rassundari Devi\n\nc) Ganesh Chandra Ghosh\n\nd) Binodini Dasi",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements\n\n1.B. G. Tilak founded the Home Rule League in April 1916 in\nMaharashtra.\n\n2.N.\nC. Kelkar\nwas\nnot\nassociated\nwith\nthe\nHome\nRule\nMovement:\nWhich of the statements above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 only",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements\n\n1. B. G. Tilak founded the Home Rule League in April 1916 in Maharashtra.\n\n2. N. C. Kelkar was not associated with the Home Rule Movement:\nWhich of the statements above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ray\nFour resolutions were passed at the famous Calcutta session of\nIndian\nNational\nCongress\nin\n1906.\nThe question\nof\neither\nretention or of\nrejection of these four resolutions became the\ncause of split in Congress at the next congress session held in\nSurat in\n1907 .\nWhich of the following was\nnot\none of those\nresolutions?\n\n(a) Annulment of Partition of Bengal\n\n(b) Boycott\n\n(c) National Education\n\n(d) Swadeshi",
    "choices": "\n(a) Annulment of Partition of Bengal\n\n(b) Boycott\n\n(c) National Education\n\n(d) Swadeshi",
    "answer": "\n(a) Annulment of Partition of Bengal",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Ray Four resolutions were passed at the famous Calcutta session of Indian National Congress in 1906.\n\nThe question of either retention or of rejection of these four resolutions became the cause of split in Congress at the next congress session held in Surat in 1907.\n\nWhich of the following was not one of those resolutions?\n\n\na) Annulment of Partition of Bengal\n\n\nb) Boycott\n\n\nc) National Education\n\n\nd) Swadeshi\n",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the context of the Indian freedom struggle, 16 October 1905\nis well known for which of the following reasons?\n\n(a) The formal proclamation of the Swadeshi movement was\nmade in Calcutta Town Hall:\n\n(b) Partition of Bengal took effect:\n\n(c) Dadabhai Naoroji declared that the goal of the Indian\nNational Congress was Swaraj:\n\n(d) Lokmanaya\nTilak\nstarted\nthe\nSwadeshi\nmovement\nin\nPoona:",
    "choices": "\n(a) The formal proclamation of the Swadeshi movement was\nmade in Calcutta Town Hall:\n\n(b) Partition of Bengal took effect:\n\n(c) Dadabhai Naoroji declared that the goal of the Indian\nNational Congress was Swaraj:\n\n(d) Lokmanaya\nTilak\nstarted\nthe\nSwadeshi\nmovement\nin\nPoona:",
    "answer": "\n(b) Partition of Bengal took effect",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In the context of the Indian freedom struggle, 16 October 1905 is well known for which of the following reasons?\n\n(a) The formal proclamation of the Swadeshi movement was made in Calcutta Town Hall:\n\n(b) Partition of Bengal took effect:\n\n(c) Dadabhai Naoroji declared that the goal of the Indian National Congress was Swaraj:\n\n(d) Lokmanaya Tilak started the Swadeshi movement in Poona:",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "The headquarters of the Ghadar Movement/Party were at\n\na) San Francisco\n\nb)Stanford University\n\nc) Portland\n\nd)Florida",
    "choices": "a) San Francisco\n\nb)Stanford University\n\nc) Portland\n\nd)Florida",
    "answer": "\n(a) San Francisco",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The headquarters of the Ghadar Movement/Party were at \n\na) San Francisco \n\nb) Stanford University \n\nc) Portland \n\nd) Florida",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following\nwas\none\nof the founders\nof the\nIndian Society of Oriental Art?\n\na) Rabindranath Tagore\n\nb)Abanindranath Tagore\n\nc) Dwarakanath Tagore\n\nd)Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyaya",
    "choices": "a) Rabindranath Tagore\n\nb)Abanindranath Tagore\n\nc) Dwarakanath Tagore\n\nd)Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyaya",
    "answer": "\n(b) Abanindranath Tagore",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following was one of the founders of the Indian Society of Oriental Art?\n\na) Rabindranath Tagore\n\nb) Abanindranath Tagore\n\nc) Dwarakanath Tagore\n\nd) Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyaya",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following had organised, in 1904,\na\nsecret\nsociety of revolutionaries named Abhinav Bharat?\n\na) Khudiram Bose\n\nb)Shyamji Krishna Verma\n\nc) Har Dayal\n\nd) VD Savarkar",
    "choices": "a) Khudiram Bose\n\nb)Shyamji Krishna Verma\n\nc) Har Dayal\n\nd) VD Savarkar",
    "answer": "\n(d) V D Savarkar",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following had organised, in 1904, a secret society of revolutionaries named Abhinav Bharat?\n\n\na) Khudiram Bose\n\nb) Shyamji Krishna Verma\n\nc) Har Dayal\n\nd) VD Savarkar",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following formed the Seva Samiti\nScouts\nAssociation in 1914?\n\na) Hriday Nath Kunzru\n\nb)S. G. Vaze\n\nc) Annie Besant\n\nd)Shri Ram Bajpai",
    "choices": "a) Hriday Nath Kunzru\n\nb)S. G. Vaze\n\nc) Annie Besant\n\nd)Shri Ram Bajpai",
    "answer": "\n(d) Shri Ram Bajpai",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following formed the Seva Samiti Scouts Association in 1914? \n\n\na) Hriday Nath Kunzru\n\nb) S. G. Vaze\n\nc) Annie Besant\n\nd) Shri Ram Bajpai",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Boy\nThe year 1916 is important in Indian history for:\n\n1. Lucknow Session of the Congress\n\n2.Congress\nLeague Pact\n\n3. Formation of Home Rule League\nSelect the correct answer using the code given\n\na) 1 and 3\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 and 2 only\n\nd)1, 2 and 3",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 3\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 and 2 only\n\nd)1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1,2 and 3",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The year 1916 is important in Indian history for:\n\n\n1. Lucknow Session of the Congress\n\n2. Congress League Pact\n\n3. Formation of Home Rule League\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given\n\n\na) 1 and 3\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 and 2 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\namong\nthe\nfollowing\npioneering\nBengali\nwomen\nserialised her autobiography Amar Katha between\n1910 and\n1913?\n\na) Binodini Dasi\n\nb)Rashsundari Debi\n\nc) Begum Rokeya Sakhawat Hossain\n\nd) Kailashbashini Debi",
    "choices": "a) Binodini Dasi\n\nb)Rashsundari Debi\n\nc) Begum Rokeya Sakhawat Hossain\n\nd) Kailashbashini Debi",
    "answer": "\n(a) Binodini Dasi",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following pioneering Bengali women serialised her autobiography Amar Katha between 1910 and 1913?\n\na) Binodini Dasi\n\nb) Rashsundari Debi\n\nc) Begum Rokeya Sakhawat Hossain\n\nd) Kailashbashini Debi",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "only\nWith\nreference\nto\nthe\nSwadeshi\nMovement,\nconsider\nthe\nfollowing statements:\n\n1.It contributed to the revival of the indigenous artisan crafts\nand industries.\n\n2. The National Council of Education was established as a part\nof the Swadeshi Movement:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n(a) 1 only\n2 only\nTG\nBoth 1 and 2\nNeither 1 nor 2",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 only\n2 only\nTG\nBoth 1 and 2\nNeither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to the Swadeshi Movement, consider the following statements:\n\nIt contributed to the revival of the indigenous artisan crafts and industries.\n\nThe National Council of Education was established as a part of the Swadeshi Movement:\n\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n\na) 1 only\n2 only\nTG Both 1 and 2\nNeither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "He\nwrote\nbiographies\nof\nMazzini;, Garibaldi;\nShivaji\nand\nShrikrishna, stayed in\nAmerica for some time; and\nwas also\nelected to the\nCentral Assembly: He was:\n\n(a) Aurobindo Ghosh\n\n(b) Bipin Chandra Pal\n\n(c) Lala Lajpat Rai\n\n(d) Motilal Nehru",
    "choices": "\n(a) Aurobindo Ghosh\n\n(b) Bipin Chandra Pal\n\n(c) Lala Lajpat Rai\n\n(d) Motilal Nehru",
    "answer": "\n(c) Lala Lajpat Rai",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "He wrote biographies of Mazzini, Garibaldi, Shivaji and Shrikrishna, stayed in America for some time, and was also elected to the Central Assembly: He was:\n\na) Aurobindo Ghosh\n\nb) Bipin Chandra Pal\n\nc) Lala Lajpat Rai\n\nd) Motilal Nehru",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Ghadr (Ghadar) was a\n\n(a) Revolutionary\nAssociation\nof\nIndians,\nwith\nheadquarters in San Francisco\n\n(b) Nationalist organisation operating from Singapore\n\n(c) Militant organisation with headquarters in Berlin\n\n(d) Communist\nmovement\nfor\nIndia's\nfreedom\nwith\nheadquarters at Tashkent",
    "choices": "\n(a) Revolutionary\nAssociation\nof\nIndians,\nwith\nheadquarters in San Francisco\n\n(b) Nationalist organisation operating from Singapore\n\n(c) Militant organisation with headquarters in Berlin\n\n(d) Communist\nmovement\nfor\nIndia's\nfreedom\nwith\nheadquarters at Tashkent",
    "answer": "\n(a) Revolutionary\nAssociation\nOf\nIndians;\nwith\nheadquarters in San Francisco",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Ghadr (Ghadar) was a\n\n\na) Revolutionary Association of Indians, with headquarters in San Francisco\n\nb) Nationalist organisation operating from Singapore\n\nc) Militant organisation with headquarters in Berlin\n\nd) Communist movement for India's freedom with headquarters at Tashkent",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the immediate cause for the launch of the Swadeshi\nMovement?\n\n(a) The partition of Bengal done by Lord Curzon\n\n(b) A\nsentence\nof\n18\nmonths\nrigorous\nimprisonment\nimposed on Lokmanya Tilak\n\n(c) The\narrest and deportation\nof\nLala Lajpat\nRai and\nAjit\nSingh; and the passing f the Punjab colonisation bill\n\n(d) Death sentence pronounced on the Chapekar brothers",
    "choices": "\n(a) The partition of Bengal done by Lord Curzon\n\n(b) A\nsentence\nof\n18\nmonths\nrigorous\nimprisonment\nimposed on Lokmanya Tilak\n\n(c) The\narrest and deportation\nof\nLala Lajpat\nRai and\nAjit\nSingh; and the passing f the Punjab colonisation bill\n\n(d) Death sentence pronounced on the Chapekar brothers",
    "answer": "\n(a) The partition of Bengal done by Lord Curzon",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "What was the immediate cause for the launch of the Swadeshi Movement? \n\na) The partition of Bengal done by Lord Curzon \n\nb) A sentence of 18 months rigorous imprisonment imposed on Lokmanya Tilak \n\nc) The arrest and deportation of Lala Lajpat Rai and Ajit Singh; and the passing f the Punjab colonisation bill \n\nd) Death sentence pronounced on the Chapekar brothers",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nof the\nfollowing are true in the context of Swadeshi\nmovement in 1905?\n\n1. Massive demonstrations were held in Bengal\n\n2. Hartal was observed in Calcutta\n\n3. The\nmovement\nwas initiated\nby the\nmoderates\nbut\nwas\ntaken over by the revolutionary nationalists at a later stage\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1,2 and 3\n\nb)1 and 2 only\n\nc) 2 and 3 only\n\nd) 1 and 3 only",
    "choices": "a) 1,2 and 3\n\nb)1 and 2 only\n\nc) 2 and 3 only\n\nd) 1 and 3 only",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1, 2 and 3",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following are true in the context of Swadeshi movement in 1905? \n\n\n1. Massive demonstrations were held in Bengal \n\n2. Hartal was observed in Calcutta \n\n3. The movement was initiated by the moderates but was taken over by the revolutionary nationalists at a later stage \n\n\na) 1,2 and 3 \n\nb)1 and 2 only \n\nc) 2 and 3 only \n\nd) 1 and 3 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about Prarthana Samaj are\ncorrect?\n\n1.Its aim was to reform the Hindu society\n\n2.It was based in Maharashtra\n\n3.It believed in monotheism\n\n4.It had greatly influenced the Brahmo Samaj\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1, 2 and 3\n\nd)1 and 4",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1, 2 and 3\n\nd)1 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(c) 1, 2 and 3",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about Prarthana Samaj are correct?\nIts aim was to reform the Hindu society.\nIt was based in Maharashtra.\nIt believed in monotheism.\nIt had greatly influenced the Brahmo Samaj.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 1, 2 and 3\n\n(d) 1 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why was Vasudeo Balwant Phadke known in history?\n\na)He led a violent struggle against the British during the revolt\nof 1857\n\nb)He was a critic of Gandhian struggle\n\nc) He led an armed uprising against the British in the 1870s\n\nd)He was a radical leader of the Indian National Congress",
    "choices": "a)He led a violent struggle against the British during the revolt\nof 1857\n\nb)He was a critic of Gandhian struggle\n\nc) He led an armed uprising against the British in the 1870s\n\nd)He was a radical leader of the Indian National Congress",
    "answer": "\n(c) He led an armed uprising against the British in the\n1870s",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Why was Vasudeo Balwant Phadke known in history?\n\na) He led a violent struggle against the British during the revolt of 1857\n\nb) He was a critic of Gandhian struggle\n\nc) He led an armed uprising against the British in the 1870s\n\nd) He was a radical leader of the Indian National Congress",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "In 1920, which of the following changed its name to \"Swarajya\nSabha\"?\n\n(a) All India Home Rule League\nHindu Mahasabha\nTG\nSouth Indian Liberal Federation\nThe Servants of India Society",
    "choices": "\n(a) All India Home Rule League\nHindu Mahasabha\nTG\nSouth Indian Liberal Federation\nThe Servants of India Society",
    "answer": "\n(a) All India Home Rule League",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In 1920, which of the following changed its name to \"Swarajya Sabha\"?\n\na) All India Home Rule League\n\nb) Hindu Mahasabha\n\nc) TG\n\nd) South Indian Liberal Federation\ne) The Servants of India Society",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the main reason for the split in the Indian National\nCongress at Surat in 1907?\n\n(a) Introduction\nof communalism\ninto\nIndian politics by\nLord Minto.\n\n(b) Extremists'\nlack\nof\nfaith\nin\nthe\ncapacity\nof\nthe\nmoderates to negotiate with the\nBritish Government:\n\n(c) Foundation of Muslim League.\n\n(d) Aurobindo\nGhosh's\ninability\nto\nbe\nelected\nas\nthe\npresident of the Indian National Congress",
    "choices": "\n(a) Introduction\nof communalism\ninto\nIndian politics by\nLord Minto.\n\n(b) Extremists'\nlack\nof\nfaith\nin\nthe\ncapacity\nof\nthe\nmoderates to negotiate with the\nBritish Government:\n\n(c) Foundation of Muslim League.\n\n(d) Aurobindo\nGhosh's\ninability\nto\nbe\nelected\nas\nthe\npresident of the Indian National Congress",
    "answer": "\n(b) Extremists' lack of faith in\nthe capacity of the\nmoderates to negotiate with the British Government",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "What was the main reason for the split in the Indian National Congress at Surat in 1907?\n\na) Introduction of communalism into Indian politics by Lord Minto.\n\nb) Extremists' lack of faith in the capacity of the moderates to negotiate with the British Government:\n\nc) Foundation of Muslim League.\n\nd) Aurobindo Ghosh's inability to be elected as the president of the Indian National Congress",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following\na\nsystematic critique of the\nmoderate politics of the Indian National Congress in a series of\narticles entitled New Lamps for Old?\n\n(a) Aurobindo Ghosh\n\n(b) R.C. Dutt\n\n(c) Syed Ahmed Khan\n\n(d) Viraghavachariar",
    "choices": "\n(a) Aurobindo Ghosh\n\n(b) R.C. Dutt\n\n(c) Syed Ahmed Khan\n\n(d) Viraghavachariar",
    "answer": "\n(a) Aurobindo Ghosh",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following a systematic critique of the moderate politics of the Indian National Congress in a series of articles entitled New Lamps for Old?\n\n\na) Aurobindo Ghosh\n\nb) R.C. Dutt\n\nc) Syed Ahmed Khan\n\nd) Viraghavachariar",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "The song\n'Amar\nSonar Bangla'\nwritten during the Swadeshi\nmovement\nof\nIndia\ninspired\nthe\nliberation\nstruggle\nof\nBangladesh\nand\nwas\nadopted\nas\nthe\nNational\nAnthem\nof\nBangladesh: Who wrote this song?\n\n(a) Rajni Kanta Sen\n\n(b) Dwijendra lal Ray\n\n(c) Mukunda Das\n\n(d) Rabindra Nath Tagore",
    "choices": "\n(a) Rajni Kanta Sen\n\n(b) Dwijendra lal Ray\n\n(c) Mukunda Das\n\n(d) Rabindra Nath Tagore",
    "answer": "\n(d) Rabindra Nath Tagore",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The song 'Amar Sonar Bangla' written during the Swadeshi movement of India inspired the liberation struggle of Bangladesh and was adopted as the National Anthem of Bangladesh: Who wrote this song?\n\na) Rajni Kanta Sen\n\nb) Dwijendra lal Ray\n\nc) Mukunda Das\n\nd) Rabindra Nath Tagore",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "gave\nThe 'Swadeshi'\nand 'Boycott'\nwere adopted\nas\nmethods\nof\nstruggle for the first time during the\n\n(a) Agitation against the partition of Bengal\nHome Rule Movement\nT\nNon-Cooperation Movement\nVisit of Simon Commission to India",
    "choices": "\n(a) Agitation against the partition of Bengal\nHome Rule Movement\nT\nNon-Cooperation Movement\nVisit of Simon Commission to India",
    "answer": "\n(a) Agitation against the partition of Bengal",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The 'Swadeshi' and 'Boycott' were adopted as methods of struggle for the first time during the\n\na) Agitation against the partition of Bengal\nHome Rule Movement\nT\nNon-Cooperation Movement\nVisit of Simon Commission to India",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following movements has contributed to\na\nsplit in the Indian National Congress resulting in emergence\nof\n'moderates' and 'extremists'?\n\n(a) Swadeshi Movement\n\n(b) Quit India Movement\nNon-Cooperation Movement\n\n(d) Civil Disobedience Movement",
    "choices": "\n(a) Swadeshi Movement\n\n(b) Quit India Movement\nNon-Cooperation Movement\n\n(d) Civil Disobedience Movement",
    "answer": "\n(a) Swadeshi Movement",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following movements has contributed to a split in the Indian National Congress resulting in emergence of 'moderates' and 'extremists'?\n\n\na) Swadeshi Movement\n\n\nb) Quit India Movement\n\nNon-Cooperation Movement\n\n\nd) Civil Disobedience Movement",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nof\nthe\nfollowing\nstatements\nabout\nthe\nSwadeshi\nmovement in Bengal in 1905 are correct?\n\n1.It\nwas\nmarked\nby\nthe\nmass\nmobilisation\nthrough\nthe\norganisation of \"Samitis\"\n\n2. It\nwas\nmarked by the\nmass\nmobilisation through\nlabour\nstrikes\n\n3.It\nadvocated\na\nconstructive\nprogramme\nof self-help\nor\n\"Atma shakti\"\n\n4.In\nthe\nsphere\nof\neducation,\nnational\nschools\nwere\nestablished\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1,2 and 3 only\n\nb)1 and 4 only\n\nc) 2,3 and 4 only\n\nd)1,2,3 and 4",
    "choices": "a) 1,2 and 3 only\n\nb)1 and 4 only\n\nc) 2,3 and 4 only\n\nd)1,2,3 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1,2,3 and 4",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_2__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the Swadeshi movement in Bengal in 1905 are correct?\n\n1. It was marked by the mass mobilisation through the organisation of \"Samitis\"\n\n2. It was marked by the mass mobilisation through labour strikes\n\n3. It advocated a constructive programme of self-help or \"Atma shakti\"\n\n4. In the sphere of education, national schools were established\n\na) 1,2 and 3 only\n\nb) 1 and 4 only\n\nc) 2,3 and 4 only\n\nd) 1,2,3 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nof\nthe\nfollowing\nstatements\nabout\nthe\nShiromani\nGurudwara Prabandhak Committee (SGPC) correct?\n\n1.It began as the political wing of the Singh Sabhas in the late\n19th century:\n\n2.It\nwas\nformed\nin\n1920\nas\nof\nthe\nupcoming\nAkali\nmovement:\n\n3.It was founded to reclaim control of the Sikh shrines from\nthe government manipulated loyalist committees.\n\n4.It formed\nthe\nAkali\nDal to coordinate groups (Jathas)\nto\nreclaim control of the shrines to\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1,3 and 4\n\nb)2,3 and 4\n\nc) 2 and 4 only\n\nd)2 and 3 only\nAnswer: \n(b) 2,3 and 4",
    "choices": "a) 1,3 and 4\n\nb)2,3 and 4\n\nc) 2 and 4 only\n\nd)2 and 3 only",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2,3 and 4",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements - 2",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_aa6671__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the Shiromani Gurudwara Prabandhak Committee (SGPC) correct?\n\n1. It began as the political wing of the Singh Sabhas in the late 19th century:\n\n2. It was formed in 1920 as of the upcoming Akali movement:\n\n3. It was founded to reclaim control of the Sikh shrines from the government manipulated loyalist committees.\n\n4. It formed the Akali Dal to coordinate groups (Jathas) to reclaim control of the shrines to Select the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1,3 and 4\n\nb) 2,3 and 4\n\nc) 2 and 4 only\n\nd) 2 and 3 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nof\nthe\nfollowing\nstatements\nabout Jyotirao\nPhule's\nSatyashodhak Samaj Movement in Maharashtra is/are true?\n\n1. The Satyashodhak Samaj was set up in 1873.\n\n2.Phule argued that\nBrahmins\nwere\nthe\nprogeny\nof 'alien'\nAryans.\n\n3.Phule's\nfocus\non\nthe\nKunbi\npeasantry\nin\nthe\n1880s\nand\n1890s led to a privileging of Maratha identity:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd)1,2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(d) 1,2 and 3",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd)1,2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1,2 and 3",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements - 2",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_aa6671__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about Jyotirao Phule's Satyashodhak Samaj Movement in Maharashtra is/are true?\n\n1. The Satyashodhak Samaj was set up in 1873.\n\n2. Phule argued that Brahmins were the progeny of 'alien' Aryans.\n\n3. Phule's focus on the Kunbi peasantry in the 1880s and 1890s led to a privileging of Maratha identity:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Mahad Satyagraha of 1927 was organised by\n\na)B. R: Ambedkar\n\nb)Mahatma Gandhi\n\nc) S. C. Bose\n\nd)Lokmanya Tilak\nAnswer: \n(a) B. R: Ambedkar",
    "choices": "a)B. R: Ambedkar\n\nb)Mahatma Gandhi\n\nc) S. C. Bose\n\nd)Lokmanya Tilak",
    "answer": "\n(a) B. R: Ambedkar",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements - 2",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_aa6671__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Mahad Satyagraha of 1927 was organised by \n\na) B. R: Ambedkar\n\nb) Mahatma Gandhi\n\nc) S. C. Bose\n\nd) Lokmanya Tilak",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Satya Shodhak Samaj organised:\n\n(a) a\nmovement for the upliftment of tribals in\nBihar\n\n(b) a\ntemple-entry movement in Gujarat\nan anti-caste movement in Maharashtra\n\n(d) a\npeasant movement in Punjab\nAnswer: \n(c) an anti-caste movement in Maharashtra",
    "choices": "\n(a) a\nmovement for the upliftment of tribals in\nBihar\n\n(b) a\ntemple-entry movement in Gujarat\nan anti-caste movement in Maharashtra\n\n(d) a\npeasant movement in Punjab",
    "answer": "\n(c) an anti-caste movement in Maharashtra",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements - 2",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_aa6671__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Satya Shodhak Samaj organised:\n\n\na) a movement for the upliftment of tribals in Bihar\n\nb) a temple-entry movement in Gujarat\n\nc) an anti-caste movement in Maharashtra\n\nd) a peasant movement in Punjab",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nof\nthe\nfollowing parties were established by\nDr:\nB.R.\nAmbedkar?\n\n1. The Peasants and Workers Party of India\n\n2.AIl India Scheduled Castes Federation\n\n3. The Independent Labour Party\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3\nonly\n1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(b) 2 and 3 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3\nonly\n1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements - 2",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_aa6671__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following parties were established by Dr: B.R. Ambedkar? \n\n\n1. The Peasants and Workers Party of India \n\n\n2. AIl India Scheduled Castes Federation \n\n\n3. The Independent Labour Party \n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below: \n\n\na) 1 and 2 only \n\n\nb) 2 and 3 only \n\n1 and 3 only \n\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Self-Respect Movement was initiated by\n\na)B.R: Ambedkar\n\nb)Jyotiba Phule\n\nc) E.V: Ramaswamy Naicker\n\nd)Jawaharlal Nehru\nAnswer: \n(c) E.V: Ramaswamy Naicker",
    "choices": "a)B.R: Ambedkar\n\nb)Jyotiba Phule\n\nc) E.V: Ramaswamy Naicker\n\nd)Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "answer": "\n(c) E.V: Ramaswamy Naicker",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements - 2",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_aa6671__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Self-Respect Movement was initiated by \n\n\na) B.R: Ambedkar \n\nb) Jyotiba Phule \n\nc) E.V: Ramaswamy Naicker \n\nd) Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nThe Vital-Vidhwansak, the first monthly journal to\nhave the\nuntouchable people as its target audience, was published by:\n\n(a) Gopal Baba Walangkar\n\n(b) Jyotiba Phule\nMohandas Karamchand Gandhi\n\n(d) Bhimrao Ramji Ambedkar\nAnswer: \n(a) Gopal Baba Walangkar",
    "choices": "\n(a) Gopal Baba Walangkar\n\n(b) Jyotiba Phule\nMohandas Karamchand Gandhi\n\n(d) Bhimrao Ramji Ambedkar",
    "answer": "\n(a) Gopal Baba Walangkar",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements - 2",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_aa6671__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Vital-Vidhwansak, the first monthly journal to have the untouchable people as its target audience, was published by:\n\na) Gopal Baba Walangkar\n\nb) Jyotiba Phule Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi\n\nc) \n\nd) Bhimrao Ramji Ambedkar",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following pairs\nMovement/Organisation Leader\n\n1.All India Anti\nUntouchability League Mahatma Gandhi\n\n2.All India Kisan Sabha\nSwami Sahajanand\nSaraswati\n\n3.Self-Respect Movement\nNaicker E.V:\nRamaswami\nWhich of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched?\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements - 2",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_aa6671__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following pairs Movement/Organisation Leader. \n\n1. All India Anti Untouchability League Mahatma Gandhi.\n\n2. All India Kisan Sabha Swami Sahajanand Saraswati. \n\n3. Self-Respect Movement Naicker E.V: Ramaswami. \nWhich of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched? \n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1 and 2 only\n2 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Satyashodhak Samaj (Truth-Seeking Society) was set up by\n\na) Vinoba Bhave\n\nb)Jyotiba Phule\n\nc) B. R: Ambedkar\n\nd)C Rajagopalachari\nAnswer: \n(b) Jyotiba Phule",
    "choices": "a) Vinoba Bhave\n\nb)Jyotiba Phule\n\nc) B. R: Ambedkar\n\nd)C Rajagopalachari",
    "answer": "\n(b) Jyotiba Phule",
    "topic": "Social and Religious Reform Movements - 2",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_aa6671__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Satyashodhak Samaj (Truth-Seeking Society) was set up by\n\na) Vinoba Bhave\n\nb)Jyotiba Phule\n\nc) B. R: Ambedkar\n\nd)C Rajagopalachari",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following provisions\nwas\nNOT made in the\nCharter act of 1833\n\n(a) The trading activities of the East India Company were to\nbe abolished\n\n(b) The designation\nof the supreme authority\nwas\nto\nbe\nchanged as the Governor-General of India-in-Council\n\n(c) All law-making powers\nto\nbe\nconferred\non\nGovernor-\nGeneral-Council\n\n(d) An Indian was to be\nappointed as a law member in the\nGovernor-General's Council\nAnswer: \n(d) An Indian was to be\nappointed as a law member in\nthe Governor-General's Council",
    "choices": "\n(a) The trading activities of the East India Company were to\nbe abolished\n\n(b) The designation\nof the supreme authority\nwas\nto\nbe\nchanged as the Governor-General of India-in-Council\n\n(c) All law-making powers\nto\nbe\nconferred\non\nGovernor-\nGeneral-Council\n\n(d) An Indian was to be\nappointed as a law member in the\nGovernor-General's Council",
    "answer": "\n(d) An Indian was to be\nappointed as a law member in\nthe Governor-General's Council",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following provisions was NOT made in the Charter act of 1833\n\na) The trading activities of the East India Company were to be abolished\n\nb) The designation of the supreme authority was to be changed as the Governor-General of India-in-Council\n\nc) All law-making powers to be conferred on Governor-General-Council\n\nd) An Indian was to be appointed as a law member in the Governor-General's Council",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nof\nthe  following\nstatements   relating\nto\nthe\nIndian\nCouncils Act, 1861 is/are correct?\n\n1. The Act introduced a grain of popular element by including\nnon-official members in the Governor-General's Executive\nCouncil:\n\n2. The\nmembers\nwere\nnominated\nand their functions\nwere\nconfined\nexclusively\nto\nconsideration\nof\nlegislative\nproposals placed before it by the Governor-General:\n\n3.The\nGovernor-General\ndid\nnot\nhave\neffective legislative\npower:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1, 2 and 3\n\nd) 1 only\nAnswer: \n(a) 1 and 2 only",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1, 2 and 3\n\nd) 1 only",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements relating to the Indian Councils Act, 1861 is/are correct?\n\n1. The Act introduced a grain of popular element by including non-official members in the Governor-General's Executive Council:\n\n2. The members were nominated and their functions were confined exclusively to consideration of legislative proposals placed before it by the Governor-General:\n\n3. The Governor-General did not have effective legislative power:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1, 2 and 3\n\nd) 1 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "In\nthe\nGovernment\nof\nIndia\nAct\n1919,\nthe\nfunctions\nof\nProvincial\nGovernment\nwere\ndivided\ninto\n\"Reserved\"\nand\n\"Transferred\" subjects. Which of the following were treated as\n\"Reserved\" subjects?\n\n1. Administration of Justice\n\n2. Local Self-Government\n\n3. Land Revenue\n\n4.Police\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1, 2 and 3\n\n(b) 2,3 and 4\n1, 3 and 4\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 4\nAnswer: \n(c) 1,3 and 4",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1, 2 and 3\n\n(b) 2,3 and 4\n1, 3 and 4\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(c) 1,3 and 4",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In the Government of India Act 1919, the functions of Provincial Government were divided into \"Reserved\" and \"Transferred\" subjects. Which of the following were treated as \"Reserved\" subjects? \n\n1. Administration of Justice\n\n2. Local Self-Government\n\n3. Land Revenue\n\n4. Police\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below: \n\na) 1, 2 and 3 \n\nb) 2,3 and 4 \n\nc) 1, 3 and 4 \n\nd) 1, 2 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\none among the following\nwas\nnot\na\nprovision of the\nRegulating Act of 1773?\n\na)It introduced Parliamentary supervision over the East India\nCompany:\n\nb) The\nGovernment\nof\nBengal\nwas\nvested\nin\na\nGovernor\nGeneral and the Council of four members.\n\nc) It changed the power of the vote in the Court of Proprietors\nby removing all restrictions on qualifications.\n\nd) The Governor General was vested with a casting vote:\nAnswer: \n(c) It changed the power of the vote in the Court of\nProprietors by removing all restrictions on qualifications",
    "choices": "a)It introduced Parliamentary supervision over the East India\nCompany:\n\nb) The\nGovernment\nof\nBengal\nwas\nvested\nin\na\nGovernor\nGeneral and the Council of four members.\n\nc) It changed the power of the vote in the Court of Proprietors\nby removing all restrictions on qualifications.\n\nd) The Governor General was vested with a casting vote:",
    "answer": "\n(c) It changed the power of the vote in the Court of\nProprietors by removing all restrictions on qualifications",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one among the following was not a provision of the Regulating Act of 1773? \n\n(a)It introduced Parliamentary supervision over the East India Company: \n\n(b) The Government of Bengal was vested in a Governor General and the Council of four members. \n\n(c) It changed the power of the vote in the Court of Proprietors by removing all restrictions on qualifications. \n\n(d) The Governor General was vested with a casting vote:",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nBy which one of the following Acts was the Governor General\nof Bengal designated as the Governor General of India?\n\na) The Regulating Act\n\nb) The Pitt's India Act\n\nc) The Charter Act of 1793\n\nd) The Charter Act of 1833\nAnswer: \n(d) The Charter Act of 1833",
    "choices": "a) The Regulating Act\n\nb) The Pitt's India Act\n\nc) The Charter Act of 1793\n\nd) The Charter Act of 1833",
    "answer": "\n(d) The Charter Act of 1833",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "By which one of the following Acts was the Governor General of Bengal designated as the Governor General of India?\n\n\na) The Regulating Act\n\nb) The Pitt's India Act\n\nc) The Charter Act of 1793\n\nd) The Charter Act of 1833",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the\nfollowing statements about the Government\nof India Act of 1919 is not correct?\n\na) It extended the practice of communal representation:\n\nb)It made the Central Executive responsible to the Legislature:\n\nc) It is also known as the Montague-Chelmsford Reforms:\n\nd)lt paved the way for federalism by clearly separating the\nresponsibilities of the Centre and the Provinces\nAnswer: \n(b) It made the Central Executive responsible to the\nLegislature",
    "choices": "a) It extended the practice of communal representation:\n\nb)It made the Central Executive responsible to the Legislature:\n\nc) It is also known as the Montague-Chelmsford Reforms:\n\nd)lt paved the way for federalism by clearly separating the\nresponsibilities of the Centre and the Provinces",
    "answer": "\n(b) It made the Central Executive responsible to the\nLegislature",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following statements about the Government of India Act of 1919 is not correct?\n\na) It extended the practice of communal representation:\n\nb) It made the Central Executive responsible to the Legislature:\n\nc) It is also known as the Montague-Chelmsford Reforms:\n\nd) lt paved the way for federalism by clearly separating the responsibilities of the Centre and the Provinces",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Government of India Act of 1919 clearly defined\n\n(a) the separation of power between the judiciary and the\nlegislature\n\n(b) the\njurisdiction\nof\nthe\ncentral\nand\nprovincial\ngovernments\n\n(c) the powers of the Secretary of State for\nIndia and the\nViceroy\n\n(d) None of the above\nAnswer: \n(b) the jurisdiction\nOf the\ncentral\nand\nprovincial\ngovernments",
    "choices": "\n(a) the separation of power between the judiciary and the\nlegislature\n\n(b) the\njurisdiction\nof\nthe\ncentral\nand\nprovincial\ngovernments\n\n(c) the powers of the Secretary of State for\nIndia and the\nViceroy\n\n(d) None of the above",
    "answer": "\n(b) the jurisdiction\nOf the\ncentral\nand\nprovincial\ngovernments",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Government of India Act of 1919 clearly defined\n\n\n(a) the separation of power between the judiciary and the legislature\n\n\n(b) the jurisdiction of the central and provincial governments\n\n\n(c) the powers of the Secretary of State for India and the Viceroy\n\n\n(d) None of the above\n",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What\nwas/were\nthe\nobject/objects\nof\nQueen\nVictoria's\nProclamation (1858)?\n\n1. To disclaim any intention to annex Indian States.\n\n2. To place the Indian administration under the British Crown:\n\n3.To\nregulate East India Company's trade with India.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) 1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(a) To disclaim any intention to annex Indian States",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) 1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(a) To disclaim any intention to annex Indian States",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "What was/were the object/objects of Queen Victoria's Proclamation (1858)?\n\n\n1. To disclaim any intention to annex Indian States.\n\n2. To place the Indian administration under the British Crown:\n\n3. To regulate East India Company's trade with India.\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What\nwas\nthe\nreal\nintention\nof the\nBritish\nto\ninclude\nthe\nprincely states in the Federal Union proposed by the India Act\nof 1935?\n\n(a) Exercise\nmore\nand\ndirect  political\nand\nadministrative\ncontrol over the princely states\n\n(b) Involve the Princes activity in the administration of the\ncolony\n\n(c) Finally effect the complete political and administrative\ntakeover of all the princely states by the British\n\n(d) Use the princes to balance the anti-imperialist doctrines\nof the nationalist leaders\nAnswer: \n(d) Use the princes to\nbalance the anti-imperialist\ndoctrines of the nationalist leaders",
    "choices": "\n(a) Exercise\nmore\nand\ndirect  political\nand\nadministrative\ncontrol over the princely states\n\n(b) Involve the Princes activity in the administration of the\ncolony\n\n(c) Finally effect the complete political and administrative\ntakeover of all the princely states by the British\n\n(d) Use the princes to balance the anti-imperialist doctrines\nof the nationalist leaders",
    "answer": "\n(d) Use the princes to\nbalance the anti-imperialist\ndoctrines of the nationalist leaders",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "What was the real intention of the British to include the princely states in the Federal Union proposed by the India Act of 1935?\n\na) Exercise more and direct political and administrative control over the princely states\n\nb) Involve the Princes activity in the administration of the colony\n\nc) Finally effect the complete political and administrative takeover of all the princely states by the British\n\nd) Use the princes to balance the anti-imperialist doctrines of the nationalist leaders",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which Act of British India strengthened the Viceroy's authority\nover\nhis\nexecutive\nCouncil\nby substituting\na\n'portfolio'\nOr\ndepartmental system for corporate functioning?\n\n(a) Indian Councils Act, 1861\n\n(b) Government of India Act, 1858\n\n(c) Indian Councils Act, 1892\n\n(d) Indian Councils Act, 1909\nAnswer: \n(a) Indian Councils Act, 1861",
    "choices": "\n(a) Indian Councils Act, 1861\n\n(b) Government of India Act, 1858\n\n(c) Indian Councils Act, 1892\n\n(d) Indian Councils Act, 1909",
    "answer": "\n(a) Indian Councils Act, 1861",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which Act of British India strengthened the Viceroy's authority over his executive Council by substituting a 'portfolio' Or departmental system for corporate functioning?\n\na) Indian Councils Act, 1861\n\nb) Government of India Act, 1858\n\nc) Indian Councils Act, 1892\n\nd) Indian Councils Act, 1909",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why did the early nationalists oppose the Council Act of 1892?\n\na) The number of members of the Imperial Legislative Council\nwas increased\n\nb) The\nnumber\nof\nmembers\nof\nProvincial\nCouncils\nwas\nincreased\n\nc) The\nCouncils\nwere given the right to discuss the\nannual\nbudgets\n\nd) The\nAct did\nnot\nthe Indians control\nover the public\nfunds\nAnswer: \n(d) The Act did not give the Indians control over the\npublic funds",
    "choices": "a) The number of members of the Imperial Legislative Council\nwas increased\n\nb) The\nnumber\nof\nmembers\nof\nProvincial\nCouncils\nwas\nincreased\n\nc) The\nCouncils\nwere given the right to discuss the\nannual\nbudgets\n\nd) The\nAct did\nnot\nthe Indians control\nover the public\nfunds",
    "answer": "\n(d) The Act did not give the Indians control over the\npublic funds",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Why did the early nationalists oppose the Council Act of 1892?\n\na) The number of members of the Imperial Legislative Council was increased\n\nb) The number of members of Provincial Councils was increased\n\nc) The Councils were given the right to discuss the annual budgets\n\nd) The Act did not give the Indians control over the public funds",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1.Robert Clive was the first Governor-General of Bengal:\n\n2. William Bentinck was the first Governor- General of India.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) Both 1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(b) 2 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) Both 1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 only",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1. Robert Clive was the first Governor-General of Bengal.\n\n2. William Bentinck was the first Governor- General of India.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) Both 1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1. Warren Hastings was the first governor-general to establish\na\nregular police force in India based on the British pattern:\n\n2. Supreme\nCourt\nwas\nestablished\nat\nCalcutta\nby\nthe\nRegulating Act of 1773.\n\n3.The Indian Penal Code came into effect in the\n1860.\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\n\n(a) 1and 2\n\n(b) 2 and 3\n\n(c) 1 and 3\n\n(d) 1,2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(b) 2 and 3",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1and 2\n\n(b) 2 and 3\n\n(c) 1 and 3\n\n(d) 1,2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 and 3",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n\n1. Warren Hastings was the first governor-general to establish a regular police force in India based on the British pattern:\n\n2. Supreme Court was established at Calcutta by the Regulating Act of 1773.\n\n3. The Indian Penal Code came into effect in the 1860.\n\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\n\n\na) 1 and 2 \n\nb) 2 and 3 \n\nc) 1 and 3 \n\nd) 1,2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "When\nwas\nthe monopoly\nof China trade lost by\nEast India\nCompany?\n\na) 1813\n\nb) 1833\n\nc) 1838\n\nd)1860\nAnswer: \n(b) 1833",
    "choices": "a) 1813\n\nb) 1833\n\nc) 1838\n\nd)1860",
    "answer": "\n(b) 1833",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "When was the monopoly of China trade lost by East India Company?\n\na) 1813\n\nb) 1833\n\nc) 1838\n\nd) 1860",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Arrange\nthe  following\nin\nthe chronological\norder\nof their\nimplementation:\n\n1. The Indian Factory Act (First)\n\n2. The Vernacular Press Act\n\n3. The Morley-Minto Reforms\n\n4.The Cornwallis Code\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na)4,2,1, 3\n\nb)2,4, 1,3\n\nc) 3,4,1,2\n\nd)2,1,3,4\nAnswer: \n(a) 4,2,1,3",
    "choices": "a)4,2,1, 3\n\nb)2,4, 1,3\n\nc) 3,4,1,2\n\nd)2,1,3,4",
    "answer": "\n(a) 4,2,1,3",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Arrange the following in the chronological order of their implementation:\n\n1. The Indian Factory Act (First)\n\n2. The Vernacular Press Act\n\n3. The Morley-Minto Reforms\n\n4. The Cornwallis Code\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 4,2,1, 3\n\nb) 2,4, 1,3\n\nc) 3,4,1,2\n\nd) 2,1,3,4",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the\nfollowing statements about the Indian Councils\nAct of 1861 is/are correct?\n\n1.It enlarged the Governor General's Council for the purpose\nof making laws.\n\n2. The Governor General was not authorised to increase the\nnumber of members.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(a) 1 only",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 only",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the Indian Councils Act of 1861 is/are correct?\n\n1. It enlarged the Governor General's Council for the purpose of making laws.\n\n2. The Governor General was not authorised to increase the number of members.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following British officials was elevated to the\nposition of General after the Regulating Act of 1773?\n\na) Warren Hastings\n\nb)Lord North\n\nc) Mountstuart Elphinstone\n\nd)Philip Francis\nAnswer: \n(a) Warren Hastings",
    "choices": "a) Warren Hastings\n\nb)Lord North\n\nc) Mountstuart Elphinstone\n\nd)Philip Francis",
    "answer": "\n(a) Warren Hastings",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following British officials was elevated to the position of General after the Regulating Act of 1773?\n\na) Warren Hastings\n\nb) Lord North\n\nc) Mountstuart Elphinstone\n\nd) Philip Francis",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "The provision for separate electorate for Muslims was given in\n\na) Morlev-Minto Reforms, 1909\n\nb)Montagu-Chelmsford Reforms, 1919\n\nc) Communal Award, 1932\n\nd)Government of India Act, 1935\nAnswer: \n(a) Morley-Minto Reforms, 1909",
    "choices": "a) Morlev-Minto Reforms, 1909\n\nb)Montagu-Chelmsford Reforms, 1919\n\nc) Communal Award, 1932\n\nd)Government of India Act, 1935",
    "answer": "\n(a) Morley-Minto Reforms, 1909",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The provision for separate electorate for Muslims was given in\n\na) Morlev-Minto Reforms, 1909\n\nb) Montagu-Chelmsford Reforms, 1919\n\nc) Communal Award, 1932\n\nd) Government of India Act, 1935",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1. The Montagu-Chelmsford Reforms of\n1919 recommended\ngranting voting rights to all women above the age of 21.\n\n2. The Government of India Act of 1935 gave women reserved\nseats in the legislature:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n(a) 1\nonly\n2 only\nT\nBoth 1 and 2\nNeither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(b) 2 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1\nonly\n2 only\nT\nBoth 1 and 2\nNeither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 only",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1. The Montagu-Chelmsford Reforms of 1919 recommended granting voting rights to all women above the age of 21.\n\n2. The Government of India Act of 1935 gave women reserved seats in the legislature:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n2 only\nT\nBoth 1 and 2\nNeither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nof the following is/are the principal featurels) of the\nGovernment of India Act, 1919?\n\n1. Introduction of diarchy in the executive government of the\nprovinces\n\n2. Introduction of separate communal electorates for Muslims\n\n3.Devolution\nof legislative authority by\nthe center to\nthe\nprovinces\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(c) 1 and 3 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(c) 1 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following is/are the principal featurels) of the Government of India Act, 1919?\n\n1. Introduction of diarchy in the executive government of the provinces\n\n2. Introduction of separate communal electorates for Muslims\n\n3. Devolution of legislative authority by the center to the provinces\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n1 and 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "The distribution of powers between the Centre and the States\nin the Indian Constitution is based on the scheme provided in\nwhich of the following?\n\n(a) Morley Minto reforms 1909\n\n(b) Montague Chelmsford Act 1919\n\n(c) Government of India Act 1935\n\n(d) Indian independence Act 1947\nAnswer: \n(c) Government of India Act 1935",
    "choices": "\n(a) Morley Minto reforms 1909\n\n(b) Montague Chelmsford Act 1919\n\n(c) Government of India Act 1935\n\n(d) Indian independence Act 1947",
    "answer": "\n(c) Government of India Act 1935",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The distribution of powers between the Centre and the States in the Indian Constitution is based on the scheme provided in which of the following?\n\n\na) Morley Minto reforms 1909\n\n\nb) Montague Chelmsford Act 1919\n\n\nc) Government of India Act 1935\n\n\nd) Indian independence Act 1947\n",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements\nabout the\nMorley-Minto\nreforms of 1909:\n\n1. They were named after the British Parliamentarians Minto\nand Morley\n\n2. They provided for limited self-government by increasing the\nnumber of elected Indians in the Legislative Councils\n\n3. They contained provisions ensuring British officials retained\ntheir majority in the Imperial Legislative Council:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(b) 2 and 3 only",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements about the Morley-Minto reforms of 1909:\n\n\n1. They were named after the British Parliamentarians Minto and Morley\n\n2. They provided for limited self-government by increasing the number of elected Indians in the Legislative Councils\n\n3. They contained provisions ensuring British officials retained their majority in the Imperial Legislative Council:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements about 'the Charter Act of\n1813' :\n\n1.It ended the trade monopoly of the East India Company in\nIndia except for trade in tea and trade with China:\n\n2. It asserted the sovereignty of the British\nCrown\nover the\nIndian territories held by the Company:\n\n3. The revenues of India were\nnow\ncontrolled by the British\nParliament:\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\n\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(a) 1 and 2 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n1 and 3 only\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements about 'the Charter Act of 1813':\n\n\n1. It ended the trade monopoly of the East India Company in India except for trade in tea and trade with China:\n\n2. It asserted the sovereignty of the British Crown over the Indian territories held by the Company:\n\n3. The revenues of India were now controlled by the British Parliament:\n\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\n\n\na) 1 and 2 only \n\nb) 2 and 3 only \n1 and 3 only \n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the federation established by the Government of India Act\nof 1935, residuary powers given to the\n\n(a) Federal Legislature\n\n(b) Governor General\n\n(c) Provincial Legislature\n\n(d) Provincial Governors\nAnswer: \n(b) Governor General",
    "choices": "\n(a) Federal Legislature\n\n(b) Governor General\n\n(c) Provincial Legislature\n\n(d) Provincial Governors",
    "answer": "\n(b) Governor General",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In the federation established by the Government of India Act of 1935, residuary powers given to the\n\na) Federal Legislature\n\nb) Governor General\n\nc) Provincial Legislature\n\nd) Provincial Governors",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\nSome of the\nmain features of the Government of India Act,\n1935 were the\n\n1.Abolition of Dyarchy in the Governor's Provinces\n\n2. Power of the Governors to\nVeto legislative action and to\nlegislate on their own\n\n3.Abolition of the Principle of Communal Representation\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct? Choose\nthe correct answer from the following options:\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1and 2\n\n(c) 2 and 3\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(b) 1 and 2",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 1and 2\n\n(c) 2 and 3\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(b) 1 and 2",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements: Some of the main features of the Government of India Act, 1935 were the\n\n1. Abolition of Dyarchy in the Governor's Provinces\n\n2. Power of the Governors to Veto legislative action and to legislate on their own\n\n3. Abolition of the Principle of Communal Representation\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct? Choose the correct answer from the following options:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 2\n\nc) 2 and 3\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Montague-Chelmsford Report formed the basis of which\nof the following\n\n(a) Indian Council Act of 1909\n\n(b) Government of India Act of 1919\n\n(c) Indian Council Act of 1935\n\n(d) Indian Council Act of 1947\nAnswer: \n(b) Government of India Act of 1919",
    "choices": "\n(a) Indian Council Act of 1909\n\n(b) Government of India Act of 1919\n\n(c) Indian Council Act of 1935\n\n(d) Indian Council Act of 1947",
    "answer": "\n(b) Government of India Act of 1919",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Montague-Chelmsford Report formed the basis of which of the following\n\na) Indian Council Act of 1909\n\nb) Government of India Act of 1919\n\nc) Indian Council Act of 1935\n\nd) Indian Council Act of 1947",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "In\nthe\ncontext\nof Indian history,\nthe principle\nof\n'Dyarchy\n(diarchy)' refers to\n\n(a) Division of the central legislature into\ntwo houses.\n\n(b) Introduction of double government, i.e.,\nCentral and\nState governments.\n\n(c) Having two sets of rulers, one in London\nand another\nin Delhi:\n\n(d) Division of the subjects delegated to the provinces into\ntwo categories:\nAnswer: \n(d) Division of the subjects delegated to the provinces\ninto two categories",
    "choices": "\n(a) Division of the central legislature into\ntwo houses.\n\n(b) Introduction of double government, i.e.,\nCentral and\nState governments.\n\n(c) Having two sets of rulers, one in London\nand another\nin Delhi:\n\n(d) Division of the subjects delegated to the provinces into\ntwo categories:",
    "answer": "\n(d) Division of the subjects delegated to the provinces\ninto two categories",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In the context of Indian history, the principle of 'Dyarchy (diarchy)' refers to \n\na) Division of the central legislature into two houses.\n\nb) Introduction of double government, i.e., Central and State governments.\n\nc) Having two sets of rulers, one in London and another in Delhi:\n\nd) Division of the subjects delegated to the provinces into two categories:",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Montague-Chelmsford Proposals were related to\n\n(a) Social reforms\n\n(b) Education reforms\nReforms in public administration\n\n(d) Constitutional reforms\nAnswer: \n(d) Constitutional reforms",
    "choices": "\n(a) Social reforms\n\n(b) Education reforms\nReforms in public administration\n\n(d) Constitutional reforms",
    "answer": "\n(d) Constitutional reforms",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Montague-Chelmsford Proposals were related to\n\na) Social reforms\n\nb) Education reforms\nReforms in public administration\n\nd) Constitutional reforms",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements. relating to the Government\nof India Act, 1858 is/are correct?\n\n1. The British Crown assumed sovereignty over India from the\nEast India Company:\n\n2. The\nBritish\nParliament\nenacted\nthe\nfirst\nstatute\nfor\nthe\ngovernance of India under the direct rule of the British:\n\n3.This\nAct\nwas\ndominated\nby\nthe\nprinciple\nof\nabsolute\nimperial control without any popular participation in the\nadministration of the country:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) 1, 2 and 3\n\nd)1 and 3 only\nAnswer: \n(c) 1, 2 and 3",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) 1, 2 and 3\n\nd)1 and 3 only",
    "answer": "\n(c) 1, 2 and 3",
    "topic": "Constitutional Development",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_cfead8__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements relating to the Government of India Act, 1858 is/are correct? \n\n\n1. The British Crown assumed sovereignty over India from the East India Company:\n\n\n2. The British Parliament enacted the first statute for the governance of India under the direct rule of the British:\n\n\n3. This Act was dominated by the principle of absolute imperial control without any popular participation in the administration of the country:\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\n\nb) 2 only\n\n\nc) 1, 2 and 3\n\n\nd) 1 and 3 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was/were the formative influence(s) on the philosophy\nof Mahatma Gandhi?\n\n1.Gandhiji was influenced by the 18th-century Pranami sect\nthat advocated the unity of faiths.\n\n2. Gandhiji was influenced by the theosophists.\n\n3.Gandhiji was an admirer of Romantic writings, such as those\nof Wordsworth.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 2\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1,2 and 3\n\nd)1 only\nAnswer: \n(a) 1 and 2 only",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 2\n\nb)2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1,2 and 3\n\nd)1 only",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 and 2 only",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "What was/were the formative influence(s) on the philosophy of Mahatma Gandhi?\n\n1. Gandhiji was influenced by the 18th-century Pranami sect that advocated the unity of faiths.\n\n2. Gandhiji was influenced by the theosophists.\n\n3. Gandhiji was an admirer of Romantic writings, such as those of Wordsworth.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1 and 2\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n\n(c) 1, 2 and 3\n\n(d) 1 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mahatma Gandhi said that some of his deepest convictions\nwere reflected in a book titled, \"Unto this Last\" and the book\ntransformed his life. What was the message from the book that\ntransformed Mahatma Gandhi?\n\n(a) Uplifting\nthe\noppressed\nand\npoor\nis\nthe\nmoral\nresponsibility of an educated man\n\n(b) The good of an individual is contained in\nthe good of\nall\n\n(c) The life of celibacy and spiritual pursuit\nare essential\nfor a noble life\n\n(d) All the statements \n(a), \n(b) and \n(c) are correct in this\ncontext\nAnswer: \n(b) The good of an individual is contained in\nthe good\nof all",
    "choices": "\n(a) Uplifting\nthe\noppressed\nand\npoor\nis\nthe\nmoral\nresponsibility of an educated man\n\n(b) The good of an individual is contained in\nthe good of\nall\n\n(c) The life of celibacy and spiritual pursuit\nare essential\nfor a noble life\n\n(d) All the statements \n(a), \n(b) and \n(c) are correct in this\ncontext",
    "answer": "\n(b) The good of an individual is contained in\nthe good\nof all",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Mahatma Gandhi said that some of his deepest convictions were reflected in a book titled, \"Unto this Last\" and the book transformed his life. What was the message from the book that transformed Mahatma Gandhi?\n\n\na) Uplifting the oppressed and poor is the moral responsibility of an educated man \n\nb) The good of an individual is contained in the good of all \n\nc) The life of celibacy and spiritual pursuit are essential for a noble life \n\nd) All the statements \n(a), \n(b) and \n(c) are correct in this context",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nWho\namong\nthe following\nis\nassociated\nwith  'Songs\nfrom\nPrison',\na\ntranslation\nof\nancient\nIndian\nreligious\nlyrics\nin\nEnglish?\n\n(a) Bal Gangadhar Tilak\n\n(b) Jawaharlal Nehru\nMohandas Karamchand Gandhi\n\n(d) Sarojini Naidu\nAnswer: \n(c) Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi",
    "choices": "\n(a) Bal Gangadhar Tilak\n\n(b) Jawaharlal Nehru\nMohandas Karamchand Gandhi\n\n(d) Sarojini Naidu",
    "answer": "\n(c) Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following is associated with 'Songs from Prison', a translation of ancient Indian religious lyrics in English?\n\na) Bal Gangadhar Tilak\n\nb) Jawaharlal Nehru\nMohandas Karamchand Gandhi\n\nd) Sarojini Naidu",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following is\na\nvery significant aspect of the\nChamparan Satyagraha?\n\n(a) Active all-India participation of lawyers,\nstudents and\nwomen in the National Movement\n\n(b) Active involvvement of Dalit and Tribal\ncommunities of\nIndia in the National Movement\n\n(c) Joining of peasant unrest to India's National Movement\n\n(d) Drastic decrease in the cultivation of plantation crops\nand commercial crops\nAnswer: \n(c) Joining\nof peasant\nunrest\nto\nIndia'$ National\nMovement",
    "choices": "\n(a) Active all-India participation of lawyers,\nstudents and\nwomen in the National Movement\n\n(b) Active involvvement of Dalit and Tribal\ncommunities of\nIndia in the National Movement\n\n(c) Joining of peasant unrest to India's National Movement\n\n(d) Drastic decrease in the cultivation of plantation crops\nand commercial crops",
    "answer": "\n(c) Joining\nof peasant\nunrest\nto\nIndia'$ National\nMovement",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following is a very significant aspect of the Champaran Satyagraha?\n\n\na) Active all-India participation of lawyers, students and women in the National Movement\n\nb) Active involvvement of Dalit and Tribal communities of India in the National Movement\n\nc) Joining of peasant unrest to India's National Movement\n\nd) Drastic decrease in the cultivation of plantation crops and commercial crops",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "In India, the first major public appearance of Mahatma Gandhi\nwas in\n\na) Champaran (1917)\n\nb)Kheda (1918)\n\nc) Inauguration of Banaras Hindu University (1916)\n\nd)Rowlatt Satyagraha (1919)\nAnswer: \n(c) Inauguration of Banaras Hindu University (1916)",
    "choices": "a) Champaran (1917)\n\nb)Kheda (1918)\n\nc) Inauguration of Banaras Hindu University (1916)\n\nd)Rowlatt Satyagraha (1919)",
    "answer": "\n(c) Inauguration of Banaras Hindu University (1916)",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In India, the first major public appearance of Mahatma Gandhi was in\n\na) Champaran (1917)\n\nb)Kheda (1918)\n\nc) Inauguration of Banaras Hindu University (1916)\n\nd)Rowlatt Satyagraha (1919)",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\namong\nthe following political\nleaders  suggested\nthe\ndissolution\nof\nthe\nIndian\nNational Congress\nas\na\npolitical\norganization and its replacement by a Lok Sevak Sangh?\n\na) Vallabhbhai Patel\n\nb)Dr: B. R: Ambedkar\n\nc) M: K. Gandhi\n\nd)Jawaharlal Nehru\nAnswer: \n(c) M: K Gandhi",
    "choices": "a) Vallabhbhai Patel\n\nb)Dr: B. R: Ambedkar\n\nc) M: K. Gandhi\n\nd)Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "answer": "\n(c) M: K Gandhi",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following political leaders suggested the dissolution of the Indian National Congress as a political organization and its replacement by a Lok Sevak Sangh?\n\na) Vallabhbhai Patel\n\nb) Dr: B. R: Ambedkar\n\nc) M: K. Gandhi\n\nd) Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\namong\nthe   following\nstatements\nabout\nMahatma\nGandhi's Satyagraha is/are correct?\n\n1.It was\nduring the course of his campaign against racialism in\nSouth Africa that Gandhiji first applied Satyagraha\n\n2. The two vital ingredients of Satyagraha are 'truth' and 'non-\nviolence'\n\n3.The Satyagrahi resists evil by inflicting suffering on himself\nand not by inflicting suffering on the opponent\n\n4.In India, Satyagraha was first tried by Gandhiji in Champaran\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 4 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) 4 only\n\nd)1,2,3 and 4\nAnswer: \n(d) 1, 2, 3 and 4",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 4 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) 4 only\n\nd)1,2,3 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1, 2, 3 and 4",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which among the following statements about Mahatma Gandhi's Satyagraha is/are correct?\n\n1. It was during the course of his campaign against racialism in South Africa that Gandhiji first applied Satyagraha\n\n2. The two vital ingredients of Satyagraha are 'truth' and 'non-violence'\n\n3. The Satyagrahi resists evil by inflicting suffering on himself and not by inflicting suffering on the opponent\n\n4. In India, Satyagraha was first tried by Gandhiji in Champaran\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 4 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) 4 only\n\nd) 1, 2, 3 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where and when did Mahatma Gandhi first use his method of\nhunger strike to achieve a desired goal?\n\na)At Natal in South Africa in the year 1906\n\nb)At Champaran in the year 1917\n\nc) At Ahmedabad in the\n1918\n\nd)At Cape Town in South Africa in the year 1906\nAnswer: \n(c) At Ahmedabad in the year 1918",
    "choices": "a)At Natal in South Africa in the year 1906\n\nb)At Champaran in the year 1917\n\nc) At Ahmedabad in the\n1918\n\nd)At Cape Town in South Africa in the year 1906",
    "answer": "\n(c) At Ahmedabad in the year 1918",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Where and when did Mahatma Gandhi first use his method of hunger strike to achieve a desired goal?\n\na) At Natal in South Africa in the year 1906\n\nb) At Champaran in the year 1917\n\nc) At Ahmedabad in the 1918\n\nd) At Cape Town in South Africa in the year 1906",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\namong\nthe\nfollowing\nwas\nthe\nfounder\nof\nPhoenix\nSettlement?\n\na) Mahatma Gandhi\n\nb)B. R: Ambedkar\n\nc) Rabindranath Tagore\n\nd)Swami Vivekananda\nAnswer: \n(a) Mahatma Gandhi",
    "choices": "a) Mahatma Gandhi\n\nb)B. R: Ambedkar\n\nc) Rabindranath Tagore\n\nd)Swami Vivekananda",
    "answer": "\n(a) Mahatma Gandhi",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following was the founder of Phoenix Settlement?\n\na) Mahatma Gandhi\n\nb) B. R: Ambedkar\n\nc) Rabindranath Tagore\n\nd) Swami Vivekananda",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What\nwas\nthe\nreason\nfor\nMahatma\nGandhi\nto\norganise\na\nsatyagraha on behalf of the peasants of Kheda?\n\n1. The\nAdministration\ndid\nnot\nsuspend\nthe\nland\nrevenue\ncollection in spite of a drought:\n\n2. The\nAdministration\nproposed\nto\nintroduce\nPermanent\nSettlement in\nGujarat:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n(a) 1 only\n2 only\nTG\nBoth 1 and 2\nNeither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(a) 1 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 only\n2 only\nTG\nBoth 1 and 2\nNeither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 only",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "What was the reason for Mahatma Gandhi to organise a satyagraha on behalf of the peasants of Kheda? \n\n1. The Administration did not suspend the land revenue collection in spite of a drought:\n\n2. The Administration proposed to introduce Permanent Settlement in Gujarat: \nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n\na) 1 only\n2 only\nTG Both 1 and 2\nNeither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nof\nthe following\nstatements\nabout\nthe Champaran\nSatyagraha is/are correct?\n\n1. The Champaran region had a long tradition of anti-planter\ndiscontent and agitation\n\n2.Mahatma Gandhi gave all India publicity to the grievances\nof Champaran cultivators\n\n3. The\ncultivators\nof\nChamparan\nhad\nprotested\nagainst\nexcessive taxation on sugar\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)1 and 2 only\n\nc) 2 and 3\n\nd)1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(b) 1 and 2 only",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)1 and 2 only\n\nc) 2 and 3\n\nd)1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(b) 1 and 2 only",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the Champaran Satyagraha is/are correct? \n\n1. The Champaran region had a long tradition of anti-planter discontent and agitation \n\n2. Mahatma Gandhi gave all India publicity to the grievances of Champaran cultivators \n\n3. The cultivators of Champaran had protested against excessive taxation on sugar \nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 2 only\n\nc) 2 and 3\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1.Dr Rajendra Prasad persuaded Mahatma Gandhi to come to\nChamparan to investigate the problem of peasants\n\n2. Acharya\nJ.\nB.\nKriplani\nwas\none\nof\nMahatma\nGandhi's\ncolleagues in\nhis Champaran investigation.\nWhich\nof the\nstatements given above is/are correct?\nChoose the correct answer from the following options:\n\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) Both 1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(b) 2 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 only\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) Both 1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 only",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1. Dr Rajendra Prasad persuaded Mahatma Gandhi to come to Champaran to investigate the problem of peasants\n\n2. Acharya J. B. Kriplani was one of Mahatma Gandhi's colleagues in his Champaran investigation.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\nChoose the correct answer from the following options:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following founded\nthe\nAhmedabad\nTextile\nLabour Association?\n\n(a) Mahatma Gandhi\n\n(b) Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel\n\n(c) N. M. Joshi\n\n(d) J. B. Kriplanians\nAnswer: \n(a) Mahatma Gandhi",
    "choices": "\n(a) Mahatma Gandhi\n\n(b) Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel\n\n(c) N. M. Joshi\n\n(d) J. B. Kriplanians",
    "answer": "\n(a) Mahatma Gandhi",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following founded the Ahmedabad Textile Labour Association?\n\n\na) Mahatma Gandhi\n\nb) Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel\n\nc) N. M. Joshi\n\nd) J. B. Kriplanians",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider\nthe\nfollowing\nstatements.\nabout\nthe\ndifferent\nmeanings of 'Swaraj' as articulated by Mahatma Gandhi:\n\n1.Swaraj is intimately linked with Ahimsa (non-violence) and\nSatyagraha (adherence to truth):\n\n2.Swaraj has two\nsenses-one political and\none beyond the\nrealm of politics.\n\n3.Swaraj\nis\nsomething that requires time\nand patience\nto\nacquire:\n\n4.With determination, Swaraj could\nbe obtained easily and\nquickly:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 2 only:\n\nc) 3 and 4\n\nd)1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(d) 1,2 and 3",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 2 only:\n\nc) 3 and 4\n\nd)1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1,2 and 3",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements about the different meanings of 'Swaraj' as articulated by Mahatma Gandhi:\n\n1. Swaraj is intimately linked with Ahimsa (non-violence) and Satyagraha (adherence to truth):\n\n2. Swaraj has two senses - one political and one beyond the realm of politics.\n\n3. Swaraj is something that requires time and patience to acquire:\n\n4. With determination, Swaraj could be obtained easily and quickly:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct? \n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 2 only:\n\nc) 3 and 4\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which one of the\nfollowing places did Mahatma Gandhi first\nstart his Satyagraha in India?\n\n(a) Ahmedabad\n\n(b) Bardoli\n\n(c) Champaran\n\n(d) Kheda\nAnswer: \n(c) Champaran",
    "choices": "\n(a) Ahmedabad\n\n(b) Bardoli\n\n(c) Champaran\n\n(d) Kheda",
    "answer": "\n(c) Champaran",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "At which one of the following places did Mahatma Gandhi first start his Satyagraha in India? \n\n(a) Ahmedabad \n\n(b) Bardoli \n\n(c) Champaran \n\n(d) Kheda",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following pairs are correctly matched?\nMovement/ Satyagraha: Person actively associated with\n\n1. Champaran: Rajendra Prasad\n\n2.Ahmedabad mill workers: Morarji Desai\n\n3.Kheda: Vallabhbhai Patel\nChoose the correct answer from the\nfollowing options.\n\n(a) 1 and 2\n\n(b) 2 and 3\n\n(c) 1 and 3\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(c) 1 and 3",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2\n\n(b) 2 and 3\n\n(c) 1 and 3\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(c) 1 and 3",
    "topic": "Gandhi's Formative Years and Early Activism",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9a31ee__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following pairs are correctly matched?\nMovement/ Satyagraha: Person actively associated with\n\n1. Champaran: Rajendra Prasad\n\n2. Ahmedabad mill workers: Morarji Desai\n\n3. Kheda: Vallabhbhai Patel\nChoose the correct answer from the following options.\n\na) 1 and 2\n\nb) 2 and 3\n\nc) 1 and 3\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following was the author of Hind Swaraj?",
    "choices": "a)Aurobindo Ghose\n\nb)c: R: Das\n\nc) Mahatma Gandhi\n\nd)Rajendra Prasad",
    "answer": "\n(c) Mahatma Gandhi",
    "topic": "Great Personalities",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1617df__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following was the author of Hind Swaraj?",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who amongst the following organized the All India Scheduled\nCastes Federation?",
    "choices": "a)Jyotiba Phule\n\nb)Periyar\n\nc) B. R: Ambedkar\n\nd)M: K. Karunanidhi",
    "answer": "\n(c) B. R. Ambedkar",
    "topic": "Great Personalities",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1617df__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who amongst the following organized the All India Scheduled Castes Federation?",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "The social ideals of Mahatma Gandhi were first put forth in",
    "choices": "a) Hind Swaraj\n\nb)An Autobiography- The Story of My Experiments with Truth\n\nc) History of the Satyagraha in South Africa\n\nd) The Bhagavad Gita According to Gandhi",
    "answer": "\n(a) Hind Swaraj",
    "topic": "Great Personalities",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1617df__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The social ideals of Mahatma Gandhi were first put forth in",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following features of the State of Arcot in\ncentury South India are correct?\n\n1.The founders of the dynasty that ruled\nArcot\nwere\nDaud\nKhan Panni and Saadatullah Khan:\n\n2.Arcot became the site of a protracted struggle between the\nEnglish and Dutch East India Companies in the 1740s.\n\n3. Decentralisation\nwas\na\nkey feature of the State of Arcot in\nthe\ncentury:\n\n4.The other major state that emerged in South India at this\ntime was\nMysore.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 2\n\nb)1,2 and 4\n\nc) 2 and 4\n\nd)3 and 4\nAnswer: \n(b) 1,2 and 4",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 2\n\nb)1,2 and 4\n\nc) 2 and 4\n\nd)3 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(b) 1,2 and 4",
    "topic": "Rise and Fall of Regional Powers",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_b41688__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following features of the State of Arcot in century South India are correct? \n\n\n1. The founders of the dynasty that ruled Arcot were Daud Khan Panni and Saadatullah Khan: \n\n2. Arcot became the site of a protracted struggle between the English and Dutch East India Companies in the 1740s. \n\n3. Decentralisation was a key feature of the State of Arcot in the century: \n\n4. The other major state that emerged in South India at this time was Mysore. \n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below: \n\n\na) 1 and 2 \n\nb) 1,2 and 4 \n\nc) 2 and 4 \n\nd) 3 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "18th\n18th\nMarthanda Varma of Travancore Kingdom defeated the Dutch\nin the battle of\n\na) Wandiwash\n\nb) Rakshasi\nTangadi\n\nc) Pullalur\n\nd) Colachel\nAnswer: \n(d) Colachel",
    "choices": "a) Wandiwash\n\nb) Rakshasi\nTangadi\n\nc) Pullalur\n\nd) Colachel",
    "answer": "\n(d) Colachel",
    "topic": "Rise and Fall of Regional Powers",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_b41688__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Marthanda Varma of Travancore Kingdom defeated the Dutch in the battle of\n\n\na) Wandiwash\n\n\nb) Rakshasi Tangadi\n\n\nc) Pullalur\n\n\nd) Colachel",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the first Nawab Wazir of Awadh in the\ncentury?\n\na) Nawab Safdarjung\n\nb) Nawab Saadat Ali Khan\n\nc) Nawab Shuja-ud-Daula\n\nd) Nawab Saadat Khan\nAnswer: \n(d) Nawab Saadat Khan",
    "choices": "a) Nawab Safdarjung\n\nb) Nawab Saadat Ali Khan\n\nc) Nawab Shuja-ud-Daula\n\nd) Nawab Saadat Khan",
    "answer": "\n(d) Nawab Saadat Khan",
    "topic": "Rise and Fall of Regional Powers",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_b41688__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who was the first Nawab Wazir of Awadh in the century?\n\na) Nawab Safdarjung\n\nb) Nawab Saadat Ali Khan\n\nc) Nawab Shuja-ud-Daula\n\nd) Nawab Saadat Khan",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "What were the 12 states of the Sikh confederacy called?\n\na) Misl\n\nb)Gurmata\n\nc) Sardari\n\nd)Rakhi\nAnswer: \n(a) Misl",
    "choices": "a) Misl\n\nb)Gurmata\n\nc) Sardari\n\nd)Rakhi",
    "answer": "\n(a) Misl",
    "topic": "Rise and Fall of Regional Powers",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_b41688__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "What were the 12 states of the Sikh confederacy called?\n\na) Misl\n\nb)Gurmata\n\nc) Sardari\n\nd)Rakhi",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "18th\nWhich\nof\nthe following  characteristics\nabout\nthe\nstate\nof\nTravancore in 18th century Kerala is/are correct?\n\n1. Travancore\nwas ruled by Marthanda Varma from\n1729 to\n1758.\n\n2. Travancore built a strong army and defeated the Dutch in\n1741.\n\n3. Travancore was an important centre of learning:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) 1,2 and 3\n\nd) 1 only\nAnswer: \n(c) 1,2 and 3",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) 1,2 and 3\n\nd) 1 only",
    "answer": "\n(c) 1,2 and 3",
    "topic": "Rise and Fall of Regional Powers",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_b41688__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following characteristics about the state of Travancore in 18th century Kerala is/are correct?\n\n1. Travancore was ruled by Marthanda Varma from 1729 to 1758.\n\n2. Travancore built a strong army and defeated the Dutch in 1741.\n\n3. Travancore was an important centre of learning:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n1. 1 and 2 only\n\n2. 2 only\n\n3. 1,2 and 3\n\n4. 1 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nWho among the following Indian rules established embassies\nin foreign countries on modern lines?\n\n(a) Hyder Ali\n\n(b) Mir Qasim\n\n(c) Shah Alam II\n\n(d) Tipu Sultan\nAnswer: \n(d) Tipu Sultan",
    "choices": "\n(a) Hyder Ali\n\n(b) Mir Qasim\n\n(c) Shah Alam II\n\n(d) Tipu Sultan",
    "answer": "\n(d) Tipu Sultan",
    "topic": "Rise and Fall of Regional Powers",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_b41688__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following Indian rules established embassies in foreign countries on modern lines?\n\n\na) Hyder Ali \n\nb) Mir Qasim \n\nc) Shah Alam II \n\nd) Tipu Sultan",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the battle in\nwhich the Travancore King defeated the\nDutch in 1741.\n\na) The Battle of Porto Novo\n\nb) The Battle of Colachel\n\nc) The Battle of Pollilore\n\nd)The Battle of Changanassery\nAnswer: \n(b) The Battle of Colachel",
    "choices": "a) The Battle of Porto Novo\n\nb) The Battle of Colachel\n\nc) The Battle of Pollilore\n\nd)The Battle of Changanassery",
    "answer": "\n(b) The Battle of Colachel",
    "topic": "Rise and Fall of Regional Powers",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_b41688__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Name the battle in\nwhich the Travancore King defeated the\nDutch in 1741.\n\n\na) The Battle of Porto Novo\n\nb) The Battle of Colachel\n\nc) The Battle of Pollilore\n\nd) The Battle of Changanassery",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to the\nperiod of India freedom struggle, which\nof\nthe   following\nwas/were\nrecommended\nby\nthe\nNehru\nReport?\n\n1.Complete Independence for India:\n\n2.Joint electorates for reservation of\nseats for minorities.\n\n3.Provision of fundamental rights for the people of India in\nthe Constitution.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1 only\n2 and 3 only\nT\n1and 3 only\n1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(b) 2 and 3 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 only\n2 and 3 only\nT\n1and 3 only\n1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Simon Commission and Poorna Swaraj",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_044dc9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to the period of India freedom struggle, which of the following was/were recommended by the Nehru Report?\n\n1. Complete Independence for India\n\n2. Joint electorates for reservation of seats for minorities\n\n3. Provision of fundamental rights for the people of India in the Constitution\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 and 3 only\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "With\nreference\nto\nSimon\nCommission's\nrecommendations,\nwhich one of the following statements is correct?\n\n(a) It\nrecommends\nthe\nreplacement\nof\nDyarchy\nwith\nresponsible government in the provinces:\n\n(b) It proposed\nthe setting\nup\nof inter provincial\ncouncil\nunder the Home Department:\n\n(c) It\nsuggested the abolition of bicameral Legislature at the\ncentre.\n\n(d) It recommended\nthe\ncreation\nof Indian\nPolice\nService\nwith the provision for increased\npay\nand\nallowances for\nBritish recruits as compared to Indian recruits.\nAnswer: \n(a) It recommends the replacement of Dyarchy with\nresponsible government in the provinces",
    "choices": "\n(a) It\nrecommends\nthe\nreplacement\nof\nDyarchy\nwith\nresponsible government in the provinces:\n\n(b) It proposed\nthe setting\nup\nof inter provincial\ncouncil\nunder the Home Department:\n\n(c) It\nsuggested the abolition of bicameral Legislature at the\ncentre.\n\n(d) It recommended\nthe\ncreation\nof Indian\nPolice\nService\nwith the provision for increased\npay\nand\nallowances for\nBritish recruits as compared to Indian recruits.",
    "answer": "\n(a) It recommends the replacement of Dyarchy with\nresponsible government in the provinces",
    "topic": "Simon Commission and Poorna Swaraj",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_044dc9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to Simon Commission's recommendations, which one of the following statements is correct?\n\na) It recommends the replacement of Dyarchy with responsible government in the provinces\n\nb) It proposed the setting up of inter provincial council under the Home Department\n\nc) It suggested the abolition of bicameral Legislature at the centre\n\nd) It recommended the creation of Indian Police Service with the provision for increased pay and allowances for British recruits as compared to Indian recruits",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under whose Presidency was the Lahore Session of the Indian\nNational Congress\nheld\nin\n1929\nwherein\na\nresolution\nwas\nadopted to\ncomplete Independence from the British?\n\n(a) Bal Gangadhar Tilak\n\n(b) Gopal Krishna Gokhale\n\n(c) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n(d) Motilal Nehru\nAnswer: \n(c) Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "choices": "\n(a) Bal Gangadhar Tilak\n\n(b) Gopal Krishna Gokhale\n\n(c) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\n(d) Motilal Nehru",
    "answer": "\n(c) Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "topic": "Simon Commission and Poorna Swaraj",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_044dc9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Under whose Presidency was the Lahore Session of the Indian National Congress held in 1929 wherein a resolution was adopted to complete Independence from the British?\n\na) Bal Gangadhar Tilak\n\nb) Gopal Krishna Gokhale\n\nc) Jawaharlal Nehru\n\nd) Motilal Nehru",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "gain\nThe people of India agitated against the arrival of the Simon\nCommission because\n\n(a) Indians never wanted the review of the working of the\nAct of 1919\n\n(b) Simon\nCommission\nrecommended\nthe\nabolition\nof\nDyarchy (Diarchy) in the provinces\n\n(c) there was no Indian member in the Simon Commission\n\n(d) the Simon Commission suggested the\npartition of the\ncountry\nAnswer: \n(c) there\nwas\nno\nIndian\nmember\nin\nthe\nSimon\nCommission",
    "choices": "\n(a) Indians never wanted the review of the working of the\nAct of 1919\n\n(b) Simon\nCommission\nrecommended\nthe\nabolition\nof\nDyarchy (Diarchy) in the provinces\n\n(c) there was no Indian member in the Simon Commission\n\n(d) the Simon Commission suggested the\npartition of the\ncountry",
    "answer": "\n(c) there\nwas\nno\nIndian\nmember\nin\nthe\nSimon\nCommission",
    "topic": "Simon Commission and Poorna Swaraj",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_044dc9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The people of India agitated against the arrival of the Simon Commission because\n\na) Indians never wanted the review of the working of the Act of 1919\n\nb) Simon Commission recommended the abolition of Dyarchy (Diarchy) in the provinces\n\nc) there was no Indian member in the Simon Commission\n\nd) the Simon Commission suggested the partition of the country",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Lahore Session of the Indian National Congress (1929) is\nvery important in history, because\n\n1. The Congress passed\na\nresolution demanding complete\nindependence:\n\n2. The\nrift\nbetween\nthe\nextremists\nand\nmoderates\nwas\nresolved in that Session.\n\n3.A resolution was passed rejecting the tWo-nation theory in\nthat Session:\nWhich of the statement(s) given above islare correct?\n\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n1 and 3 only\n\n(d) None of the above\nAnswer: \n(a) 1 only",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only\n1 and 3 only\n\n(d) None of the above",
    "answer": "\n(a) 1 only",
    "topic": "Simon Commission and Poorna Swaraj",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_044dc9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Lahore Session of the Indian National Congress (1929) is very important in history, because \n\n\n1. The Congress passed a resolution demanding complete independence: \n\n\n2. The rift between the extremists and moderates was resolved in that Session. \n\n\n3. A resolution was passed rejecting the tWo-nation theory in that Session: \n\nWhich of the statement(s) given above islare correct? \n\n\n(a) 1 only \n\n\n(b) 2 and 3 only  \n\n1 and 3 only \n\n\n(d) None of the above",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nThe\n1929\nSession\nof\nthe\nIndian\nNational\nCongress\nis\nof\nsignificance in the history of the Freedom Movement because\nthe\n\n(a) attainment\nof Self-Government\nwas\ndeclared\nas the\nobjective of the Congress\n\n(b) attainment of Poorna Swaraj was adopted as the goal\nof the Congress\n\n(c) Non-Cooperation Movement was\nlaunched\n\n(d) the\ndecision\nto\nparticipate\nin\nthe\nRound\nTable\nConference in London was taken\nAnswer: \n(b) attainment of Poorna Swaraj was adopted as the\ngoal of the Congress",
    "choices": "\n(a) attainment\nof Self-Government\nwas\ndeclared\nas the\nobjective of the Congress\n\n(b) attainment of Poorna Swaraj was adopted as the goal\nof the Congress\n\n(c) Non-Cooperation Movement was\nlaunched\n\n(d) the\ndecision\nto\nparticipate\nin\nthe\nRound\nTable\nConference in London was taken",
    "answer": "\n(b) attainment of Poorna Swaraj was adopted as the\ngoal of the Congress",
    "topic": "Simon Commission and Poorna Swaraj",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_044dc9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The 1929 Session of the Indian National Congress is of significance in the history of the Freedom Movement because the\n\na) attainment of Self-Government was declared as the objective of the Congress\n\nb) attainment of Poorna Swaraj was adopted as the goal of the Congress\n\nc) Non-Cooperation Movement was launched\n\nd) the decision to participate in the Round Table Conference in London was taken",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "On\n31st\nDecember;\n1929,\nin\nwhich\none\nof\nthe  following\nCongress Sessions was proclamation of Purna Swaraj made?\n\na)Ahmedabad\n\nb)Calcutta\n\nc) Lahore\n\nd)Lucknow\nAnswer: \n(c) Lahore",
    "choices": "a)Ahmedabad\n\nb)Calcutta\n\nc) Lahore\n\nd)Lucknow",
    "answer": "\n(c) Lahore",
    "topic": "Simon Commission and Poorna Swaraj",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_044dc9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "On 31st December; 1929, in which one of the following Congress Sessions was proclamation of Purna Swaraj made?\n\n\na) Ahmedabad\n\nb) Calcutta\n\nc) Lahore\n\nd) Lucknow",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the year 1928,\na committee of Congress leaders drafted\na\nConstitution for India: The Committee was headed by\n\na) Mahatma Gandhi\n\nb)T: B. Sapru\n\nc) Motilal Nehru\n\nd)Jawaharlal Nehru\nAnswer: \n(c) Motilal Nehru",
    "choices": "a) Mahatma Gandhi\n\nb)T: B. Sapru\n\nc) Motilal Nehru\n\nd)Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "answer": "\n(c) Motilal Nehru",
    "topic": "Simon Commission and Poorna Swaraj",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_044dc9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In the year 1928, a committee of Congress leaders drafted a Constitution for India: The Committee was headed by \n\na) Mahatma Gandhi\n\nb) T: B. Sapru\n\nc) Motilal Nehru\n\nd) Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the Deccan Riots of\n1875 is/are true?\n\n1. The\nDeccan\nRiots\nresulted\nin\nprotection\nfor\npeasants\nthrough the Deccan Agriculturalists Relief Act of 1879.\n\n2. The\nriots\ndid\nnot spread\nto\nthe\nwhole\nof\nMaharashtra\nbecause of prompt suppression\nthe British.\n\n3.The\nBritish\nwere\nunable\nto\ncontain\nthe riots,\nand they\nspread throughout Maharashtra:\n\n4. The cotton boom in the Deccan that had been caused by the\nartificial\ndemand\ngenerated\nby\nthe\nAmerican\nCivil\nWar\ncaused the impoverishment of the peasants.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 3\n\nc) 2 and 4 only\n\nd)1,2 and 4\nAnswer: \n(d) 1,2 and 4",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 3\n\nc) 2 and 4 only\n\nd)1,2 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1,2 and 4",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the Deccan Riots of 1875 is/are true?\n\n1. The Deccan Riots resulted in protection for peasants through the Deccan Agriculturalists Relief Act of 1879.\n\n2. The riots did not spread to the whole of Maharashtra because of prompt suppression the British.\n\n3. The British were unable to contain the riots, and they spread throughout Maharashtra:\n\n4. The cotton boom in the Deccan that had been caused by the artificial demand generated by the American Civil War caused the impoverishment of the peasants.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 3\n\nc) 2 and 4 only\n\nd) 1,2 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "After\nthe\nSanthal\nUprising\nsubsided,\nwhat\nwere\nthe\nmeasure/measures taken by the colonial government?\n\n1. The territories called 'Santhal Parganas'\nwere created:\n\n2. It became illegal for a Santhal to transfer\nland to\na\nnon-\nSanthal:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) Both 1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1\nonly\n\n(b) 2 only\n\n(c) Both 1 and 2\n\n(d) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "After the Santhal Uprising subsided, what were the measure/measures taken by the colonial government?\n\n1. The territories called 'Santhal Parganas' were created:\n\n2. It became illegal for a Santhal to transfer land to a non-Santhal:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nIndigo cultivation in India declined by the beginning of the\ncentury because of:\n\n(a) peasant\nresistance\nto\nthe\noppressive\nconduct\nof\nplanters\n\n(b) its unprofitability in the world market\nbecause of new\ninventions\n\n(c) national leaders' opposition to the cultivation of indigo\n\n(d) Government control over the planters\nAnswer: \n(b) its unprofitability in the world market because of\nnew inventions",
    "choices": "\n(a) peasant\nresistance\nto\nthe\noppressive\nconduct\nof\nplanters\n\n(b) its unprofitability in the world market\nbecause of new\ninventions\n\n(c) national leaders' opposition to the cultivation of indigo\n\n(d) Government control over the planters",
    "answer": "\n(b) its unprofitability in the world market because of\nnew inventions",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Indigo cultivation in India declined by the beginning of the century because of:\n\n\na) peasant resistance to the oppressive conduct of planters\n\nb) its unprofitability in the world market because of new inventions\n\nc) national leaders' opposition to the cultivation of indigo\n\nd) Government control over the planters",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to the history of India, \"Ulgulan\" or the Great\nTumult is the description of which of the following events?\n\n(a) The Revolt of 1857\n\n(b) The Mappila Rebellion of 1921\n\n(c) The Indigo Revolt of 1859-60\n\n(d) Birsa Munda's Revolt of 1899-1900\nAnswer: \n(d) Birsa Munda's Revolt of 1899-1900",
    "choices": "\n(a) The Revolt of 1857\n\n(b) The Mappila Rebellion of 1921\n\n(c) The Indigo Revolt of 1859-60\n\n(d) Birsa Munda's Revolt of 1899-1900",
    "answer": "\n(d) Birsa Munda's Revolt of 1899-1900",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "With reference to the history of India, \"Ulgulan\" or the Great Tumult is the description of which of the following events?\n\n\na) The Revolt of 1857\n\n\nb) The Mappila Rebellion of 1921\n\n\nc) The Indigo Revolt of 1859-60\n\n\nd) Birsa Munda's Revolt of 1899-1900\n",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "20th\nConsider the following statements about the Santhal Hool of\n1855-56:\n\n1. The Santhals were in\na\ndesperate situation\nas tribal lands\nwere leased out\n\n2. The Santhal rebels\nwere treated very leniently by British\nofficials\n\n3.Santhal\ninhabited\nareas\nwere\neventually constituted\ninto\nseparate administrative units called Santhal Parganas\n\n4.The Santhal rebellion\nwas the only major rebellion in mid\n19th century India\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 and 3\n\nc) 1,3 and 4\n\nd)1 and 3 only\nAnswer: \n(d) 1 and 3 only",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 and 3\n\nc) 1,3 and 4\n\nd)1 and 3 only",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements about the Santhal Hool of 1855-56:\n\n\n1. The Santhals were in a desperate situation as tribal lands were leased out\n\n2. The Santhal rebels were treated very leniently by British officials\n\n3. Santhal inhabited areas were eventually constituted into separate administrative units called Santhal Parganas\n\n4. The Santhal rebellion was the only major rebellion in mid 19th century India\n\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 and 3\n\nc) 1,3 and 4\n\nd) 1 and 3 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is/are the characteristic of the Sannyasi\nand Fakir uprisings?\n\n1. These uprisings refer to a series of skirmishes between the\nEnglish\nEast India Company and\na\ngroup of sannyasis and\nfakirs.\n\n2.One\nreason\nfor\nthe\nuprising\nwas\nthe\nban\non\nthe\nfree\nmovement of the sannyasis along pilgrimage routes:\n\n3.In\nthe\ncourse\nof the uprisings\nin\n1773,\nWarren Hastings\nissued\na\nproclamation banishing all sannyasis from Bengal\nand Bihar\n\n4.Are\ncontemporaneous\nwith\nthe\nNon-Cooperation\nMovement\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)1 and 3 only\n\nc) 1,2 and 3\n\nd)2 and 4 only\nAnswer: \n(c) 1,2 and 3",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)1 and 3 only\n\nc) 1,2 and 3\n\nd)2 and 4 only",
    "answer": "\n(c) 1,2 and 3",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following is/are the characteristic of the Sannyasi and Fakir uprisings?\n\n\n1. These uprisings refer to a series of skirmishes between the English East India Company and a group of sannyasis and fakirs.\n\n2. One reason for the uprising was the ban on the free movement of the sannyasis along pilgrimage routes:\n\n3. In the course of the uprisings in 1773, Warren Hastings issued a proclamation banishing all sannyasis from Bengal and Bihar\n\n4. Are contemporaneous with the Non-Cooperation Movement\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 1 and 3 only\n\nc) 1,2 and 3\n\nd) 2 and 4 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the Sanyasi and Faqir\ndisturbances/rebellions are correct?\n\n1. Governor-General\nWarren\nHastings\nfaced\nthe\npersistent\nSanyasi and Faqir disturbances in Bengal and Bihar:\n\n2. There were a number of Shaivite Naga Sanyasis who formed\ninto armed bands.\n\n3. Majnu Shah,\nwho led bands into Bengal from 1771,\nwas\ntheir prominent leader:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below :\n\na) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)1,2 and 3\nand 3 only\n\nd) 1 and 3 only\nAnswer: \n(b) 1,2 and 3",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 2 only\n\nb)1,2 and 3\nand 3 only\n\nd) 1 and 3 only",
    "answer": "\n(b) 1,2 and 3",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the Sanyasi and Faqir disturbances/rebellions are correct? \n\n\n1. Governor-General Warren Hastings faced the persistent Sanyasi and Faqir disturbances in Bengal and Bihar: \n\n2. There were a number of Shaivite Naga Sanyasis who formed into armed bands. \n\n3. Majnu Shah, who led bands into Bengal from 1771, was their prominent leader: \n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below : \n\n\na) 1 and 2 only \n\nb) 1,2 and 3 \nand 3 only \n\nd) 1 and 3 only",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dinabandhu\nMitra   published\na\nplay\nin\nBengali\ntitled\nNeel\nDarpan\n(Blue\nMirror),\nwhich depicted the atrocities\non\nthe\nindigo planters: The play was translated into English by :\n\na) Reverend James Long\n\nb) Dwarkanath Tagore\n\nc) Michael Madhusudan Dutta\n\nd) Rabindranath Tagore\nAnswer: \n(c) Michael Madhusudan Dutta",
    "choices": "a) Reverend James Long\n\nb) Dwarkanath Tagore\n\nc) Michael Madhusudan Dutta\n\nd) Rabindranath Tagore",
    "answer": "\n(c) Michael Madhusudan Dutta",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Dinabandhu Mitra published a play in Bengali titled Neel Darpan (Blue Mirror), which depicted the atrocities on the indigo planters: The play was translated into English by: \n\na) Reverend James Long \n\nb) Dwarkanath Tagore \n\nc) Michael Madhusudan Dutta \n\nd) Rabindranath Tagore",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nof the following statements about the\nDeccan\nRiots\nCommission is/are correct?\n\n1.The Commission did not hold enquiries in the districts which\nwere not affected.\n\n2. The\nCommission\ndid\nrecord\nthe\nstatements\nof\nryots,\nsahukars and eve-witnesses\nSelect the correct answer\nusing the code given below :\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(B) 2 only",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(B) 2 only",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following statements about the Deccan Riots Commission is/are correct?\n\n1. The Commission did not hold enquiries in the districts which were not affected. \n\n2. The Commission did record the statements of ryots, sahukars and eve-witnesses. \nSelect the correct answer using the code given below :\n\na) 1 only \n\nb) 2 only \n\nc) Both 1 and 2 \n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "B"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following provided\na\ncommon factor for tribal\ninsurrection in India in the\ncentury?\n\n(a) Introduction\nof\na\nnew\nsystem\nof land\nrevenue and\ntaxation- of tribal products\n\n(b) Influence\nof foreign\nreligious\nmissionaries\nin\ntribal\nareas\n\n(c) Rise of a large number of money lenders, traders and\nrevenue farmers as\nmiddlemen in tribal areas\n\n(d) The complete disruption of the old\nagrarian order of\nthe tribal communities\nAnswer: \n(d) The complete disruption of the old agrarian order\nof the tribal communities",
    "choices": "\n(a) Introduction\nof\na\nnew\nsystem\nof land\nrevenue and\ntaxation- of tribal products\n\n(b) Influence\nof foreign\nreligious\nmissionaries\nin\ntribal\nareas\n\n(c) Rise of a large number of money lenders, traders and\nrevenue farmers as\nmiddlemen in tribal areas\n\n(d) The complete disruption of the old\nagrarian order of\nthe tribal communities",
    "answer": "\n(d) The complete disruption of the old agrarian order\nof the tribal communities",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following provided a common factor for tribal insurrection in India in the century?\n\na) Introduction of a new system of land revenue and taxation- of tribal products\n\nb) Influence of foreign religious missionaries in tribal areas\n\nc) Rise of a large number of money lenders, traders and revenue farmers as middlemen in tribal areas\n\nd) The complete disruption of the old agrarian order of the tribal communities",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "19th\nConsider the following statements:\n\n1.In the\ncentury, peasants in various parts of India rose in\nrevolt against moneylenders and grain dealers.\n\n2. In May 1875,at village Supa in Poona District in the Bombay\nDeccan, peasants\nattacked shopkeepers,\nburned\nthe\nbahi\nkhatas (account books), looted grain shops and set fire to\nthe houses of Sahukars.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2\nAnswer: \n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "19th\nConsider the following statements:\n\n1. In the century, peasants in various parts of India rose in revolt against moneylenders and grain dealers. \n\n2. In May 1875, at village Supa in Poona District in the Bombay Deccan, peasants attacked shopkeepers, burned the bahi khatas (account books), looted grain shops and set fire to the houses of Sahukars. \nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n\n\na) 1 only\n\nb) 2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "19th\nWhich\none\nof the following\nrevolts\nwas\nmade famous\nby\nBankim Chandra Chatterjee in his novel Anand Math?\n\n(a) Bhil Uprising\n\n(b) Rangpur and Dinapur Uprising\n\n(c) Bishnupur and Birbhum rebellion\n\n(d) Sanyasi rebellion\nAnswer: \n(d) Sanyasi rebellion",
    "choices": "\n(a) Bhil Uprising\n\n(b) Rangpur and Dinapur Uprising\n\n(c) Bishnupur and Birbhum rebellion\n\n(d) Sanyasi rebellion",
    "answer": "\n(d) Sanyasi rebellion",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "19th Which one of the following revolts was made famous by Bankim Chandra Chatterjee in his novel Anand Math?\n\na) Bhil Uprising\n\nb) Rangpur and Dinapur Uprising\n\nc) Bishnupur and Birbhum rebellion\n\nd) Sanyasi rebellion",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which one of the following revolts did the Koya and Konda\ntribal chiefs rise against the local overlord from a Mansabdar\nfamily?\n\na) The Rampa Rebellion, 1879-1880\n\nb) The Gudem Uprising, 1886\n\nc) The Rampa Rebellion, 1922-1924\n\nd) The Telangana Armed Struggle, 1946-1951\nAnswer: \n(a) The Rampa Rebellion, 1879-1880",
    "choices": "a) The Rampa Rebellion, 1879-1880\n\nb) The Gudem Uprising, 1886\n\nc) The Rampa Rebellion, 1922-1924\n\nd) The Telangana Armed Struggle, 1946-1951",
    "answer": "\n(a) The Rampa Rebellion, 1879-1880",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In which one of the following revolts did the Koya and Konda tribal chiefs rise against the local overlord from a Mansabdar family?\n\n\na) The Rampa Rebellion, 1879-1880\n\nb) The Gudem Uprising, 1886\n\nc) The Rampa Rebellion, 1922-1924\n\nd) The Telangana Armed Struggle, 1946-1951",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "The\nDeccan Agriculturalists' Relief Act of 1879\nwas enacted\nwith which one of the following objectives?\n\na) Restore lands to the dispossessed peasants\n\nb)Ensure financial assistance to peasants during social and\nreligious occasions\n\nc) Restrict the sale of land for indebtedness to outsiders\n\nd) Give legal aid to insolvent peasants\nAnswer: \n(c)",
    "choices": "a) Restore lands to the dispossessed peasants\n\nb)Ensure financial assistance to peasants during social and\nreligious occasions\n\nc) Restrict the sale of land for indebtedness to outsiders\n\nd) Give legal aid to insolvent peasants",
    "answer": "\n(c) Restrict\nthe\nsale\nof\nland\nfor\nindebtedness\nto\noutside",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Deccan Agriculturalists' Relief Act of 1879 was enacted with which one of the following objectives? \n\n\n(a) Restore lands to the dispossessed peasants \n\n\n(b)Ensure financial assistance to peasants during social and religious occasions \n\n\n(c) Restrict the sale of land for indebtedness to outsiders \n\n\n(d) Give legal aid to insolvent peasants",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "The\nDamin-i-Koh\nwas created by the British Government to\nsettle which one of the following communities?\n\na) Santhals\n\nb)Mundas\n\nc) Oraons\n\nd) Saoras\nAnswer: \n(a) Santhals",
    "choices": "a) Santhals\n\nb)Mundas\n\nc) Oraons\n\nd) Saoras",
    "answer": "\n(a) Santhals",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Damin-i-Koh was created by the British Government to settle which one of the following communities?\n\na) Santhals\n\nb) Mundas\n\nc) Oraons\n\nd) Saoras",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which one of the following years did the British demarcate a\nlarge area of land as Damin-i-koh for settling the Santhals?\n\na)1810\n6)1793\n\nc) 1885\n\nd) 1832\nAnswer: \n(d) 1832",
    "choices": "a)1810\n6)1793\n\nc) 1885\n\nd) 1832",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1832",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In which one of the following years did the British demarcate a large area of land as Damin-i-koh for settling the Santhals?\n\na) 1810\n\nb) 1793\n\nc) 1885\n\nd) 1832",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was Damin-i Koh in Rajmahal area?\n\na)A large area of land demarcated and declared to be the land\nof the Santhals\n\nb) The land ofthe Paharias cultivated exclusively for paddy\n\nc) The British territory marked for their military camp\n\nd) The land earmarked for locating settled agriculturists\nAnswer: \n(a) A large area of land demarcated and declared to be\nthe land of the Santhals",
    "choices": "a)A large area of land demarcated and declared to be the land\nof the Santhals\n\nb) The land ofthe Paharias cultivated exclusively for paddy\n\nc) The British territory marked for their military camp\n\nd) The land earmarked for locating settled agriculturists",
    "answer": "\n(a) A large area of land demarcated and declared to be\nthe land of the Santhals",
    "topic": "Tribal and Peasant Movements - 1",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_6__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "What was Damin-i Koh in Rajmahal area?\n\n\na)A large area of land demarcated and declared to be the land of the Santhals\n\nb) The land ofthe Paharias cultivated exclusively for paddy\n\nc) The British territory marked for their military camp\n\nd) The land earmarked for locating settled agriculturists",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following historical events in India carefully:\n\n1. The Indian\npress failed\nto protest against the\nVernacular\nPress Act of 1878.\n\n2. The Vernacular Press Act of 1878 was introduced by Viceroy\nLytton against the counsel of his own Law Member\nWhich of the above is/are correct?\n\na) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n\nb)2 only\n\nc) Both 1 and 2\n\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "\n(b) 2 only",
    "topic": "Development of Indian Press under British Rule",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following historical events in India carefully: \n\n1. The Indian press failed to protest against the Vernacular Press Act of 1878. \n\n2. The Vernacular Press Act of 1878 was introduced by Viceroy Lytton against the counsel of his own Law Member Which of the above is/are correct? \n\na) 1 only \n\nb) 2 only \n\nc) Both 1 and 2 \n\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following founded the Marathi newspaper\n'Kesari'?",
    "choices": "a) Lokmanya Tilak\n\nb) Vallabhbhai Patel\n\nc) Lala Lajpat Rai\n\nd) Mahatma Gandhi",
    "answer": "\n(a) Lokmanya Tilak",
    "topic": "Development of Indian Press under British Rule",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the following founded the Marathi newspaper 'Kesari'?",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the editor of the journal Indian Social Reformer that\nwas started in 1890?",
    "choices": "a)K: T Telang\n\nb) Veeresalingam\n\nc) N: G. Chandavarkar\n\nd)K N: Natarajan",
    "answer": "\n(d) K N: Natarajan",
    "topic": "Development of Indian Press under British Rule",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who was the editor of the journal Indian Social Reformer that was started in 1890?",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Match List\nwith List Il and select the correct answer using the\ncode given below the Lists:\nList | (Editor)\nList II (Journal/ Newspaper)\nA.S.A. Dange\n\n1. Labour-Kisan Gazette\nB. Muzaffar Ahmed\n\n2. Inquilab\nC.Ghulam Hussain\n\n3. Navayug\nD.M: Singaravelu\n4,The Socialist\nCode\n'\nABCD\n\na)4231\n\nb)4321\n\nc) 1234\n\nd)1324",
    "choices": "a)4231\n\nb)4321\n\nc) 1234\n\nd)1324",
    "answer": "\n(b) 4321",
    "topic": "Development of Indian Press under British Rule",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Match List with List Il and select the correct answer using the code given below the Lists: \nList | (Editor) List II (Journal/ Newspaper) \nA. S. A. Dange 1. Labour-Kisan Gazette \nB. Muzaffar Ahmed 2. Inquilab \nC. Ghulam Hussain 3. Navayug \nD. M: Singaravelu 4,The Socialist \nCode \nABCD \n\na) 4231 \n\nb) 4321 \n\nc) 1234 \n\nd) 1324",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nWho\namong\nthe  following\nstarted\nthe\nnewspaper\nShome\nPrakash?\n\n(a) Dayanand Saraswati\n\n(b) Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar\n\n(c) Raja Ram Mohan\n\n(d) Surendranath Banerjee",
    "choices": "\n(a) Dayanand Saraswati\n\n(b) Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar\n\n(c) Raja Ram Mohan\n\n(d) Surendranath Banerjee",
    "answer": "\n(b) Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar",
    "topic": "Development of Indian Press under British Rule",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Who among the  following started the newspaper Shome Prakash? \n\n\na) Dayanand Saraswati \n\nb) Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar \n\nc) Raja Ram Mohan \n\nd) Surendranath Banerjee",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following pairs of Newspaper and Editor is\nnot correctly matched ?\nNewspaper\nEditor\n\na) Navjivan\nMahatma Gandhi\n\nb) Mahratta\nBal Gangadhar Tilak\nC\nBengalee\nSurendranath Banerjea\n\nd) Voice of India\nGopal Krishna Gokhale",
    "choices": "a) Navjivan\nMahatma Gandhi\n\nb) Mahratta\nBal Gangadhar Tilak\nC\nBengalee\nSurendranath Banerjea\n\nd) Voice of India\nGopal Krishna Gokhale",
    "answer": "\n(d) Voice of India\nGopal Krishna Gokhale",
    "topic": "Development of Indian Press under British Rule",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_9__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which one of the following pairs of Newspaper and Editor is not correctly matched?\nNewspaper Editor\n\na) Navjivan Mahatma Gandhi\n\nb) Mahratta Bal Gangadhar Tilak\nC Bengalee Surendranath Banerjea\n\nd) Voice of India Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the elections to the provincial legislatures in 1937 in British\nIndia\n\n1.only about 10 to 12 percent of the population had the right\nto vote\n\n2.the untouchables had no right to vote\n\n3.the Congress won an absolute majority in five out of eleven\nprovinces\n\n4.the Muslim League won\nmore than 80 percent of the seats\nreserved for Muslims\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1,3 and 4\n\nb) 1 and 4\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd)2,3 and 4\nAnswer: \n(c) 1 and 3 only\nonly",
    "choices": "a) 1,3 and 4\n\nb) 1 and 4\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd)2,3 and 4",
    "answer": "\n(c) 1 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement (1934-39)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1a7f45__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In the elections to the provincial legislatures in 1937 in British India\n\n1. only about 10 to 12 percent of the population had the right to vote\n\n2. the untouchables had no right to vote\n\n3. the Congress won an absolute majority in five out of eleven provinces\n\n4. the Muslim League won more than 80 percent of the seats reserved for Muslims\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n\na) 1,3 and 4\n\nb) 1 and 4\n\nc) 1 and 3 only\n\nd) 2,3 and 4",
    "correct_answer_text": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following was the reason for the resignations of\nthe Indian ministers in all the provinces in 1939?\n\na) The Governors refused to act as constitutional heads\n\nb) The Centre did\nnot provide the required financial help to\nprovinces\n\nc) The\nGovernor-General\nconverted\nIndian\nadministration\nfrom federal to unitary one because of the beginning of the\nSecond World War\n\nd)India was declared a party to the Second World War without\nthe consent of the provincial governments\nAnswer: \n(d) India\nwas declared\na\nparty to the Second World\nWar without the consent of the provincial governments",
    "choices": "a) The Governors refused to act as constitutional heads\n\nb) The Centre did\nnot provide the required financial help to\nprovinces\n\nc) The\nGovernor-General\nconverted\nIndian\nadministration\nfrom federal to unitary one because of the beginning of the\nSecond World War\n\nd)India was declared a party to the Second World War without\nthe consent of the provincial governments",
    "answer": "\n(d) India\nwas declared\na\nparty to the Second World\nWar without the consent of the provincial governments",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement (1934-39)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1a7f45__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Which of the following was the reason for the resignations of the Indian ministers in all the provinces in 1939?\n\na) The Governors refused to act as constitutional heads\n\nb) The Centre did not provide the required financial help to provinces\n\nc) The Governor-General converted Indian administration from federal to unitary one because of the beginning of the Second World War\n\nd) India was declared a party to the Second World War without the consent of the provincial governments",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements: The Government of India\nAct, 1935 provided for\n\n1. The Provincial Autonomy\n\n2. The establishment of the Federal Court\n\n3.All India Federation at the centre\nWhich of the following statements given above are correct?\nChoose the correct answer from the following options:\n\n(a) 1 and 2\n\n(b) 2 and 3\n\n(c) 1 and 3\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3\nAnswer: \n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "choices": "\n(a) 1 and 2\n\n(b) 2 and 3\n\n(c) 1 and 3\n\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "\n(d) 1, 2 and 3",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement (1934-39)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1a7f45__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "Consider the following statements: The Government of India Act, 1935 provided for \n\n\n1. The Provincial Autonomy\n\n2. The establishment of the Federal Court\n\n3. All India Federation at the centre\n\nWhich of the following statements given above are correct?\n\nChoose the correct answer from the following options:\n\n\na) 1 and 2\n\nb) 2 and 3\n\nc) 1 and 3\n\nd) 1, 2 and 3",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "In\nwhich\none\nof\nthe  following   provinces\nwas\na\nCongress\nMinistry not formed under the Act of 1935?\n\n(a) Bihar\n\n(b) Madras\n\n(c) Orissa\n\n(d) Punjab\nAnswer: \n(d) Punjab",
    "choices": "\n(a) Bihar\n\n(b) Madras\n\n(c) Orissa\n\n(d) Punjab",
    "answer": "\n(d) Punjab",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement (1934-39)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1a7f45__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In which one of the following provinces was a Congress Ministry not formed under the Act of 1935?\n\na) Bihar\n\nb) Madras\n\nc) Orissa\n\nd) Punjab",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the election held in 1937, in which two provinces was the\nIndian\nNational Congress\nnot able to\nemerge\nas the single\nlargest party?\n\na) Punjab and Sind\n\nb)Assam and North-West Frontier Province\n\nc) Punjab and Assam\nd\nAssam and Madras\nAnswer: \n(a) Punjab and Sind",
    "choices": "a) Punjab and Sind\n\nb)Assam and North-West Frontier Province\n\nc) Punjab and Assam\nd\nAssam and Madras",
    "answer": "\n(a) Punjab and Sind",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement (1934-39)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1a7f45__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "In the election held in 1937, in which two provinces was the Indian National Congress not able to emerge as the single largest party?\n\na) Punjab and Sind\n\nb)Assam and North-West Frontier Province\n\nc) Punjab and Assam\n\nd)Assam and Madras",
    "correct_answer_text": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nThe Congress\nministries resigned\nin\nthe\nseven\nprovinces in\n1939, because\n\n(a) The Congress could not form\nministries in the other\nfour provinces.\n\n(b) Emergence of a 'left wing' in the\nCongress made the\nworking of the\nministries impossible.\n\n(c) There\nwere\nwidespread\ncommunal\ndisturbances\nin\ntheir provinces:\n\n(d) None of the statements \n(a), \n(b) and \n(c) given above is\ncorrect.\nAnswer: \n(d) None of the statements \n(a), \n(b) and \n(c) given above\nis correct",
    "choices": "\n(a) The Congress could not form\nministries in the other\nfour provinces.\n\n(b) Emergence of a 'left wing' in the\nCongress made the\nworking of the\nministries impossible.\n\n(c) There\nwere\nwidespread\ncommunal\ndisturbances\nin\ntheir provinces:\n\n(d) None of the statements \n(a), \n(b) and \n(c) given above is\ncorrect.",
    "answer": "\n(d) None of the statements \n(a), \n(b) and \n(c) given above\nis correct",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement (1934-39)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1a7f45__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The Congress ministries resigned in the seven provinces in 1939, because\n\na) The Congress could not form ministries in the other four provinces.\n\nb) Emergence of a 'left wing' in the Congress made the working of the ministries impossible.\n\nc) There were widespread communal disturbances in their provinces:\n\nd) None of the statements \n(a), \n(b) and \n(c) given above is correct.",
    "correct_answer_text": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "The\nfollowing item\nconsists\nof statements: Statement\n7\nand\nStatement\nIl: Examine\nthese\ntwo\nstatements  carefully\nand\nselect the correct answer using the code below:\nCode:\n\na)Both statements are individually true, and Statement\nIlL is\nthe correct explanation of Statement /\n\nb)Both the statements are individually true, and Statement II\nis NOT the correct explanation of Statement |\n\nc) Statement\nis true, but Statement II is false\n\nd)Statement\nis false, but Statement Il is true\nStatement #: The Kisan manifesto adopted by the All India Kisan\nSabha in August 1936 contained radical demands\nStatement\nII:\nThe\nAll\nIndia\nKisan\nSabha\nwas\na\npart of\nthe\nCongress and maintained a close relationship with the Provincial\nCongress Committees\nAnswer:\n\n(b) Both\nstatements\nare\nindividually\ntrue,\nand\nStatement II is the correct explanation of Statement |",
    "choices": "a)Both statements are individually true, and Statement\nIlL is\nthe correct explanation of Statement /\n\nb)Both the statements are individually true, and Statement II\nis NOT the correct explanation of Statement |\n\nc) Statement\nis true, but Statement II is false\n\nd)Statement\nis false, but Statement Il is true",
    "answer": "\n(b) Both\nstatements\nare\nindividually\ntrue,\nand\nStatement II is the correct explanation of Statement |",
    "topic": "Nationalist Movement (1934-39)",
    "originalPath": "files3/Doc7_1a7f45__combined.json",
    "cleaned_question": "The following item consists of statements: Statement 7 and Statement Il: Examine these two statements carefully and select the correct answer using the code below:\nCode:\n\na) Both statements are individually true, and Statement IlL is the correct explanation of Statement /\n\nb) Both the statements are individually true, and Statement II is NOT the correct explanation of Statement |\n\nc) Statement is true, but Statement II is false\n\nd) Statement is false, but Statement Il is true\nStatement #: The Kisan manifesto adopted by the All India Kisan Sabha in August 1936 contained radical demands\nStatement II: The All India Kisan Sabha was a part of the Congress and maintained a close relationship with the Provincial Congress Committees",
    "correct_answer_text": "b"
  }
]